<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Junkman]]></title>
  <link href="http://panlw.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://panlw.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-10T23:47:47+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://panlw.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://www.mweb.im/">MWeb</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java 8 Concurrency Tutorial: Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15358820607055.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T17:54:20+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15358820607055.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/">https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welcome to the third part of my tutorial series about multi-threaded programming in Java 8. This tutorial covers two important parts of the Concurrency API: Atomic Variables and Concurrent Maps. Both have been greatly improved with the introduction of lambda expressions and functional programming in the latest Java 8 release. All those new features are described with a bunch of easily understood code samples. Enjoy!</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: <a href="/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/">Threads and Executors</a></li>
<li>  Part 2: <a href="/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">Synchronization and Locks</a></li>
<li>  Part 3: Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</li>
</ul>

<p>For simplicity the code samples of this tutorial make use of the two helper methods <code>sleep(seconds)</code> and <code>stop(executor)</code> as defined <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial/blob/master/src/com/winterbe/java8/samples/concurrent/ConcurrentUtils.java">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">AtomicInteger<a href="#atomicinteger" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The package <code>java.concurrent.atomic</code> contains many useful classes to perform atomic operations. An operation is atomic when you can safely perform the operation in parallel on multiple threads without using the <code>synchronized</code> keyword or locks as shown in my <a href="/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">previous tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>Internally, the atomic classes make heavy use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compare-and-swap">compare-and-swap</a> (CAS), an atomic instruction directly supported by most modern CPUs. Those instructions usually are much faster than synchronizing via locks. So my advice is to prefer atomic classes over locks in case you just have to change a single mutable variable concurrently.</p>

<p>Now let&#39;s pick one of the atomic classes for a few examples: <code>AtomicInteger</code></p>

<pre><code>AtomicInteger atomicInt = new AtomicInteger(0);

ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 1000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(atomicInt::incrementAndGet));

stop(executor);

System.out.println(atomicInt.get());    // =&gt; 1000

</code></pre>

<p>By using <code>AtomicInteger</code> as a replacement for <code>Integer</code> we&#39;re able to increment the number concurrently in a thread-safe manor without synchronizing the access to the variable. The method <code>incrementAndGet()</code> is an atomic operation so we can safely call this method from multiple threads.</p>

<p>AtomicInteger supports various kinds of atomic operations. The method <code>updateAndGet()</code> accepts a lambda expression in order to perform arbitrary arithmetic operations upon the integer:</p>

<pre><code>AtomicInteger atomicInt = new AtomicInteger(0);

ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 1000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; {
        Runnable task = () -&gt;
            atomicInt.updateAndGet(n -&gt; n + 2);
        executor.submit(task);
    });

stop(executor);

System.out.println(atomicInt.get());    // =&gt; 2000

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>accumulateAndGet()</code> accepts another kind of lambda expression of type <code>IntBinaryOperator</code>. We use this method to sum up all values from 0 to 1000 concurrently in the next sample:</p>

<pre><code>AtomicInteger atomicInt = new AtomicInteger(0);

ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 1000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; {
        Runnable task = () -&gt;
            atomicInt.accumulateAndGet(i, (n, m) -&gt; n + m);
        executor.submit(task);
    });

stop(executor);

System.out.println(atomicInt.get());    // =&gt; 499500

</code></pre>

<p>Other useful atomic classes are <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/atomic/AtomicBoolean.html">AtomicBoolean</a>, <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/atomic/AtomicLong.html">AtomicLong</a> and <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/atomic/AtomicReference.html">AtomicReference</a>.</p>

<h3 id="toc_1">LongAdder<a href="#longadder" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The class <code>LongAdder</code> as an alternative to <code>AtomicLong</code> can be used to consecutively add values to a number.</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 1000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(adder::increment));

stop(executor);

System.out.println(adder.sumThenReset());   // =&gt; 1000

</code></pre>

<p>LongAdder provides methods <code>add()</code> and <code>increment()</code> just like the atomic number classes and is also thread-safe. But instead of summing up a single result this class maintains a set of variables internally to reduce contention over threads. The actual result can be retrieved by calling <code>sum()</code> or <code>sumThenReset()</code>.</p>

<p>This class is usually preferable over atomic numbers when updates from multiple threads are more common than reads. This is often the case when capturing statistical data, e.g. you want to count the number of requests served on a web server. The drawback of <code>LongAdder</code> is higher memory consumption because a set of variables is held in-memory.</p>

<h3 id="toc_2">LongAccumulator<a href="#longaccumulator" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>LongAccumulator is a more generalized version of LongAdder. Instead of performing simple add operations the class <code>LongAccumulator</code> builds around a lambda expression of type <code>LongBinaryOperator</code> as demonstrated in this code sample:</p>

<pre><code>LongBinaryOperator op = (x, y) -&gt; 2 * x + y;
LongAccumulator accumulator = new LongAccumulator(op, 1L);

ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 10)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(() -&gt; accumulator.accumulate(i)));

stop(executor);

System.out.println(accumulator.getThenReset());     // =&gt; 2539

</code></pre>

<p>We create a LongAccumulator with the function <code>2 * x + y</code> and an initial value of one. With every call to <code>accumulate(i)</code> both the current result and the value <code>i</code> are passed as parameters to the lambda expression.</p>

<p>A <code>LongAccumulator</code> just like <code>LongAdder</code> maintains a set of variables internally to reduce contention over threads.</p>

<h3 id="toc_3">ConcurrentMap<a href="#concurrentmap" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The interface <code>ConcurrentMap</code> extends the map interface and defines one of the most useful concurrent collection types. Java 8 introduces functional programming by adding new methods to this interface.</p>

<p>In the next code snippets we use the following sample map to demonstrates those new methods:</p>

<pre><code>ConcurrentMap&lt;String, String&gt; map = new ConcurrentHashMap&lt;&gt;();
map.put(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;);
map.put(&quot;han&quot;, &quot;solo&quot;);
map.put(&quot;r2&quot;, &quot;d2&quot;);
map.put(&quot;c3&quot;, &quot;p0&quot;);

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>forEach()</code> accepts a lambda expression of type <code>BiConsumer</code> with both the key and value of the map passed as parameters. It can be used as a replacement to for-each loops to iterate over the entries of the concurrent map. The iteration is performed sequentially on the current thread.</p>

<pre><code>map.forEach((key, value) -&gt; System.out.printf(&quot;%s = %s\n&quot;, key, value));

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>putIfAbsent()</code> puts a new value into the map only if no value exists for the given key. At least for the <code>ConcurrentHashMap</code> implementation of this method is thread-safe just like <code>put()</code> so you don&#39;t have to synchronize when accessing the map concurrently from different threads:</p>

<pre><code>String value = map.putIfAbsent(&quot;c3&quot;, &quot;p1&quot;);
System.out.println(value);    // p0

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>getOrDefault()</code> returns the value for the given key. In case no entry exists for this key the passed default value is returned:</p>

<pre><code>String value = map.getOrDefault(&quot;hi&quot;, &quot;there&quot;);
System.out.println(value);    // there

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>replaceAll()</code> accepts a lambda expression of type <code>BiFunction</code>. BiFunctions take two parameters and return a single value. In this case the function is called with the key and the value of each map entry and returns a new value to be assigned for the current key:</p>

<pre><code>map.replaceAll((key, value) -&gt; &quot;r2&quot;.equals(key) ? &quot;d3&quot; : value);
System.out.println(map.get(&quot;r2&quot;));    // d3

</code></pre>

<p>Instead of replacing all values of the map <code>compute()</code> let&#39;s us transform a single entry. The method accepts both the key to be computed and a bi-function to specify the transformation of the value.</p>

<pre><code>map.compute(&quot;foo&quot;, (key, value) -&gt; value + value);
System.out.println(map.get(&quot;foo&quot;));   // barbar

</code></pre>

<p>In addition to <code>compute()</code> two variants exist: <code>computeIfAbsent()</code> and <code>computeIfPresent()</code>. The functional parameters of these methods only get called if the key is absent or present respectively.</p>

<p>Finally, the method <code>merge()</code> can be utilized to unify a new value with an existing value in the map. Merge accepts a key, the new value to be merged into the existing entry and a bi-function to specify the merging behavior of both values:</p>

<pre><code>map.merge(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;boo&quot;, (oldVal, newVal) -&gt; newVal + &quot; was &quot; + oldVal);
System.out.println(map.get(&quot;foo&quot;));   // boo was foo

</code></pre>

<h3 id="toc_4">ConcurrentHashMap<a href="#concurrenthashmap" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>All those methods above are part of the <code>ConcurrentMap</code> interface, thereby available to all implementations of that interface. In addition the most important implementation <code>ConcurrentHashMap</code> has been further enhanced with a couple of new methods to perform parallel operations upon the map.</p>

<p>Just like parallel streams those methods use a special <code>ForkJoinPool</code> available via <code>ForkJoinPool.commonPool()</code> in Java 8. This pool uses a preset parallelism which depends on the number of available cores. Four CPU cores are available on my machine which results in a parallelism of three:</p>

<pre><code>System.out.println(ForkJoinPool.getCommonPoolParallelism());  // 3

</code></pre>

<p>This value can be decreased or increased by setting the following JVM parameter:</p>

<pre><code>-Djava.util.concurrent.ForkJoinPool.common.parallelism=5

</code></pre>

<p>We use the same example map for demonstrating purposes but this time we work upon the concrete implementation <code>ConcurrentHashMap</code> instead of the interface <code>ConcurrentMap</code>, so we can access all public methods from this class:</p>

<pre><code>ConcurrentHashMap&lt;String, String&gt; map = new ConcurrentHashMap&lt;&gt;();
map.put(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;);
map.put(&quot;han&quot;, &quot;solo&quot;);
map.put(&quot;r2&quot;, &quot;d2&quot;);
map.put(&quot;c3&quot;, &quot;p0&quot;);

</code></pre>

<p>Java 8 introduces three kinds of parallel operations: <code>forEach</code>, <code>search</code> and <code>reduce</code>. Each of those operations are available in four forms accepting functions with keys, values, entries and key-value pair arguments.</p>

<p>All of those methods use a common first argument called <code>parallelismThreshold</code>. This threshold indicates the minimum collection size when the operation should be executed in parallel. E.g. if you pass a threshold of 500 and the actual size of the map is 499 the operation will be performed sequentially on a single thread. In the next examples we use a threshold of one to always force parallel execution for demonstrating purposes.</p>

<h4 id="toc_5">ForEach<a href="#foreach" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The method <code>forEach()</code> is capable of iterating over the key-value pairs of the map in parallel. The lambda expression of type <code>BiConsumer</code> is called with the key and value of the current iteration step. In order to visualize parallel execution we print the current threads name to the console. Keep in mind that in my case the underlying <code>ForkJoinPool</code> uses up to a maximum of three threads.</p>

<pre><code>map.forEach(1, (key, value) -&gt;
    System.out.printf(&quot;key: %s; value: %s; thread: %s\n&quot;,
        key, value, Thread.currentThread().getName()));

// key: r2; value: d2; thread: main
// key: foo; value: bar; thread: ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1
// key: han; value: solo; thread: ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2
// key: c3; value: p0; thread: main

</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_6">Search<a href="#search" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The method <code>search()</code> accepts a <code>BiFunction</code> returning a non-null search result for the current key-value pair or <code>null</code> if the current iteration doesn&#39;t match the desired search criteria. As soon as a non-null result is returned further processing is suppressed. Keep in mind that <code>ConcurrentHashMap</code> is unordered. The search function should not depend on the actual processing order of the map. If multiple entries of the map match the given search function the result may be non-deterministic.</p>

<pre><code>String result = map.search(1, (key, value) -&gt; {
    System.out.println(Thread.currentThread().getName());
    if (&quot;foo&quot;.equals(key)) {
        return value;
    }
    return null;
});
System.out.println(&quot;Result: &quot; + result);

// ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2
// main
// ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3
// Result: bar

</code></pre>

<p>Here&#39;s another example searching solely on the values of the map:</p>

<pre><code>String result = map.searchValues(1, value -&gt; {
    System.out.println(Thread.currentThread().getName());
    if (value.length() &gt; 3) {
        return value;
    }
    return null;
});

System.out.println(&quot;Result: &quot; + result);

// ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2
// main
// main
// ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1
// Result: solo

</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_7">Reduce<a href="#reduce" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The method <code>reduce()</code> already known from Java 8 Streams accepts two lambda expressions of type <code>BiFunction</code>. The first function transforms each key-value pair into a single value of any type. The second function combines all those transformed values into a single result, ignoring any possible <code>null</code> values.</p>

<pre><code>String result = map.reduce(1,
    (key, value) -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;Transform: &quot; + Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return key + &quot;=&quot; + value;
    },
    (s1, s2) -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;Reduce: &quot; + Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return s1 + &quot;, &quot; + s2;
    });

System.out.println(&quot;Result: &quot; + result);

// Transform: ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2
// Transform: main
// Transform: ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3
// Reduce: ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3
// Transform: main
// Reduce: main
// Reduce: main
// Result: r2=d2, c3=p0, han=solo, foo=bar

</code></pre>

<p>I hope you&#39;ve enjoyed reading the third part of my tutorial series about Java 8 Concurrency. The code samples from this tutorial are <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial">hosted on GitHub</a> along with many other Java 8 code snippets. You&#39;re welcome to fork the repo and try it by your own.</p>

<p>If you want to support my work, please share this tutorial with your friends. You should also <a href="https://twitter.com/winterbe_">follow me on Twitter</a> as I constantly tweet about Java and programming related stuff.</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: <a href="/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/">Threads and Executors</a></li>
<li>  Part 2: <a href="/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">Synchronization and Locks</a></li>
<li>  Part 3: Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java 8 Concurrency Tutorial: Synchronization and Locks]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15358774987730.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T16:38:18+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15358774987730.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welcome to the second part of my Java 8 Concurrency Tutorial out of a series of guides teaching multi-threaded programming in Java 8 with easily understood code examples. In the next 15 min you learn how to synchronize access to mutable shared variables via the synchronized keyword, locks and semaphores.</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: <a href="/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/">Threads and Executors</a></li>
<li>  Part 2: Synchronization and Locks</li>
<li>  Part 3: <a href="/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/">Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The majority of concepts shown in this article also work in older versions of Java. However the code samples focus on Java 8 and make heavy use of lambda expressions and new concurrency features. If you&#39;re not yet familiar with lambdas I recommend reading my <a href="/posts/2014/03/16/java-8-tutorial/">Java 8 Tutorial</a> first.</p>

<p>For simplicity the code samples of this tutorial make use of the two helper methods <code>sleep(seconds)</code> and <code>stop(executor)</code> as defined <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial/blob/master/src/com/winterbe/java8/samples/concurrent/ConcurrentUtils.java">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">Synchronized<a href="#synchronized" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>In the <a href="(/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/)">previous tutorial</a> we&#39;ve learned how to execute code in parallel via executor services. When writing such multi-threaded code you have to pay particular attention when accessing shared mutable variables concurrently from multiple threads. Let&#39;s just say we want to increment an integer which is accessible simultaneously from multiple threads.</p>

<p>We define a field <code>count</code> with a method <code>increment()</code> to increase count by one:</p>

<pre><code>int count = 0;

void increment() {
    count = count + 1;
}

</code></pre>

<p>When calling this method concurrently from multiple threads we&#39;re in serious trouble:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 10000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(this::increment));

stop(executor);

System.out.println(count);  // 9965

</code></pre>

<p>Instead of seeing a constant result count of 10000 the actual result varies with every execution of the above code. The reason is that we share a mutable variable upon different threads without synchronizing the access to this variable which results in a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Race_condition">race condition</a>.</p>

<p>Three steps have to be performed in order to increment the number: (i) read the current value, (ii) increase this value by one and (iii) write the new value to the variable. If two threads perform these steps in parallel it&#39;s possible that both threads perform step 1 simultaneously thus reading the same current value. This results in lost writes so the actual result is lower. In the above sample 35 increments got lost due to concurrent unsynchronized access to count but you may see different results when executing the code by yourself.</p>

<p>Luckily Java supports thread-synchronization since the early days via the <code>synchronized</code> keyword. We can utilize <code>synchronized</code> to fix the above race conditions when incrementing the count:</p>

<pre><code>synchronized void incrementSync() {
    count = count + 1;
}

</code></pre>

<p>When using <code>incrementSync()</code> concurrently we get the desired result count of 10000. No race conditions occur any longer and the result is stable with every execution of the code:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);

IntStream.range(0, 10000)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(this::incrementSync));

stop(executor);

System.out.println(count);  // 10000

</code></pre>

<p>The <code>synchronized</code> keyword is also available as a block statement.</p>

<pre><code>void incrementSync() {
    synchronized (this) {
        count = count + 1;
    }
}

</code></pre>

<p>Internally Java uses a so called <u>monitor</u> also known as <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/concurrency/locksync.html">monitor lock or intrinsic lock</a> in order to manage synchronization. This monitor is bound to an object, e.g. when using synchronized methods each method share the same monitor of the corresponding object.</p>

<p>All implicit monitors implement the <u>reentrant</u> characteristics. Reentrant means that locks are bound to the current thread. A thread can safely acquire the same lock multiple times without running into deadlocks (e.g. a synchronized method calls another synchronized method on the same object).</p>

<h3 id="toc_1">Locks<a href="#locks" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Instead of using implicit locking via the <code>synchronized</code> keyword the Concurrency API supports various explicit locks specified by the <code>Lock</code> interface. Locks support various methods for finer grained lock control thus are more expressive than implicit monitors.</p>

<p>Multiple lock implementations are available in the standard JDK which will be demonstrated in the following sections.</p>

<h4 id="toc_2">ReentrantLock<a href="#reentrantlock" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The class <code>ReentrantLock</code> is a mutual exclusion lock with the same basic behavior as the implicit monitors accessed via the <code>synchronized</code> keyword but with extended capabilities. As the name suggests this lock implements reentrant characteristics just as implicit monitors.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s see how the above sample looks like using <code>ReentrantLock</code>:</p>

<pre><code>ReentrantLock lock = new ReentrantLock();
int count = 0;

void increment() {
    lock.lock();
    try {
        count++;
    } finally {
        lock.unlock();
    }
}

</code></pre>

<p>A lock is acquired via <code>lock()</code> and released via <code>unlock()</code>. It&#39;s important to wrap your code into a <code>try/finally</code> block to ensure unlocking in case of exceptions. This method is thread-safe just like the synchronized counterpart. If another thread has already acquired the lock subsequent calls to <code>lock()</code> pause the current thread until the lock has been unlocked. Only one thread can hold the lock at any given time.</p>

<p>Locks support various methods for fine grained control as seen in the next sample:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);
ReentrantLock lock = new ReentrantLock();

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    lock.lock();
    try {
        sleep(1);
    } finally {
        lock.unlock();
    }
});

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    System.out.println(&quot;Locked: &quot; + lock.isLocked());
    System.out.println(&quot;Held by me: &quot; + lock.isHeldByCurrentThread());
    boolean locked = lock.tryLock();
    System.out.println(&quot;Lock acquired: &quot; + locked);
});

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>While the first task holds the lock for one second the second task obtains different information about the current state of the lock:</p>

<pre><code>Locked: true
Held by me: false
Lock acquired: false

</code></pre>

<p>The method <code>tryLock()</code> as an alternative to <code>lock()</code> tries to acquire the lock without pausing the current thread. The boolean result must be used to check if the lock has actually been acquired before accessing any shared mutable variables.</p>

<h4 id="toc_3">ReadWriteLock<a href="#readwritelock" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The interface <code>ReadWriteLock</code> specifies another type of lock maintaining a pair of locks for read and write access. The idea behind read-write locks is that it&#39;s usually safe to read mutable variables concurrently as long as nobody is writing to this variable. So the read-lock can be held simultaneously by multiple threads as long as no threads hold the write-lock. This can improve performance and throughput in case that reads are more frequent than writes.</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);
Map&lt;String, String&gt; map = new HashMap&lt;&gt;();
ReadWriteLock lock = new ReentrantReadWriteLock();

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    lock.writeLock().lock();
    try {
        sleep(1);
        map.put(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;);
    } finally {
        lock.writeLock().unlock();
    }
});

</code></pre>

<p>The above example first acquires a write-lock in order to put a new value to the map after sleeping for one second. Before this task has finished two other tasks are being submitted trying to read the entry from the map and sleep for one second:</p>

<pre><code>Runnable readTask = () -&gt; {
    lock.readLock().lock();
    try {
        System.out.println(map.get(&quot;foo&quot;));
        sleep(1);
    } finally {
        lock.readLock().unlock();
    }
};

executor.submit(readTask);
executor.submit(readTask);

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>When you execute this code sample you&#39;ll notice that both read tasks have to wait the whole second until the write task has finished. After the write lock has been released both read tasks are executed in parallel and print the result simultaneously to the console. They don&#39;t have to wait for each other to finish because read-locks can safely be acquired concurrently as long as no write-lock is held by another thread.</p>

<h4 id="toc_4">StampedLock<a href="#stampedlock" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>Java 8 ships with a new kind of lock called <code>StampedLock</code> which also support read and write locks just like in the example above. In contrast to <code>ReadWriteLock</code> the locking methods of a <code>StampedLock</code> return a stamp represented by a <code>long</code> value. You can use these stamps to either release a lock or to check if the lock is still valid. Additionally stamped locks support another lock mode called <u>optimistic locking</u>.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s rewrite the last example code to use <code>StampedLock</code> instead of <code>ReadWriteLock</code>:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);
Map&lt;String, String&gt; map = new HashMap&lt;&gt;();
StampedLock lock = new StampedLock();

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    long stamp = lock.writeLock();
    try {
        sleep(1);
        map.put(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;);
    } finally {
        lock.unlockWrite(stamp);
    }
});

Runnable readTask = () -&gt; {
    long stamp = lock.readLock();
    try {
        System.out.println(map.get(&quot;foo&quot;));
        sleep(1);
    } finally {
        lock.unlockRead(stamp);
    }
};

executor.submit(readTask);
executor.submit(readTask);

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>Obtaining a read or write lock via <code>readLock()</code> or <code>writeLock()</code> returns a stamp which is later used for unlocking within the finally block. Keep in mind that stamped locks don&#39;t implement reentrant characteristics. Each call to lock returns a new stamp and blocks if no lock is available even if the same thread already holds a lock. So you have to pay particular attention not to run into deadlocks.</p>

<p>Just like in the previous <code>ReadWriteLock</code> example both read tasks have to wait until the write lock has been released. Then both read tasks print to the console simultaneously because multiple reads doesn&#39;t block each other as long as no write-lock is held.</p>

<p>The next example demonstrates <u>optimistic locking</u>:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);
StampedLock lock = new StampedLock();

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    long stamp = lock.tryOptimisticRead();
    try {
        System.out.println(&quot;Optimistic Lock Valid: &quot; + lock.validate(stamp));
        sleep(1);
        System.out.println(&quot;Optimistic Lock Valid: &quot; + lock.validate(stamp));
        sleep(2);
        System.out.println(&quot;Optimistic Lock Valid: &quot; + lock.validate(stamp));
    } finally {
        lock.unlock(stamp);
    }
});

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    long stamp = lock.writeLock();
    try {
        System.out.println(&quot;Write Lock acquired&quot;);
        sleep(2);
    } finally {
        lock.unlock(stamp);
        System.out.println(&quot;Write done&quot;);
    }
});

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>An optimistic read lock is acquired by calling <code>tryOptimisticRead()</code> which always returns a stamp without blocking the current thread, no matter if the lock is actually available. If there&#39;s already a write lock active the returned stamp equals zero. You can always check if a stamp is valid by calling <code>lock.validate(stamp)</code>.</p>

<p>Executing the above code results in the following output:</p>

<pre><code>Optimistic Lock Valid: true
Write Lock acquired
Optimistic Lock Valid: false
Write done
Optimistic Lock Valid: false

</code></pre>

<p>The optimistic lock is valid right after acquiring the lock. In contrast to normal read locks an optimistic lock doesn&#39;t prevent other threads to obtain a write lock instantaneously. After sending the first thread to sleep for one second the second thread obtains a write lock without waiting for the optimistic read lock to be released. From this point the optimistic read lock is no longer valid. Even when the write lock is released the optimistic read locks stays invalid.</p>

<p>So when working with optimistic locks you have to validate the lock every time <u>after</u> accessing any shared mutable variable to make sure the read was still valid.</p>

<p>Sometimes it&#39;s useful to convert a read lock into a write lock without unlocking and locking again. <code>StampedLock</code> provides the method <code>tryConvertToWriteLock()</code> for that purpose as seen in the next sample:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(2);
StampedLock lock = new StampedLock();

executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    long stamp = lock.readLock();
    try {
        if (count == 0) {
            stamp = lock.tryConvertToWriteLock(stamp);
            if (stamp == 0L) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Could not convert to write lock&quot;);
                stamp = lock.writeLock();
            }
            count = 23;
        }
        System.out.println(count);
    } finally {
        lock.unlock(stamp);
    }
});

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>The task first obtains a read lock and prints the current value of field <code>count</code> to the console. But if the current value is zero we want to assign a new value of <code>23</code>. We first have to convert the read lock into a write lock to not break potential concurrent access by other threads. Calling <code>tryConvertToWriteLock()</code> doesn&#39;t block but may return a zero stamp indicating that no write lock is currently available. In that case we call <code>writeLock()</code> to block the current thread until a write lock is available.</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">Semaphores<a href="#semaphores" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>In addition to locks the Concurrency API also supports counting semaphores. Whereas locks usually grant exclusive access to variables or resources, a semaphore is capable of maintaining whole sets of permits. This is useful in different scenarios where you have to limit the amount concurrent access to certain parts of your application.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s an example how to limit access to a long running task simulated by <code>sleep(5)</code>:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(10);

Semaphore semaphore = new Semaphore(5);

Runnable longRunningTask = () -&gt; {
    boolean permit = false;
    try {
        permit = semaphore.tryAcquire(1, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
        if (permit) {
            System.out.println(&quot;Semaphore acquired&quot;);
            sleep(5);
        } else {
            System.out.println(&quot;Could not acquire semaphore&quot;);
        }
    } catch (InterruptedException e) {
        throw new IllegalStateException(e);
    } finally {
        if (permit) {
            semaphore.release();
        }
    }
}

IntStream.range(0, 10)
    .forEach(i -&gt; executor.submit(longRunningTask));

stop(executor);

</code></pre>

<p>The executor can potentially run 10 tasks concurrently but we use a semaphore of size 5, thus limiting concurrent access to 5. It&#39;s important to use a <code>try/finally</code> block to properly release the semaphore even in case of exceptions.</p>

<p>Executing the above code results in the following output:</p>

<pre><code>Semaphore acquired
Semaphore acquired
Semaphore acquired
Semaphore acquired
Semaphore acquired
Could not acquire semaphore
Could not acquire semaphore
Could not acquire semaphore
Could not acquire semaphore
Could not acquire semaphore

</code></pre>

<p>The semaphores permits access to the actual long running operation simulated by <code>sleep(5)</code> up to a maximum of 5. Every subsequent call to <code>tryAcquire()</code> elapses the maximum wait timeout of one second, resulting in the appropriate console output that no semaphore could be acquired.</p>

<p>This was the second part out of a series of concurrency tutorials. More parts will be released in the near future, so stay tuned. As usual you find all code samples from this article on <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial">GitHub</a>, so feel free to fork the repo and try it by your own.</p>

<p>I hope you&#39;ve enjoyed this article. If you have any further questions send me your feedback in the comments below. You should also <a href="https://twitter.com/winterbe_">follow me on Twitter</a> for more dev-related stuff!</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: <a href="/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/">Threads and Executors</a></li>
<li>  Part 2: Synchronization and Locks</li>
<li>  Part 3: <a href="/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/">Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java 8 Concurrency Tutorial: Threads and Executors]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15358757119900.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T16:08:31+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15358757119900.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/">https://winterbe.com/posts/2015/04/07/java8-concurrency-tutorial-thread-executor-examples/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welcome to the first part of my Java 8 Concurrency tutorial. This guide teaches you <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concurrent_computing">concurrent programming</a> in Java 8 with easily understood code examples. It&#39;s the first part out of a series of tutorials covering the Java Concurrency API. In the next 15 min you learn how to execute code in parallel via threads, tasks and executor services.</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: Threads and Executors</li>
<li>  Part 2: <a href="/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">Synchronization and Locks</a></li>
<li>  Part 3: <a href="/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/">Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/package-summary.html">Concurrency API</a> was first introduced with the release of Java 5 and then progressively enhanced with every new Java release. The majority of concepts shown in this article also work in older versions of Java. However my code samples focus on Java 8 and make heavy use of lambda expressions and other new features. If you&#39;re not yet familiar with lambdas I recommend reading my <a href="/posts/2014/03/16/java-8-tutorial/">Java 8 Tutorial</a> first.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">Threads and Runnables<a href="#threads-and-runnables" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>All modern operating systems support concurrency both via <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Process_(computing)">processes</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thread_%28computing%29">threads</a>. Processes are instances of programs which typically run independent to each other, e.g. if you start a java program the operating system spawns a new process which runs in parallel to other programs. Inside those processes we can utilize threads to execute code concurrently, so we can make the most out of the available cores of the CPU.</p>

<p>Java supports <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/lang/Thread.html">Threads</a> since JDK 1.0. Before starting a new thread you have to specify the code to be executed by this thread, often called the <u>task</u>. This is done by implementing <code>Runnable</code> - a functional interface defining a single void no-args method <code>run()</code> as demonstrated in the following example:</p>

<pre><code>Runnable task = () -&gt; {
    String threadName = Thread.currentThread().getName();
    System.out.println(&quot;Hello &quot; + threadName);
};

task.run();

Thread thread = new Thread(task);
thread.start();

System.out.println(&quot;Done!&quot;);

</code></pre>

<p>Since <code>Runnable</code> is a functional interface we can utilize Java 8 lambda expressions to print the current threads name to the console. First we execute the runnable directly on the main thread before starting a new thread.</p>

<p>The result on the console might look like this:</p>

<pre><code>Hello main
Hello Thread-0
Done!

</code></pre>

<p>Or that:</p>

<pre><code>Hello main
Done!
Hello Thread-0

</code></pre>

<p>Due to concurrent execution we cannot predict if the runnable will be invoked before or after printing &#39;done&#39;. The order is non-deterministic, thus making concurrent programming a complex task in larger applications.</p>

<p>Threads can be put to sleep for a certain duration. This is quite handy to simulate long running tasks in the subsequent code samples of this article:</p>

<pre><code>Runnable runnable = () -&gt; {
    try {
        String name = Thread.currentThread().getName();
        System.out.println(&quot;Foo &quot; + name);
        TimeUnit.SECONDS.sleep(1);
        System.out.println(&quot;Bar &quot; + name);
    }
    catch (InterruptedException e) {
        e.printStackTrace();
    }
};

Thread thread = new Thread(runnable);
thread.start();

</code></pre>

<p>When you run the above code you&#39;ll notice the one second delay between the first and the second print statement. <code>TimeUnit</code> is a useful enum for working with units of time. Alternatively you can achieve the same by calling <code>Thread.sleep(1000)</code>.</p>

<p>Working with the <code>Thread</code> class can be very tedious and error-prone. Due to that reason the <strong>Concurrency API</strong> has been introduced back in 2004 with the release of Java 5. The API is located in package <code>java.util.concurrent</code> and contains many useful classes for handling concurrent programming. Since that time the Concurrency API has been enhanced with every new Java release and even Java 8 provides new classes and methods for dealing with concurrency.</p>

<p>Now let&#39;s take a deeper look at one of the most important parts of the Concurrency API - the executor services.</p>

<h3 id="toc_1">Executors<a href="#executors" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The Concurrency API introduces the concept of an <code>ExecutorService</code> as a higher level replacement for working with threads directly. Executors are capable of running asynchronous tasks and typically manage a pool of threads, so we don&#39;t have to create new threads manually. All threads of the internal pool will be reused under the hood for revenant tasks, so we can run as many concurrent tasks as we want throughout the life-cycle of our application with a single executor service.</p>

<p>This is how the first thread-example looks like using executors:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newSingleThreadExecutor();
executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    String threadName = Thread.currentThread().getName();
    System.out.println(&quot;Hello &quot; + threadName);
});

// =&gt; Hello pool-1-thread-1

</code></pre>

<p>The class <code>Executors</code> provides convenient factory methods for creating different kinds of executor services. In this sample we use an executor with a thread pool of size one.</p>

<p>The result looks similar to the above sample but when running the code you&#39;ll notice an important difference: the java process never stops! Executors have to be stopped explicitly - otherwise they keep listening for new tasks.</p>

<p>An <code>ExecutorService</code> provides two methods for that purpose: <code>shutdown()</code> waits for currently running tasks to finish while <code>shutdownNow()</code> interrupts all running tasks and shut the executor down immediately.</p>

<p>This is the preferred way how I typically shutdown executors:</p>

<pre><code>try {
    System.out.println(&quot;attempt to shutdown executor&quot;);
    executor.shutdown();
    executor.awaitTermination(5, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
}
catch (InterruptedException e) {
    System.err.println(&quot;tasks interrupted&quot;);
}
finally {
    if (!executor.isTerminated()) {
        System.err.println(&quot;cancel non-finished tasks&quot;);
    }
    executor.shutdownNow();
    System.out.println(&quot;shutdown finished&quot;);
}

</code></pre>

<p>The executor shuts down softly by waiting a certain amount of time for termination of currently running tasks. After a maximum of five seconds the executor finally shuts down by interrupting all running tasks.</p>

<h4 id="toc_2">Callables and Futures<a href="#callables-and-futures" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>In addition to <code>Runnable</code> executors support another kind of task named <code>Callable</code>. Callables are functional interfaces just like runnables but instead of being <code>void</code> they return a value.</p>

<p>This lambda expression defines a callable returning an integer after sleeping for one second:</p>

<pre><code>Callable&lt;Integer&gt; task = () -&gt; {
    try {
        TimeUnit.SECONDS.sleep(1);
        return 123;
    }
    catch (InterruptedException e) {
        throw new IllegalStateException(&quot;task interrupted&quot;, e);
    }
};

</code></pre>

<p>Callables can be submitted to executor services just like runnables. But what about the callables result? Since <code>submit()</code> doesn&#39;t wait until the task completes, the executor service cannot return the result of the callable directly. Instead the executor returns a special result of type <code>Future</code> which can be used to retrieve the actual result at a later point in time.</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(1);
Future&lt;Integer&gt; future = executor.submit(task);

System.out.println(&quot;future done? &quot; + future.isDone());

Integer result = future.get();

System.out.println(&quot;future done? &quot; + future.isDone());
System.out.print(&quot;result: &quot; + result);

</code></pre>

<p>After submitting the callable to the executor we first check if the future has already been finished execution via <code>isDone()</code>. I&#39;m pretty sure this isn&#39;t the case since the above callable sleeps for one second before returning the integer.</p>

<p>Calling the method <code>get()</code> blocks the current thread and waits until the callable completes before returning the actual result <code>123</code>. Now the future is finally done and we see the following result on the console:</p>

<pre><code>future done? false
future done? true
result: 123

</code></pre>

<p>Futures are tightly coupled to the underlying executor service. Keep in mind that every non-terminated future will throw exceptions if you shutdown the executor:</p>

<pre><code>executor.shutdownNow();
future.get();

</code></pre>

<p>You might have noticed that the creation of the executor slightly differs from the previous example. We use <code>newFixedThreadPool(1)</code> to create an executor service backed by a thread-pool of size one. This is equivalent to <code>newSingleThreadExecutor()</code> but we could later increase the pool size by simply passing a value larger than one.</p>

<h4 id="toc_3">Timeouts<a href="#timeouts" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>Any call to <code>future.get()</code> will block and wait until the underlying callable has been terminated. In the worst case a callable runs forever - thus making your application unresponsive. You can simply counteract those scenarios by passing a timeout:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newFixedThreadPool(1);

Future&lt;Integer&gt; future = executor.submit(() -&gt; {
    try {
        TimeUnit.SECONDS.sleep(2);
        return 123;
    }
    catch (InterruptedException e) {
        throw new IllegalStateException(&quot;task interrupted&quot;, e);
    }
});

future.get(1, TimeUnit.SECONDS);

</code></pre>

<p>Executing the above code results in a <code>TimeoutException</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Exception in thread &quot;main&quot; java.util.concurrent.TimeoutException
    at java.util.concurrent.FutureTask.get(FutureTask.java:205)

</code></pre>

<p>You might already have guessed why this exception is thrown: We specified a maximum wait time of one second but the callable actually needs two seconds before returning the result.</p>

<h4 id="toc_4">InvokeAll<a href="#invokeall" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>Executors support batch submitting of multiple callables at once via <code>invokeAll()</code>. This method accepts a collection of callables and returns a list of futures.</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newWorkStealingPool();

List&lt;Callable&lt;String&gt;&gt; callables = Arrays.asList(
        () -&gt; &quot;task1&quot;,
        () -&gt; &quot;task2&quot;,
        () -&gt; &quot;task3&quot;);

executor.invokeAll(callables)
    .stream()
    .map(future -&gt; {
        try {
            return future.get();
        }
        catch (Exception e) {
            throw new IllegalStateException(e);
        }
    })
    .forEach(System.out::println);

</code></pre>

<p>In this example we utilize Java 8 functional streams in order to process all futures returned by the invocation of <code>invokeAll</code>. We first map each future to its return value and then print each value to the console. If you&#39;re not yet familiar with streams read my <a href="/posts/2014/07/31/java8-stream-tutorial-examples/">Java 8 Stream Tutorial</a>.</p>

<h4 id="toc_5">InvokeAny<a href="#invokeany" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>Another way of batch-submitting callables is the method <code>invokeAny()</code> which works slightly different to <code>invokeAll()</code>. Instead of returning future objects this method blocks until the first callable terminates and returns the result of that callable.</p>

<p>In order to test this behavior we use this helper method to simulate callables with different durations. The method returns a callable that sleeps for a certain amount of time until returning the given result:</p>

<pre><code>Callable&lt;String&gt; callable(String result, long sleepSeconds) {
    return () -&gt; {
        TimeUnit.SECONDS.sleep(sleepSeconds);
        return result;
    };
}

</code></pre>

<p>We use this method to create a bunch of callables with different durations from one to three seconds. Submitting those callables to an executor via <code>invokeAny()</code> returns the string result of the fastest callable - in that case task2:</p>

<pre><code>ExecutorService executor = Executors.newWorkStealingPool();

List&lt;Callable&lt;String&gt;&gt; callables = Arrays.asList(
    callable(&quot;task1&quot;, 2),
    callable(&quot;task2&quot;, 1),
    callable(&quot;task3&quot;, 3));

String result = executor.invokeAny(callables);
System.out.println(result);

// =&gt; task2

</code></pre>

<p>The above example uses yet another type of executor created via <code>newWorkStealingPool()</code>. This factory method is part of Java 8 and returns an executor of type <code>ForkJoinPool</code> which works slightly different than normal executors. Instead of using a fixed size thread-pool <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ForkJoinPool.html">ForkJoinPools</a> are created for a given parallelism size which per default is the number of available cores of the hosts CPU.</p>

<p>ForkJoinPools exist since Java 7 and will be covered in detail in a later tutorial of this series. Let&#39;s finish this tutorial by taking a deeper look at scheduled executors.</p>

<h3 id="toc_6">Scheduled Executors<a href="#scheduled-executors" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>We&#39;ve already learned how to submit and run tasks once on an executor. In order to periodically run common tasks multiple times, we can utilize scheduled thread pools.</p>

<p>A <code>ScheduledExecutorService</code> is capable of scheduling tasks to run either periodically or once after a certain amount of time has elapsed.</p>

<p>This code sample schedules a task to run after an initial delay of three seconds has passed:</p>

<pre><code>ScheduledExecutorService executor = Executors.newScheduledThreadPool(1);

Runnable task = () -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;Scheduling: &quot; + System.nanoTime());
ScheduledFuture&lt;?&gt; future = executor.schedule(task, 3, TimeUnit.SECONDS);

TimeUnit.MILLISECONDS.sleep(1337);

long remainingDelay = future.getDelay(TimeUnit.MILLISECONDS);
System.out.printf(&quot;Remaining Delay: %sms&quot;, remainingDelay);

</code></pre>

<p>Scheduling a task produces a specialized future of type <code>ScheduledFuture</code> which - in addition to <code>Future</code> - provides the method <code>getDelay()</code> to retrieve the remaining delay. After this delay has elapsed the task will be executed concurrently.</p>

<p>In order to schedule tasks to be executed periodically, executors provide the two methods <code>scheduleAtFixedRate()</code> and <code>scheduleWithFixedDelay()</code>. The first method is capable of executing tasks with a fixed time rate, e.g. once every second as demonstrated in this example:</p>

<pre><code>ScheduledExecutorService executor = Executors.newScheduledThreadPool(1);

Runnable task = () -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;Scheduling: &quot; + System.nanoTime());

int initialDelay = 0;
int period = 1;
executor.scheduleAtFixedRate(task, initialDelay, period, TimeUnit.SECONDS);

</code></pre>

<p>Additionally this method accepts an initial delay which describes the leading wait time before the task will be executed for the first time.</p>

<p>Please keep in mind that <code>scheduleAtFixedRate()</code> doesn&#39;t take into account the actual duration of the task. So if you specify a period of one second but the task needs 2 seconds to be executed then the thread pool will working to capacity very soon.</p>

<p>In that case you should consider using <code>scheduleWithFixedDelay()</code> instead. This method works just like the counterpart described above. The difference is that the wait time period applies between the end of a task and the start of the next task. For example:</p>

<pre><code>ScheduledExecutorService executor = Executors.newScheduledThreadPool(1);

Runnable task = () -&gt; {
    try {
        TimeUnit.SECONDS.sleep(2);
        System.out.println(&quot;Scheduling: &quot; + System.nanoTime());
    }
    catch (InterruptedException e) {
        System.err.println(&quot;task interrupted&quot;);
    }
};

executor.scheduleWithFixedDelay(task, 0, 1, TimeUnit.SECONDS);

</code></pre>

<p>This example schedules a task with a fixed delay of one second between the end of an execution and the start of the next execution. The initial delay is zero and the tasks duration is two seconds. So we end up with an execution interval of 0s, 3s, 6s, 9s and so on. As you can see <code>scheduleWithFixedDelay()</code> is handy if you cannot predict the duration of the scheduled tasks.</p>

<p>This was the first part out of a series of concurrency tutorials. I recommend practicing the shown code samples by your own. You find all code samples from this article on <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial">GitHub</a>, so feel free to fork the repo and <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial/stargazers">give me star</a>.</p>

<p>I hope you&#39;ve enjoyed this article. If you have any further questions send me your feedback in the comments below or via <a href="https://twitter.com/winterbe_">Twitter</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>  Part 1: Threads and Executors</li>
<li>  Part 2: <a href="/posts/2015/04/30/java8-concurrency-tutorial-synchronized-locks-examples/">Synchronization and Locks</a></li>
<li>  Part 3: <a href="/posts/2015/05/22/java8-concurrency-tutorial-atomic-concurrent-map-examples/">Atomic Variables and ConcurrentMap</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java 8 Stream Tutorial]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15358756631902.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T16:07:43+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15358756631902.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://winterbe.com/posts/2014/07/31/java8-stream-tutorial-examples/">https://winterbe.com/posts/2014/07/31/java8-stream-tutorial-examples/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This example-driven tutorial gives an in-depth overview about Java 8 streams. When I first read about the <code>Stream</code> API, I was confused about the name since it sounds similar to <code>InputStream</code> and <code>OutputStream</code> from Java I/O. But Java 8 streams are a completely different thing. Streams are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monad_%28functional_programming%29">Monads</a>, thus playing a big part in bringing <u>functional programming</u> to Java:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>In functional programming, a monad is a structure that represents computations defined as sequences of steps. A type with a monad structure defines what it means to chain operations, or nest functions of that type together.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This guide teaches you how to work with Java 8 streams and how to use the different kind of available stream operations. You&#39;ll learn about the processing order and how the ordering of stream operations affect runtime performance. The more powerful stream operations <code>reduce</code>, <code>collect</code> and <code>flatMap</code> are covered in detail. The tutorial ends with an in-depth look at parallel streams.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re not yet familiar with Java 8 lambda expressions, functional interfaces and method references, you probably want to read my <a href="http://winterbe.com/posts/2014/03/16/java-8-tutorial/">Java 8 Tutorial</a> first before starting with this tutorial.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">How streams work<a href="#how-streams-work" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>A stream represents a sequence of elements and supports different kind of operations to perform computations upon those elements:</p>

<pre><code>List&lt;String&gt; myList =
    Arrays.asList(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;c2&quot;, &quot;c1&quot;);

myList
    .stream()
    .filter(s -&gt; s.startsWith(&quot;c&quot;))
    .map(String::toUpperCase)
    .sorted()
    .forEach(System.out::println);

// C1
// C2

</code></pre>

<p>Stream operations are either intermediate or terminal. Intermediate operations return a stream so we can chain multiple intermediate operations without using semicolons. Terminal operations are either void or return a non-stream result. In the above example <code>filter</code>, <code>map</code> and <code>sorted</code> are intermediate operations whereas <code>forEach</code> is a terminal operation. For a full list of all available stream operations see the <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/Stream.html">Stream Javadoc</a>. Such a chain of stream operations as seen in the example above is also known as <u>operation pipeline</u>.</p>

<p>Most stream operations accept some kind of lambda expression parameter, a functional interface specifying the exact behavior of the operation. Most of those operations must be both <u>non-interfering</u> and <u>stateless</u>. What does that mean?</p>

<p>A function is <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/package-summary.html#NonInterference">non-interfering</a> when it does not modify the underlying data source of the stream, e.g. in the above example no lambda expression does modify <code>myList</code> by adding or removing elements from the collection.</p>

<p>A function is <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/package-summary.html#Statelessness">stateless</a> when the execution of the operation is deterministic, e.g. in the above example no lambda expression depends on any mutable variables or states from the outer scope which might change during execution.</p>

<h3 id="toc_1">Different kind of streams<a href="#different-kind-of-streams" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Streams can be created from various data sources, especially collections. Lists and Sets support new methods <code>stream()</code> and <code>parallelStream()</code> to either create a sequential or a parallel stream. Parallel streams are capable of operating on multiple threads and will be covered in a later section of this tutorial. We focus on sequential streams for now:</p>

<pre><code>Arrays.asList(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;a3&quot;)
    .stream()
    .findFirst()
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);  // a1

</code></pre>

<p>Calling the method <code>stream()</code> on a list of objects returns a regular object stream. But we don&#39;t have to create collections in order to work with streams as we see in the next code sample:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;a3&quot;)
    .findFirst()
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);  // a1

</code></pre>

<p>Just use <code>Stream.of()</code> to create a stream from a bunch of object references.</p>

<p>Besides regular object streams Java 8 ships with special kinds of streams for working with the primitive data types <code>int</code>, <code>long</code> and <code>double</code>. As you might have guessed it&#39;s <code>IntStream</code>, <code>LongStream</code> and <code>DoubleStream</code>.</p>

<p>IntStreams can replace the regular for-loop utilizing <code>IntStream.range()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>IntStream.range(1, 4)
    .forEach(System.out::println);

// 1
// 2
// 3

</code></pre>

<p>All those primitive streams work just like regular object streams with the following differences: Primitive streams use specialized lambda expressions, e.g. <code>IntFunction</code> instead of <code>Function</code> or <code>IntPredicate</code> instead of <code>Predicate</code>. And primitive streams support the additional terminal aggregate operations <code>sum()</code> and <code>average()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Arrays.stream(new int[] {1, 2, 3})
    .map(n -&gt; 2 * n + 1)
    .average()
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);  // 5.0

</code></pre>

<p>Sometimes it&#39;s useful to transform a regular object stream to a primitive stream or vice versa. For that purpose object streams support the special mapping operations <code>mapToInt()</code>, <code>mapToLong()</code> and <code>mapToDouble</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;a3&quot;)
    .map(s -&gt; s.substring(1))
    .mapToInt(Integer::parseInt)
    .max()
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);  // 3

</code></pre>

<p>Primitive streams can be transformed to object streams via <code>mapToObj()</code>:</p>

<pre><code>IntStream.range(1, 4)
    .mapToObj(i -&gt; &quot;a&quot; + i)
    .forEach(System.out::println);

// a1
// a2
// a3

</code></pre>

<p>Here&#39;s a combined example: the stream of doubles is first mapped to an int stream and than mapped to an object stream of strings:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(1.0, 2.0, 3.0)
    .mapToInt(Double::intValue)
    .mapToObj(i -&gt; &quot;a&quot; + i)
    .forEach(System.out::println);

// a1
// a2
// a3

</code></pre>

<h3 id="toc_2">Processing Order<a href="#processing-order" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Now that we&#39;ve learned how to create and work with different kinds of streams, let&#39;s dive deeper into how stream operations are processed under the hood.</p>

<p>An important characteristic of intermediate operations is laziness. Look at this sample where a terminal operation is missing:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return true;
    });

</code></pre>

<p>When executing this code snippet, nothing is printed to the console. That is because intermediate operations will only be executed when a terminal operation is present.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s extend the above example by the terminal operation <code>forEach</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return true;
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;forEach: &quot; + s));

</code></pre>

<p>Executing this code snippet results in the desired output on the console:</p>

<pre><code>filter:  d2
forEach: d2
filter:  a2
forEach: a2
filter:  b1
forEach: b1
filter:  b3
forEach: b3
filter:  c
forEach: c

</code></pre>

<p>The order of the result might be surprising. A naive approach would be to execute the operations horizontally one after another on all elements of the stream. But instead each element moves along the chain vertically. The first string &quot;d2&quot; passes <code>filter</code> then <code>forEach</code>, only then the second string &quot;a2&quot; is processed.</p>

<p>This behavior can reduce the actual number of operations performed on each element, as we see in the next example:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;map: &quot; + s);
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .anyMatch(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;anyMatch: &quot; + s);
        return s.startsWith(&quot;A&quot;);
    });

// map:      d2
// anyMatch: D2
// map:      a2
// anyMatch: A2

</code></pre>

<p>The operation <code>anyMatch</code> returns <code>true</code> as soon as the predicate applies to the given input element. This is true for the second element passed &quot;A2&quot;. Due to the vertical execution of the stream chain, <code>map</code> has only to be executed twice in this case. So instead of mapping all elements of the stream, <code>map</code> will be called as few as possible.</p>

<h4 id="toc_3">Why order matters<a href="#why-order-matters" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The next example consists of two intermediate operations <code>map</code> and <code>filter</code> and the terminal operation <code>forEach</code>. Let&#39;s once again inspect how those operations are being executed:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;map: &quot; + s);
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return s.startsWith(&quot;A&quot;);
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;forEach: &quot; + s));

// map:     d2
// filter:  D2
// map:     a2
// filter:  A2
// forEach: A2
// map:     b1
// filter:  B1
// map:     b3
// filter:  B3
// map:     c
// filter:  C

</code></pre>

<p>As you might have guessed both <code>map</code> and <code>filter</code> are called five times for every string in the underlying collection whereas <code>forEach</code> is only called once.</p>

<p>We can greatly reduce the actual number of executions if we change the order of the operations, moving <code>filter</code> to the beginning of the chain:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return s.startsWith(&quot;a&quot;);
    })
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;map: &quot; + s);
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;forEach: &quot; + s));

// filter:  d2
// filter:  a2
// map:     a2
// forEach: A2
// filter:  b1
// filter:  b3
// filter:  c

</code></pre>

<p>Now, <code>map</code> is only called once so the operation pipeline performs much faster for larger numbers of input elements. Keep that in mind when composing complex method chains.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s extend the above example by an additional operation, <code>sorted</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .sorted((s1, s2) -&gt; {
        System.out.printf(&quot;sort: %s; %s\n&quot;, s1, s2);
        return s1.compareTo(s2);
    })
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return s.startsWith(&quot;a&quot;);
    })
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;map: &quot; + s);
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;forEach: &quot; + s));

</code></pre>

<p>Sorting is a special kind of intermediate operation. It&#39;s a so called <u>stateful operation</u> since in order to sort a collection of elements you have to maintain state during ordering.</p>

<p>Executing this example results in the following console output:</p>

<pre><code>sort:    a2; d2
sort:    b1; a2
sort:    b1; d2
sort:    b1; a2
sort:    b3; b1
sort:    b3; d2
sort:    c; b3
sort:    c; d2
filter:  a2
map:     a2
forEach: A2
filter:  b1
filter:  b3
filter:  c
filter:  d2

</code></pre>

<p>First, the sort operation is executed on the entire input collection. In other words <code>sorted</code> is executed horizontally. So in this case <code>sorted</code> is called eight times for multiple combinations on every element in the input collection.</p>

<p>Once again we can optimize the performance by reordering the chain:</p>

<pre><code>Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;filter: &quot; + s);
        return s.startsWith(&quot;a&quot;);
    })
    .sorted((s1, s2) -&gt; {
        System.out.printf(&quot;sort: %s; %s\n&quot;, s1, s2);
        return s1.compareTo(s2);
    })
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.println(&quot;map: &quot; + s);
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.println(&quot;forEach: &quot; + s));

// filter:  d2
// filter:  a2
// filter:  b1
// filter:  b3
// filter:  c
// map:     a2
// forEach: A2

</code></pre>

<p>In this example <code>sorted</code> is never been called because <code>filter</code> reduces the input collection to just one element. So the performance is greatly increased for larger input collections.</p>

<h3 id="toc_4">Reusing Streams<a href="#reusing-streams" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Java 8 streams cannot be reused. As soon as you call any terminal operation the stream is closed:</p>

<pre><code>Stream&lt;String&gt; stream =
    Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
        .filter(s -&gt; s.startsWith(&quot;a&quot;));

stream.anyMatch(s -&gt; true);    // ok
stream.noneMatch(s -&gt; true);   // exception

</code></pre>

<p>Calling <code>noneMatch</code> after <code>anyMatch</code> on the same stream results in the following exception:</p>

<pre><code>java.lang.IllegalStateException: stream has already been operated upon or closed
    at java.util.stream.AbstractPipeline.evaluate(AbstractPipeline.java:229)
    at java.util.stream.ReferencePipeline.noneMatch(ReferencePipeline.java:459)
    at com.winterbe.java8.Streams5.test7(Streams5.java:38)
    at com.winterbe.java8.Streams5.main(Streams5.java:28)

</code></pre>

<p>To overcome this limitation we have to to create a new stream chain for every terminal operation we want to execute, e.g. we could create a stream supplier to construct a new stream with all intermediate operations already set up:</p>

<pre><code>Supplier&lt;Stream&lt;String&gt;&gt; streamSupplier =
    () -&gt; Stream.of(&quot;d2&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;b3&quot;, &quot;c&quot;)
            .filter(s -&gt; s.startsWith(&quot;a&quot;));

streamSupplier.get().anyMatch(s -&gt; true);   // ok
streamSupplier.get().noneMatch(s -&gt; true);  // ok

</code></pre>

<p>Each call to <code>get()</code> constructs a new stream on which we are save to call the desired terminal operation.</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">Advanced Operations<a href="#advanced-operations" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Streams support plenty of different operations. We&#39;ve already learned about the most important operations like <code>filter</code> or <code>map</code>. I leave it up to you to discover all other available operations (see <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/Stream.html">Stream Javadoc</a>). Instead let&#39;s dive deeper into the more complex operations <code>collect</code>, <code>flatMap</code> and <code>reduce</code>.</p>

<p>Most code samples from this section use the following list of persons for demonstration purposes:</p>

<pre><code>class Person {
    String name;
    int age;

    Person(String name, int age) {
        this.name = name;
        this.age = age;
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return name;
    }
}

List&lt;Person&gt; persons =
    Arrays.asList(
        new Person(&quot;Max&quot;, 18),
        new Person(&quot;Peter&quot;, 23),
        new Person(&quot;Pamela&quot;, 23),
        new Person(&quot;David&quot;, 12));

</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_6">Collect<a href="#collect" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>Collect is an extremely useful terminal operation to transform the elements of the stream into a different kind of result, e.g. a <code>List</code>, <code>Set</code> or <code>Map</code>. Collect accepts a <code>Collector</code> which consists of four different operations: a <u>supplier</u>, an <u>accumulator</u>, a <u>combiner</u> and a <u>finisher</u>. This sounds super complicated at first, but the good part is Java 8 supports various built-in collectors via the <code>Collectors</code> class. So for the most common operations you don&#39;t have to implement a collector yourself.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s start with a very common usecase:</p>

<pre><code>List&lt;Person&gt; filtered =
    persons
        .stream()
        .filter(p -&gt; p.name.startsWith(&quot;P&quot;))
        .collect(Collectors.toList());

System.out.println(filtered);    // [Peter, Pamela]

</code></pre>

<p>As you can see it&#39;s very simple to construct a list from the elements of a stream. Need a set instead of list - just use <code>Collectors.toSet()</code>.</p>

<p>The next example groups all persons by age:</p>

<pre><code>Map&lt;Integer, List&lt;Person&gt;&gt; personsByAge = persons
    .stream()
    .collect(Collectors.groupingBy(p -&gt; p.age));

personsByAge
    .forEach((age, p) -&gt; System.out.format(&quot;age %s: %s\n&quot;, age, p));

// age 18: [Max]
// age 23: [Peter, Pamela]
// age 12: [David]

</code></pre>

<p>Collectors are extremely versatile. You can also create aggregations on the elements of the stream, e.g. determining the average age of all persons:</p>

<pre><code>Double averageAge = persons
    .stream()
    .collect(Collectors.averagingInt(p -&gt; p.age));

System.out.println(averageAge);     // 19.0

</code></pre>

<p>If you&#39;re interested in more comprehensive statistics, the summarizing collectors return a special built-in summary statistics object. So we can simply determine <u>min</u>, <u>max</u> and arithmetic <u>average</u> age of the persons as well as the <u>sum</u> and <u>count</u>.</p>

<pre><code>IntSummaryStatistics ageSummary =
    persons
        .stream()
        .collect(Collectors.summarizingInt(p -&gt; p.age));

System.out.println(ageSummary);
// IntSummaryStatistics{count=4, sum=76, min=12, average=19.000000, max=23}

</code></pre>

<p>The next example joins all persons into a single string:</p>

<pre><code>String phrase = persons
    .stream()
    .filter(p -&gt; p.age &gt;= 18)
    .map(p -&gt; p.name)
    .collect(Collectors.joining(&quot; and &quot;, &quot;In Germany &quot;, &quot; are of legal age.&quot;));

System.out.println(phrase);
// In Germany Max and Peter and Pamela are of legal age.

</code></pre>

<p>The join collector accepts a delimiter as well as an optional prefix and suffix.</p>

<p>In order to transform the stream elements into a map, we have to specify how both the keys and the values should be mapped. Keep in mind that the mapped keys must be unique, otherwise an <code>IllegalStateException</code> is thrown. You can optionally pass a merge function as an additional parameter to bypass the exception:</p>

<pre><code>Map&lt;Integer, String&gt; map = persons
    .stream()
    .collect(Collectors.toMap(
        p -&gt; p.age,
        p -&gt; p.name,
        (name1, name2) -&gt; name1 + &quot;;&quot; + name2));

System.out.println(map);
// {18=Max, 23=Peter;Pamela, 12=David}

</code></pre>

<p>Now that we know some of the most powerful built-in collectors, let&#39;s try to build our own special collector. We want to transform all persons of the stream into a single string consisting of all names in upper letters separated by the <code>|</code> pipe character. In order to achieve this we create a new collector via <code>Collector.of()</code>. We have to pass the four ingredients of a collector: a <u>supplier</u>, an <u>accumulator</u>, a <u>combiner</u> and a <u>finisher</u>.</p>

<pre><code>Collector&lt;Person, StringJoiner, String&gt; personNameCollector =
    Collector.of(
        () -&gt; new StringJoiner(&quot; | &quot;),          // supplier
        (j, p) -&gt; j.add(p.name.toUpperCase()),  // accumulator
        (j1, j2) -&gt; j1.merge(j2),               // combiner
        StringJoiner::toString);                // finisher

String names = persons
    .stream()
    .collect(personNameCollector);

System.out.println(names);  // MAX | PETER | PAMELA | DAVID

</code></pre>

<p>Since strings in Java are immutable, we need a helper class like <code>StringJoiner</code> to let the collector construct our string. The supplier initially constructs such a StringJoiner with the appropriate delimiter. The accumulator is used to add each persons upper-cased name to the StringJoiner. The combiner knows how to merge two StringJoiners into one. In the last step the finisher constructs the desired String from the StringJoiner.</p>

<h4 id="toc_7">FlatMap<a href="#flatmap" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>We&#39;ve already learned how to transform the objects of a stream into another type of objects by utilizing the <code>map</code> operation. Map is kinda limited because every object can only be mapped to exactly one other object. But what if we want to transform one object into multiple others or none at all? This is where <code>flatMap</code> comes to the rescue.</p>

<p>FlatMap transforms each element of the stream into a stream of other objects. So each object will be transformed into zero, one or multiple other objects backed by streams. The contents of those streams will then be placed into the returned stream of the <code>flatMap</code> operation.</p>

<p>Before we see <code>flatMap</code> in action we need an appropriate type hierarchy:</p>

<pre><code>class Foo {
    String name;
    List&lt;Bar&gt; bars = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;();

    Foo(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
}

class Bar {
    String name;

    Bar(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }
}

</code></pre>

<p>Next, we utilize our knowledge about streams to instantiate a couple of objects:</p>

<pre><code>List&lt;Foo&gt; foos = new ArrayList&lt;&gt;();

// create foos
IntStream
    .range(1, 4)
    .forEach(i -&gt; foos.add(new Foo(&quot;Foo&quot; + i)));

// create bars
foos.forEach(f -&gt;
    IntStream
        .range(1, 4)
        .forEach(i -&gt; f.bars.add(new Bar(&quot;Bar&quot; + i + &quot; &lt;- &quot; + f.name))));

</code></pre>

<p>Now we have a list of three foos each consisting of three bars.</p>

<p>FlatMap accepts a function which has to return a stream of objects. So in order to resolve the bar objects of each foo, we just pass the appropriate function:</p>

<pre><code>foos.stream()
    .flatMap(f -&gt; f.bars.stream())
    .forEach(b -&gt; System.out.println(b.name));

// Bar1 &lt;- Foo1
// Bar2 &lt;- Foo1
// Bar3 &lt;- Foo1
// Bar1 &lt;- Foo2
// Bar2 &lt;- Foo2
// Bar3 &lt;- Foo2
// Bar1 &lt;- Foo3
// Bar2 &lt;- Foo3
// Bar3 &lt;- Foo3

</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, we&#39;ve successfully transformed the stream of three foo objects into a stream of nine bar objects.</p>

<p>Finally, the above code example can be simplified into a single pipeline of stream operations:</p>

<pre><code>IntStream.range(1, 4)
    .mapToObj(i -&gt; new Foo(&quot;Foo&quot; + i))
    .peek(f -&gt; IntStream.range(1, 4)
        .mapToObj(i -&gt; new Bar(&quot;Bar&quot; + i + &quot; &lt;- &quot; f.name))
        .forEach(f.bars::add))
    .flatMap(f -&gt; f.bars.stream())
    .forEach(b -&gt; System.out.println(b.name));

</code></pre>

<p>FlatMap is also available for the <code>Optional</code> class introduced in Java 8. Optionals <code>flatMap</code> operation returns an optional object of another type. So it can be utilized to prevent nasty <code>null</code> checks.</p>

<p>Think of a highly hierarchical structure like this:</p>

<pre><code>class Outer {
    Nested nested;
}

class Nested {
    Inner inner;
}

class Inner {
    String foo;
}

</code></pre>

<p>In order to resolve the inner string <code>foo</code> of an outer instance you have to add multiple null checks to prevent possible NullPointerExceptions:</p>

<pre><code>Outer outer = new Outer();
if (outer != null &amp;&amp; outer.nested != null &amp;&amp; outer.nested.inner != null) {
    System.out.println(outer.nested.inner.foo);
}

</code></pre>

<p>The same behavior can be obtained by utilizing optionals <code>flatMap</code> operation:</p>

<pre><code>Optional.of(new Outer())
    .flatMap(o -&gt; Optional.ofNullable(o.nested))
    .flatMap(n -&gt; Optional.ofNullable(n.inner))
    .flatMap(i -&gt; Optional.ofNullable(i.foo))
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);

</code></pre>

<p>Each call to <code>flatMap</code> returns an <code>Optional</code> wrapping the desired object if present or <code>null</code> if absent.</p>

<h4 id="toc_8">Reduce<a href="#reduce" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h4>

<p>The reduction operation combines all elements of the stream into a single result. Java 8 supports three different kind of <code>reduce</code> methods. The first one reduces a stream of elements to exactly one element of the stream. Let&#39;s see how we can use this method to determine the oldest person:</p>

<pre><code>persons
    .stream()
    .reduce((p1, p2) -&gt; p1.age &gt; p2.age ? p1 : p2)
    .ifPresent(System.out::println);    // Pamela

</code></pre>

<p>The <code>reduce</code> method accepts a <code>BinaryOperator</code> accumulator function. That&#39;s actually a <code>BiFunction</code> where both operands share the same type, in that case <code>Person</code>. BiFunctions are like <code>Function</code> but accept two arguments. The example function compares both persons ages in order to return the person with the maximum age.</p>

<p>The second <code>reduce</code> method accepts both an identity value and a <code>BinaryOperator</code> accumulator. This method can be utilized to construct a new Person with the aggregated names and ages from all other persons in the stream:</p>

<pre><code>Person result =
    persons
        .stream()
        .reduce(new Person(&quot;&quot;, 0), (p1, p2) -&gt; {
            p1.age += p2.age;
            p1.name += p2.name;
            return p1;
        });

System.out.format(&quot;, result.name, result.age);
// name=MaxPeterPamelaDavid; age=76

</code></pre>

<p>The third <code>reduce</code> method accepts three parameters: an identity value, a <code>BiFunction</code> accumulator and a combiner function of type <code>BinaryOperator</code>. Since the identity values type is not restricted to the <code>Person</code> type, we can utilize this reduction to determine the sum of ages from all persons:</p>

<pre><code>Integer ageSum = persons
    .stream()
    .reduce(0, (sum, p) -&gt; sum += p.age, (sum1, sum2) -&gt; sum1 + sum2);

System.out.println(ageSum);  // 76

</code></pre>

<p>As you can see the result is <u>76</u>, but what&#39;s happening exactly under the hood? Let&#39;s extend the above code by some debug output:</p>

<pre><code>Integer ageSum = persons
    .stream()
    .reduce(0,
        (sum, p) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;accumulator: sum=%s; person=%s\n&quot;, sum, p);
            return sum += p.age;
        },
        (sum1, sum2) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;combiner: sum1=%s; sum2=%s\n&quot;, sum1, sum2);
            return sum1 + sum2;
        });

// accumulator: sum=0; person=Max
// accumulator: sum=18; person=Peter
// accumulator: sum=41; person=Pamela
// accumulator: sum=64; person=David

</code></pre>

<p>As you can see the accumulator function does all the work. It first get called with the initial identity value <u>0</u> and the first person <u>Max</u>. In the next three steps <code>sum</code> continually increases by the age of the last steps person up to a total age of <u>76</u>.</p>

<p>Wait wat? The combiner never gets called? Executing the same stream in parallel will lift the secret:</p>

<pre><code>Integer ageSum = persons
    .parallelStream()
    .reduce(0,
        (sum, p) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;accumulator: sum=%s; person=%s\n&quot;, sum, p);
            return sum += p.age;
        },
        (sum1, sum2) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;combiner: sum1=%s; sum2=%s\n&quot;, sum1, sum2);
            return sum1 + sum2;
        });

// accumulator: sum=0; person=Pamela
// accumulator: sum=0; person=David
// accumulator: sum=0; person=Max
// accumulator: sum=0; person=Peter
// combiner: sum1=18; sum2=23
// combiner: sum1=23; sum2=12
// combiner: sum1=41; sum2=35

</code></pre>

<p>Executing this stream in parallel results in an entirely different execution behavior. Now the combiner is actually called. Since the accumulator is called in parallel, the combiner is needed to sum up the separate accumulated values.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s dive deeper into parallel streams in the next chapter.</p>

<h3 id="toc_9">Parallel Streams<a href="#parallel-streams" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>Streams can be executed in parallel to increase runtime performance on large amount of input elements. Parallel streams use a common <code>ForkJoinPool</code> available via the static <code>ForkJoinPool.commonPool()</code> method. The size of the underlying thread-pool uses up to five threads - depending on the amount of available physical CPU cores:</p>

<pre><code>ForkJoinPool commonPool = ForkJoinPool.commonPool();
System.out.println(commonPool.getParallelism());    // 3

</code></pre>

<p>On my machine the common pool is initialized with a parallelism of 3 per default. This value can be decreased or increased by setting the following JVM parameter:</p>

<pre><code>-Djava.util.concurrent.ForkJoinPool.common.parallelism=5

</code></pre>

<p>Collections support the method <code>parallelStream()</code> to create a parallel stream of elements. Alternatively you can call the intermediate method <code>parallel()</code> on a given stream to convert a sequential stream to a parallel counterpart.</p>

<p>In order to understate the parallel execution behavior of a parallel stream the next example prints information about the current thread to <code>sout</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Arrays.asList(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;c2&quot;, &quot;c1&quot;)
    .parallelStream()
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.format(&quot;filter: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
            s, Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return true;
    })
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.format(&quot;map: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
            s, Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.format(&quot;forEach: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
        s, Thread.currentThread().getName()));

</code></pre>

<p>By investigating the debug output we should get a better understanding which threads are actually used to execute the stream operations:</p>

<pre><code>filter:  b1 [main]
filter:  a2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
map:     a2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
filter:  c2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
map:     c2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
filter:  c1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
map:     c1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
forEach: C2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
forEach: A2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
map:     b1 [main]
forEach: B1 [main]
filter:  a1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
map:     a1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
forEach: A1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
forEach: C1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]

</code></pre>

<p>As you can see the parallel stream utilizes all available threads from the common <code>ForkJoinPool</code> for executing the stream operations. The output may differ in consecutive runs because the behavior which particular thread is actually used is non-deterministic.</p>

<p>Let&#39;s extend the example by an additional stream operation, <code>sort</code>:</p>

<pre><code>Arrays.asList(&quot;a1&quot;, &quot;a2&quot;, &quot;b1&quot;, &quot;c2&quot;, &quot;c1&quot;)
    .parallelStream()
    .filter(s -&gt; {
        System.out.format(&quot;filter: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
            s, Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return true;
    })
    .map(s -&gt; {
        System.out.format(&quot;map: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
            s, Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return s.toUpperCase();
    })
    .sorted((s1, s2) -&gt; {
        System.out.format(&quot;sort: %s &lt;&gt; %s [%s]\n&quot;,
            s1, s2, Thread.currentThread().getName());
        return s1.compareTo(s2);
    })
    .forEach(s -&gt; System.out.format(&quot;forEach: %s [%s]\n&quot;,
        s, Thread.currentThread().getName()));

</code></pre>

<p>The result may look strange at first:</p>

<pre><code>filter:  c2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
filter:  c1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
map:     c1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
filter:  a2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
map:     a2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
filter:  b1 [main]
map:     b1 [main]
filter:  a1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
map:     a1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
map:     c2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
sort:    A2 &lt;&gt; A1 [main]
sort:    B1 &lt;&gt; A2 [main]
sort:    C2 &lt;&gt; B1 [main]
sort:    C1 &lt;&gt; C2 [main]
sort:    C1 &lt;&gt; B1 [main]
sort:    C1 &lt;&gt; C2 [main]
forEach: A1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
forEach: C2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
forEach: B1 [main]
forEach: A2 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
forEach: C1 [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]

</code></pre>

<p>It seems that <code>sort</code> is executed sequentially on the main thread only. Actually, <code>sort</code> on a parallel stream uses the new Java 8 method <code>Arrays.parallelSort()</code> under the hood. As stated in <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/Arrays.html#parallelSort-T:A-">Javadoc</a> this method decides on the length of the array if sorting will be performed sequentially or in parallel:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>If the length of the specified array is less than the minimum granularity, then it is sorted using the appropriate Arrays.sort method.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Coming back to the <code>reduce</code> example from the last section. We already found out that the combiner function is only called in parallel but not in sequential streams. Let&#39;s see which threads are actually involved:</p>

<pre><code>List&lt;Person&gt; persons = Arrays.asList(
    new Person(&quot;Max&quot;, 18),
    new Person(&quot;Peter&quot;, 23),
    new Person(&quot;Pamela&quot;, 23),
    new Person(&quot;David&quot;, 12));

persons
    .parallelStream()
    .reduce(0,
        (sum, p) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;accumulator: sum=%s; person=%s [%s]\n&quot;,
                sum, p, Thread.currentThread().getName());
            return sum += p.age;
        },
        (sum1, sum2) -&gt; {
            System.out.format(&quot;combiner: sum1=%s; sum2=%s [%s]\n&quot;,
                sum1, sum2, Thread.currentThread().getName());
            return sum1 + sum2;
        });

</code></pre>

<p>The console output reveals that both the <u>accumulator</u> and the <u>combiner</u> functions are executed in parallel on all available threads:</p>

<pre><code>accumulator: sum=0; person=Pamela; [main]
accumulator: sum=0; person=Max;    [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-3]
accumulator: sum=0; person=David;  [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
accumulator: sum=0; person=Peter;  [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
combiner:    sum1=18; sum2=23;     [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-1]
combiner:    sum1=23; sum2=12;     [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]
combiner:    sum1=41; sum2=35;     [ForkJoinPool.commonPool-worker-2]

</code></pre>

<p>In summary, it can be stated that parallel streams can bring be a nice performance boost to streams with a large amount of input elements. But keep in mind that some parallel stream operations like <code>reduce</code> and <code>collect</code> need additional computations (combine operations) which isn&#39;t needed when executed sequentially.</p>

<p>Furthermore we&#39;ve learned that all parallel stream operations share the same JVM-wide common <code>ForkJoinPool</code>. So you probably want to avoid implementing slow blocking stream operations since that could potentially slow down other parts of your application which rely heavily on parallel streams.</p>

<h3 id="toc_10">That&#39;s it<a href="#thats-it" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>My programming guide to Java 8 streams ends here. If you&#39;re interested in learning more about Java 8 streams, I recommend to you the <a href="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/stream/package-summary.html#NonInterference">Stream Javadoc</a> package documentation. If you want to learn more about the underlying mechanisms, you probably want to read Martin Fowlers article about <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/collection-pipeline/">Collection Pipelines</a>.</p>

<p>If you&#39;re interested in JavaScript as well, you may want to have a look at <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/streamjs">Stream.js</a> - a JavaScript implementation of the Java 8 Streams API. You may also wanna read my <a href="/posts/2014/03/16/java-8-tutorial/">Java 8 Tutorial</a> and my <a href="/posts/2014/04/05/java8-nashorn-tutorial/">Java 8 Nashorn Tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>Hopefully this tutorial was helpful to you and you&#39;ve enjoyed reading it. The full source code of the tutorial samples is <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial">hosted on GitHub</a>. Feel free to <a href="https://github.com/winterbe/java8-tutorial/fork">fork the repository</a> or send me your feedback via <a href="https://twitter.com/winterbe_">Twitter</a>.</p>

<p>Happy coding!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrate Maven Projects to Java 11]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15358753472382.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T16:02:27+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15358753472382.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://winterbe.com/posts/2018/08/29/migrate-maven-projects-to-java-11-jigsaw/">https://winterbe.com/posts/2018/08/29/migrate-maven-projects-to-java-11-jigsaw/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>So you want to migrate to Java 11 but your Maven project is still sitting on Java 8? You don&#39;t care much about the new <a href="https://www.oracle.com/corporate/features/understanding-java-9-modules.html">module system</a> (Jigsaw) introduced in Java 9, you just want your application to run on the latest JDK version? Then this guide is for you. It includes everything I&#39;ve learned while migrating our product to Java 11.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>As of 2019 Oracle Java 8 will no longer receive free security updates. So now is the time to migrate to <a href="http://jdk.java.net/11/">JDK 11</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_0">Clean up your <code>pom.xml</code> files<a href="#clean-up-your-pom-xml-files" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The first thing you should do before even thinking about upgrading the Java version is to clean up your <code>pom.xml</code> files. If your project is a multi-module Maven project then it helps to establish a parent POM and maintain <code>dependencyManagement</code> und <code>pluginManagement</code> in this file. That way all your plugins and dependencies are defined in a single file and are not spread across multiple POM files what makes managing versions easier.</p>

<p>In order to migrate your project to the latest Java version 11 it&#39;s highly recommended to update as much plugins and dependencies to the latest stable version as possible. Many plugins such as the compiler plugin, surefire or failsafe are not compatible with Java 9 if you use older versions. Also a lot of libraries are incompatible without migrating to the latest version.</p>

<p>Make sure you have the versions plugin configured in your master POM:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;plugin&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.codehaus.mojo&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;versions-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.5&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;configuration&gt;
        &lt;generateBackupPoms&gt;false&lt;/generateBackupPoms&gt;
    &lt;/configuration&gt;
&lt;/plugin&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>This plugin helps finding the latest plugin or dependency versions for your modules. Open up the terminal and execute this command to find the plugin versions you have to update:</p>

<pre><code>mvn versions:display-plugin-updates

</code></pre>

<p>You will see a list of plugins used in your project with newer versions available. Update all of those plugins to the lastest stable version. After you&#39;ve updated your plugin versions make sure that your project still compiles and runs properly.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>You can use <code>mvn -N ...</code> from your projects root directory to just check your parent POM in case of multi-module projects.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_1">Configure plugins for Java 11<a href="#configure-plugins-for-java-11" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>The most important plugins for Java 11 are the compiler plugin, surefire (for unit-tests) and failsafe (for integration-tests).</p>

<p>In order to compile your project for Java 11 add the <code>release</code> configuration to the compiler plugin, a new compiler parameter to replace the <code>source</code> and <code>target</code> version parameters:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;plugin&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-compiler-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.8.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;configuration&gt;
        &lt;release&gt;11&lt;/release&gt;
    &lt;/configuration&gt;
&lt;/plugin&gt;

</code></pre>

<blockquote>
<p>Also don&#39;t forget to set your IDEs project SDK to same JDK version. In Intellij IDEA go to Module Settings -&gt; Project -&gt; SDK.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For surefire and failsafe plugins we add an additional argument <code>--illegal-access=permit</code> to allow all reflection access for third party libraries:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;plugin&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-surefire-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.22.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;configuration&gt;
        &lt;argLine&gt;
            --illegal-access=permit
        &lt;/argLine&gt;
    &lt;/configuration&gt;
&lt;/plugin&gt;
&lt;plugin&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;maven-failsafe-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.22.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;configuration&gt;
        &lt;argLine&gt;
            --illegal-access=permit
        &lt;/argLine&gt;
    &lt;/configuration&gt;
&lt;/plugin&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>This is only needed if your dependencies make heavy use of reflection. If you&#39;re unsure whether you need this you can add the <code>argLine</code> later if your tests run into trouble.</p>

<p>You&#39;ll see warnings like this when a library tries to illegally access classes via <code>setAccessible(true)</code>:</p>

<pre><code>WARNING: Please consider reporting this to the maintainers of org.codehaus.groovy.reflection.CachedClass
WARNING: Use --illegal-access=warn to enable warnings of further illegal reflective access operations
WARNING: All illegal access operations will be denied in a future release

</code></pre>

<blockquote>
<p>Keep in mind that later you probably also have to pass the <code>--illegal-access=permit</code> parameter when starting your application.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_2">Update dependencies<a href="#update-dependencies" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>As mentioned before the best thing you can do is to migrate all your dependencies to the latest stable versions to make sure everything works fine with Java 11. While many older dependencies might work just fine there&#39;s a couple of dependencies where version updates are mandatory, e.g. all those various bytecode enhancement libaries such as <code>javassist</code>, <code>cglib</code>, <code>asm</code> or <code>byte-buddy</code>. Those libraries often come as transitive dependencies so make sure at least those libaries are up-to-date.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.javassist&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;javassist&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.23.1-GA&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;cglib&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;cglib-nodep&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.2.7&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;

</code></pre>

<p>This command helps to find outdated dependency versions from your modules:</p>

<pre><code>mvn versions:display-dependency-updates

</code></pre>

<p>Update as much libaries as possible to the latest stable version. If there&#39;s some dependency that you can&#39;t update due to compatibility issues in your project than leave it as is. Chances are that it just runs fine with Java 11.</p>

<p>Now is a good time to compile your project with JDK 11 for the first time:</p>

<pre><code>mvn clean test-compile compile

</code></pre>

<blockquote>
<p>Hint: You can speed up multi-module Maven projects by using parallel builds, e.g. <code>mvn -T 4 compile</code> compiles all modules in parallel on 4 CPU cores.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You will eventually face different compiler errors such as <code>ClassNotFoundException</code>. Every project is different so I cannot provide solutions for every problem you will face. The rest of this article describes solutions to various problems we had to solve in order to run our application with JDK 11.</p>

<h3 id="toc_3">Add missing modules<a href="#add-missing-modules" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>With the introduction of the Java module system (Jigsaw) in Java 9 the Java standard libary has been divided into separate modules. While most classes are still available without any changes, some are not. You have to explicitely define which additional modules your application needs access to or you can just add those modules from the Maven central repository.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The command <code>java --list-modules</code> lists all available modules.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When migrating our web project to Java 11 we had to add <code>jaxb</code> and <code>javax.annotations</code> to prevent <code>ClassNotFoundException</code>. We&#39;ve added the following libaries as additional Maven dependencies to our POMs:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;javax.annotation&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;javax.annotation-api&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;1.3.2&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;javax.xml.bind&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;jaxb-api&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.4.0-b180725.0427&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.glassfish.jaxb&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;jaxb-runtime&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;2.4.0-b180725.0644&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;

</code></pre>

<blockquote>
<p>Instead of adding those libaries via Maven we could utilize the <code>add-modules</code> Java parameter to add additional JDK modules to the project.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_4">Fixing <code>sun.*</code> and <code>com.sun.*</code> imports<a href="#fixing-sun-and-com-sun-imports" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>While some classes have been moved to additional Java modules other classes can no longer been used in user code, namely classes from <code>sun.*</code> packages and also some classes from <code>com.sun.*</code>. If you get compiler errors because your code links to classes from those packages you have to remove those imports from your code.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s a few things we had to fix in our project:</p>

<ul>
<li>  <code>sun.misc.BASE64Encoder</code>: This can simply be replaced by <code>java.util.Base64.getEncoder()</code> which is available since Java 8.</li>
<li>  <code>sun.reflect.generics.reflectiveObjects.ParameterizedTypeImpl</code>: This class has accidentally been used in our code base and can simply be replaced by the interface type <code>java.lang.reflect.ParameterizedType</code>.</li>
<li>  <code>sun.reflect.annotation.AnnotationParser</code>: We use this class to programmatically create annotation instances. The class is no longer accessible but can be replaced by <code>AnnotationFactory</code> from Hibernate Validator.</li>
<li>  <code>com.sun.org.apache.xml.internal.utils.DefaultErrorHandler</code>: We&#39;ve replaced this class with a custom implementation of the interface.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="toc_5">Currency formats<a href="#currency-formats" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>We&#39;ve encountered a curious case with number formats for locales such as <code>Locale.GERMANY</code> which let a bunch of our tests fail with a rather strange assertion error:</p>

<pre><code>java.lang.AssertionError:
Expected: is &quot;9,80 &quot;
     but: was &quot;9,80&quot;

</code></pre>

<p>The underlying code uses <code>NumberFormat.getCurrencyInstance(Locale.GERMANY)</code> to format numbers into the german currency format. So what the heck is happening here?</p>

<p>Javas number formats have been modified to use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-breaking_space">non-breaking spaces</a> instead of normal spaces between the number and the currency symbol. This change makes perfectly sense because it prevents line-breaks between the number and the currency symbol in various presentation formats. Changing the strings in our tests to use non-breaking spaces (use OPTION SPACE on Mac OSX keyboards) fixed this issue.</p>

<h3 id="toc_6">Servlet Container<a href="#servlet-container" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>When running web applications with Apache Tomcat you need at least Apache Tomcat 7.0.85 or later. Otherwise Tomcat will not start on Java 9 and above and you would see the following error:</p>

<pre><code>/path/to/apache-tomcat-7.0.64/bin/catalina.sh run
-Djava.endorsed.dirs=/path/to/apache-tomcat-7.0.64/endorsed is not supported. Endorsed standards and standalone APIs
Error: Could not create the Java Virtual Machine.
Error: A fatal exception has occurred. Program will exit.
in modular form will be supported via the concept of upgradeable modules.
Disconnected from server

</code></pre>

<p>Also don&#39;t forget to eventually add the additional startup parameter <code>--illegal-access=permit</code> to your servlet container.</p>

<h3 id="toc_7">That&#39;s all<a href="#thats-all" title="Permalink to this section">#</a></h3>

<p>I hope these tips are somewhat useful to you and helps you migrating your application from Java 8 to 11. If you like this guide please consider sharing the link with your followers. Also <a href="https://twitter.com/winterbe_">let me know on Twitter</a> if your migration was successful.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zookeeper ]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15356007721649.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-30T11:46:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15356007721649.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://juejin.im/post/5a3b542d6fb9a0452725c25f">https://juejin.im/post/5a3b542d6fb9a0452725c25f</a></p>

<p> Zookeeper  Release 3.4.11 </p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="toc_0">Zookeeper</h2>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="#1">Zookeeper: <code></code></a>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="#1.1">Zookeeper </a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.2">Zookeeper<code></code><code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.3">Zookeeper<code></code><code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.4">Zookeeper<code></code><code></code>(watches)</a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.5">Zookeeper<code></code>(Guarantees)</a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.6">Zookeeper<code>API</code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.7">Zookeeper<code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.8">Zookeeper<code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.9">Zookeeper<code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.10">Zookeeper<code></code></a></li>
<li>  <a href="#1.11">Zookeeper </a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="toc_1"><a id="1">Zookeeper: <code></code></a></h3>

<p>ZooKeeper <code></code><code></code><code></code>Zookeeper  java  java  c  (binding)</p>

<p><code></code>ZooKeeper </p>

<h3 id="toc_2"><a id="1.1"></a></h3>

<h5 id="toc_3">Zookeeper </h5>

<p>ZooKeeper <code>znode</code> ZooKeeper ZooKeeper  ZooKeeper </p>

<p>Zookeeper ZooKeeper </p>

<h5 id="toc_4">Zookeeper replicated</h5>

<p>Zookeeper  ensemble </p>

<p><img src="media/15356007721649/15356009470781.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> Zookeeper  (Service)  (server)  (servers)  ZooKeeper </p>

<p> (client)  ZooKeeper  TCP  TCP </p>

<h5 id="toc_5">Zokeeper </h5>

<p>ZooKeeper  ZooKeeper </p>

<h5 id="toc_6">ZooKeeper </h5>

<p>  ZooKeeper  101</p>

<h3 id="toc_7"><a id="1.2">Zookeeper </a></h3>

<p>ZooKeeper <code>/</code> ZooKeeper <br/>
<img src="media/15356007721649/15356009665985.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<h3 id="toc_8"><a id="1.3">Zookeeper<code></code><code></code></a></h3>

<p>ZooKeeper ZooKeeper  (byte)  (kb)  znode  ZooKeeper </p>

<p>Znode  (<code>stat</code>) ACL znode </p>

<p> znode </p>

<p>ZooKeeper </p>

<h3 id="toc_9"><a id="1.4">Zookeeper<code></code><code></code>(watches)</a></h3>

<p>ZooKeeper  (watches)  znode  (watch) znode (watch)  (watch)    znode  Zookeeper </p>

<h3 id="toc_10"><a id="1.5">Zookeeper<code></code>(Guarantees)</a></h3>

<p>Zookeeper   </p>

<ul>
<li>   - </li>
<li>   - </li>
<li>   -  Zookeeper </li>
<li>   - </li>
<li>   - </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="toc_11"><a id="1.6"> API</a></h3>

<p>ZooKeeper  </p>

<ul>
<li><p>###### create</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### delete</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### exists</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### get data</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### set data</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### get children</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>###### sync</p>

<blockquote>
<p></p>
</blockquote></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="toc_12"><a id="1.7">Zookeeper<code></code></a></h3>

<p><a href="https://link.juejin.im?target=http%3A%2F%2Fzookeeper.apache.org%2Fdoc%2Fr3.4.11%2FzookeeperOver.html%23fg_zkComponents">ZooKeeper Components</a>  ZooKeeper <code>Request Processor</code> ZooKeeper </p>

<p><img src="media/15356007721649/15356009879352.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><code>replicated database</code></p>

<p> Zookeeper  Zookeeper  Zookeeper </p>

<p> leader follower leader proposal leader  leader  follower </p>

<p>Zookeeper Zookeeper  leader </p>

<h3 id="toc_13"><a id="1.8"></a></h3>

<p>Zookeeper </p>

<h3 id="toc_14"><a id="1.9"></a></h3>

<p>Zookeeper  Zookeeper Zookeeper         </p>

<p>Zookeeper </p>

<p><img src="media/15356007721649/15356010042046.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> Zookeeper   Zookeeper3.2  Dual 2Gh Xeon + 2  15K RPM  SATA  Zookeeper  1K  1K Servers  Zookeeper Ensemble  Zookeeper  30 Zookeeper Ensemble  Leader </p>

<p>3.2  /  3.1  2 </p>

<p> Zookeeper    Zookeeper </p>

<ol>
<li><p> Follower </p></li>
<li><p> Follower </p></li>
<li><p>Leader </p></li>
<li><p> Follower </p></li>
<li><p> Leader </p></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="toc_15"><a id="1.10"></a></h3>

<p><img src="media/15356007721649/15356010153963.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> follower Zookeeper leader Zookeeper  200  leader follower Zookeeper </p>

<h3 id="toc_16"><a id="1.11"> ZooKeeper </a></h3>

<p>Zookeeper Zookeeper Zookeeper  Zookeeper </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MySQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15353470248085.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-27T13:17:04+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15353470248085.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<h2 id="toc_0">JDBC Connect failed</h2>

<blockquote>
<p>Check VPN Global Mode</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="toc_1">Version 8+</h2>

<blockquote>
<p>&quot;Public Key Retrieval is not allowed&quot;</p>

<p>/usr/local/var/mysql/ca.pem</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Here are examples of everything new in ECMAScript 2016, 2017, and2018]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15352961449208.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T23:09:04+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15352961449208.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/here-are-examples-of-everything-new-in-ecmascript-2016-2017-and-2018-d52fa3b5a70e">https://medium.freecodecamp.org/here-are-examples-of-everything-new-in-ecmascript-2016-2017-and-2018-d52fa3b5a70e</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*Z-9unq6Am3vekNOa5fD1xg.png" alt=""/></p>

<p>Its hard to keep track of whats new in JavaScript (ECMAScript). And its even harder to find useful code examples.</p>

<p>So in this article, Ill cover all 18 features that are listed in the <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposals/blob/master/finished-proposals.md">TC39s finished proposals</a> that were added in ES2016, ES2017, and ES2018 (final draft) and show them with useful examples.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>This is a pretty long post but should be an easy read. Think of this as <strong>Netflix binge reading.</strong> By the end of this, I promise that youll have a ton of knowledge about all these features.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="toc_0"><strong>OK, lets go over these one byone.</strong></h4>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*K09EWrqTcTwN9_dlhlzy6Q.png" alt=""/></p>

<h3 id="toc_1"><code>1\. Array.prototype.includes</code></h3>

<p><code>includes</code> is a simple instance method on the Array and helps to easily find if an item is in the Array (including <code>NaN</code> unlike <code>indexOf</code>).</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OhhFTNabUEz8ZeI4vaCIJw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2016 or ES7Array.prototype.includes()</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Trivia: the JavaScript spec people wanted to name it <code>contains</code>, but this was apparently already used by Mootools so they used <code>includes</code>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="toc_2"><code>2\.</code> Exponentiation <code>infixoperator</code></h4>

<p>Math operations like addition and subtraction have infix operators like <code>+</code> and <code>-</code>, respectively. Similar to them, the <code>**</code> infix operator is commonly used for exponent operation. In ECMAScript 2016, the <code>**</code> was introduced instead of <code>Math.pow</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*c1k1vgBgGaam7XA8xAp49w.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*c1k1vgBgGaam7XA8xAp49w.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*c1k1vgBgGaam7XA8xAp49w.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2016 or ES7** Exponent infixoperator<img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*fV_95TaY3ocgE8hlDhhv8w.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*fV_95TaY3ocgE8hlDhhv8w.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*fV_95TaY3ocgE8hlDhhv8w.png" alt=""/></p>

<h3 id="toc_3">1. Object.values()</h3>

<p><code>Object.values()</code> is a new function thats similar to <code>Object.keys()</code> but returns all the values of the Objects own properties excluding any value(s) in the prototypical chain.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*OkcC2Sozg0MKvkaqZWxmnw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OkcC2Sozg0MKvkaqZWxmnw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OkcC2Sozg0MKvkaqZWxmnw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES8) Object.values()</p>

<h3 id="toc_4">2. Object.entries()</h3>

<p><code>Object.entries()</code> is related to <code>Object.keys</code>, but instead of returning just keys, it returns both keys and values in the array fashion. This makes it very simple to do things like using objects in loops or converting objects into Maps.</p>

<p><strong>Example 1:</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*23RYJzstZ7iMxKNYbfAAWg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*23RYJzstZ7iMxKNYbfAAWg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*23RYJzstZ7iMxKNYbfAAWg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES8)Using Object.entries() inloops</p>

<p><strong>Example 2:</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*XAXiVkw2zKyBio4OX6DQoQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*XAXiVkw2zKyBio4OX6DQoQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*XAXiVkw2zKyBio4OX6DQoQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES8)Using Object.entries() to convert Object toMap</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">3. Stringpadding</h3>

<p>Two instance methods were added to String<code>String.prototype.padStart</code> and <code>String.prototype.padEnd</code>that allow appending/prepending either an empty string or some other string to the start or the end of the original string.</p>

<pre>'someString'.padStart(numberOfCharcters [,stringForPadding]); </pre>

<pre>'5'.padStart(10) // '          5'
'5'.padStart(10, '=*') //'=*=*=*=*=5'</pre>

<pre>'5'.padEnd(10) // '5         '
'5'.padEnd(10, '=*') //'5=*=*=*=*='</pre>

<blockquote>
<p>This comes in handy when we want to align things in scenarios like pretty print display or terminal print.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="toc_6">3.1 padStartexample:</h4>

<p>In the below example, we have a list of numbers of varying lengths. We want to prepend 0 so that all the items have the same length of 10 digits for display purposes. We can use <code>padStart(10, &#39;0&#39;)</code> to easily achieve this.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*KLrT9Xmh43cIi2MFUmIfcw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*KLrT9Xmh43cIi2MFUmIfcw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*KLrT9Xmh43cIi2MFUmIfcw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017padStartexample</p>

<h4 id="toc_7">3.2 padEndexample:</h4>

<p><code>padEnd</code> really comes in handy when we are printing multiple items of varying lengths and want to right-align them properly.</p>

<p>The example below is a good realistic example of how <code>padEnd</code>, <code>padStart</code>, and <code>Object.entries</code> all come together to produce a beautiful output.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*fLXPci_E_yXK9uSqLz-axQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*fLXPci_E_yXK9uSqLz-axQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*fLXPci_E_yXK9uSqLz-axQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017padEnd, padStart and Object.Entries example</p>

<pre>const cars = {
  'BMW': '10',
  'Tesla': '5',
  'Lamborghini': '0'
}</pre>

<pre>Object.entries(cars).map(([name, count]) => {
  //padEnd appends ' -' until the name becomes 20 characters
  //padStart prepends '0' until the count becomes 3 characters.
  console.log(`${name.padEnd(20, ' -')} Count: ${count.padStart(3, '0')}`)
});</pre>

<pre>//Prints..
// BMW - - - - - - -  Count: 010
// Tesla - - - - - -  Count: 005
// Lamborghini - - -  Count: 000</pre>

<h4 id="toc_8">3.3  padStart and padEnd on Emojis and other double-byte chars</h4>

<p>Emojis and other double-byte chars are represented using multiple bytes of unicode. So padStart and padEnd might not work as expected!</p>

<p>For example: Lets say we are trying to pad the string <code>heart</code> to reach <code>10</code> characters with the  emoji. The result will look like below:</p>

<pre>//Notice that instead of 5 hearts, there are only 2 hearts and 1 heart that looks odd!
'heart'.padStart(10, ""); // prints.. 'heart'</pre>

<p>This is because  is 2 code points long (<code>&#39;\u2764\uFE0F&#39;</code> )! The word <code>heart</code> itself is 5 characters, so we only have a total of 5 chars left to pad. So what happens is that JS pads two hearts using <code>&#39;\u2764\uFE0F&#39;</code> and that produces . For the last one it simply uses the first byte of the heart <code>\u2764</code> which produces </p>

<p>So we end up with: <code>heart</code></p>

<blockquote>
<p>PS: You may use <a href="https://encoder.internetwache.org/#tab_uni">this link</a> to check out unicode char conversions.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_9">4. <code>Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors</code></h3>

<p>This method returns all the details (including getter <code>get</code>and setter <code>set</code> methods) for all the properties of a given object. The main motivation to add this is to allow shallow copying / cloning an object into another objectthat also copies getter and setter functions as opposed to <code>Object.assign</code><strong>.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Object.assign shallow copies all the details except getter and setter functions of the original source object.</strong></p>

<p>The example below shows the difference between <code>Object.assign</code> and <code>Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors</code> along with <code>Object.defineProperties</code> to copy an original object <code>Car</code> into a new object <code>ElectricCar</code>. Youll see that by using <code>Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors</code>,<code>discount</code> getter and setter functions are also copied into the target object.</p>

<p>BEFORE</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*7r4pk8hfx5VQ9-ERu--xCw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*7r4pk8hfx5VQ9-ERu--xCw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*7r4pk8hfx5VQ9-ERu--xCw.png" alt=""/>BeforeUsing Object.assign</p>

<p>AFTER</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*gvlG4DfnkiOrlgPsQrjLfg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*gvlG4DfnkiOrlgPsQrjLfg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*gvlG4DfnkiOrlgPsQrjLfg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES8)Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors</p>

<pre>var Car = {
 name: 'BMW',
 price: 1000000,
 set discount(x) {
  this.d = x;
 },
 get discount() {
  return this.d;
 },
};</pre>

<pre>//Print details of Car object's 'discount' property
console.log(Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptor(Car, 'discount'));
//prints..
// { 
//   get: [Function: get],
//   set: [Function: set],
//   enumerable: true,
//   configurable: true
// }</pre>

<pre>//Copy Car's properties to ElectricCar using Object.assign
const ElectricCar = Object.assign({}, Car);</pre>

<pre>//Print details of ElectricCar object's 'discount' property
console.log(Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptor(ElectricCar, 'discount'));
//prints..
// { 
//   value: undefined,
//   writable: true,
//   enumerable: true,
//   configurable: true 

// }
//Notice that getters and setters are missing in ElectricCar object for 'discount' property !</pre>

<pre>//Copy Car's properties to ElectricCar2 using Object.defineProperties 
//and extract Car's properties using Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors
const ElectricCar2 = Object.defineProperties({}, Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptors(Car));</pre>

<pre>//Print details of ElectricCar2 object's 'discount' property
console.log(Object.getOwnPropertyDescriptor(ElectricCar2, 'discount'));
//prints..
// { get: [Function: get],  
//   set: [Function: set],  
//   enumerable: true,
//   configurable: true 
// }
// Notice that getters and setters are present in the ElectricCar2 object for 'discount' property!</pre>

<h3 id="toc_10">5. <code>Add trailing commas in the function parameters</code></h3>

<p>This is a minor update that allows us to have trailing commas after the last function parameter. Why? To help with tools like git blame to ensure only new developers get blamed.</p>

<p>The below example shows the problem and the solution.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*-SKZCxQdf8Rk48SSaPtDGg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*-SKZCxQdf8Rk48SSaPtDGg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*-SKZCxQdf8Rk48SSaPtDGg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES 8)Trailing comma in function paramameter</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Note: You can also call functions with trailing commas!</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="toc_11">6. Async/Await</h3>

<p>This, by far, is the most important and most useful feature if you ask me. Async functions allows us to not deal with callback hell and make the entire code look simple.</p>

<p>The <code>async</code> keyword tells the JavaScript compiler to treat the function differently. The compiler pauses whenever it reaches the <code>await</code> keyword within that function. It assumes that the expression after <code>await</code> returns a promise and waits until the promise is resolved or rejected before moving further.</p>

<p>In the example below, the <code>getAmount</code> function is calling two asynchronous functions <code>getUser</code> and <code>getBankBalance</code>. We can do this in promise, but using <code>async await</code> is more elegant and simple.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*L3FZ0onbBD4ay6UhZvPoMw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*L3FZ0onbBD4ay6UhZvPoMw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*L3FZ0onbBD4ay6UhZvPoMw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES 8)Async Await basicexample</p>

<h4 id="toc_12"><strong>6.1</strong> Async functions themselves return aPromise.</h4>

<p>If you are waiting for the result from an async function, you need to use Promises <code>then</code> syntax to capture its result.</p>

<p>In the following example, we want to log the result using <code>console.log</code> but not within the doubleAndAdd. So we want to wait and use <code>then</code> syntax to pass the result to <code>console.log</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*ylheY6gJawprWEVNL68mRQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ylheY6gJawprWEVNL68mRQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ylheY6gJawprWEVNL68mRQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES 8)Async Await themselves returnsPromise</p>

<h4 id="toc_13"><strong>6.2 Calling async/await inparallel</strong></h4>

<p>In the previous example we are calling await twice, but each time we are waiting for one second (total 2 seconds). Instead we can parallelize it since <code>a</code> and <code>b</code> are not dependent on each other using <code>Promise.all</code>.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*VEF_Sq067Liq4lfTV8Xv0A.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*VEF_Sq067Liq4lfTV8Xv0A.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*VEF_Sq067Liq4lfTV8Xv0A.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017 (ES 8)Using Promise.all to parallelize async/await</p>

<h4 id="toc_14">6.3 Error handling async/await functions</h4>

<p>There are various ways to handle errors when using async await.</p>

<h4 id="toc_15"><strong>Option 1Use try catch within thefunction</strong></h4>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*iP84ax2TOt5dbaIjW7kzcw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*iP84ax2TOt5dbaIjW7kzcw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*iP84ax2TOt5dbaIjW7kzcw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017<strong>Use try catch within the async/await function</strong></p>

<pre>//Option 1 - Use try catch within the function
async function doubleAndAdd(a, b) {
 try {
  a = await doubleAfter1Sec(a);
  b = await doubleAfter1Sec(b);
 } catch (e) {
  return NaN; //return something
 }</pre>

<pre>return a + b;
}
//Usage:
doubleAndAdd('one', 2).then(console.log); // NaN
doubleAndAdd(1, 2).then(console.log); // 6</pre>

<pre>function doubleAfter1Sec(param) {
 return new Promise((resolve, reject) => {
  setTimeout(function() {
   let val = param * 2;
   isNaN(val) ? reject(NaN) : resolve(val);
  }, 1000);
 });
}</pre>

<h4 id="toc_16"><strong>Option 2 Catch every await expression</strong></h4>

<p>Since every <code>await</code> expression returns a Promise, you can catch errors on each line as shown below.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*Bkls3dXMIRGKAwFN2r--qg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Bkls3dXMIRGKAwFN2r--qg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Bkls3dXMIRGKAwFN2r--qg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017<strong>Use try catch every await expression</strong></p>

<pre>//Option 2 - *Catch* errors on  every await line
//as each await expression is a Promise in itself
async function doubleAndAdd(a, b) {
 a = await doubleAfter1Sec(a).catch(e => console.log('"a" is NaN')); // 
 b = await doubleAfter1Sec(b).catch(e => console.log('"b" is NaN')); // 
 if (!a || !b) {
  return NaN;
 }
 return a + b;
}</pre>

<pre>//Usage:
doubleAndAdd('one', 2).then(console.log); // NaN  and logs:  "a" is NaN
doubleAndAdd(1, 2).then(console.log); // 6</pre>

<pre>function doubleAfter1Sec(param) {
 return new Promise((resolve, reject) => {
  setTimeout(function() {
   let val = param * 2;
   isNaN(val) ? reject(NaN) : resolve(val);
  }, 1000);
 });
}</pre>

<h4 id="toc_17"><strong>Option 3Catch the entire async-await function</strong></h4>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*hhkv5ZBOUYViCL2UP0sv5Q.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*hhkv5ZBOUYViCL2UP0sv5Q.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*hhkv5ZBOUYViCL2UP0sv5Q.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2017<strong>Catch the entire async/await function at theend</strong></p>

<pre>//Option 3 - Dont do anything but handle outside the function
//since async / await returns a promise, we can catch the whole function's error
async function doubleAndAdd(a, b) {
 a = await doubleAfter1Sec(a);
 b = await doubleAfter1Sec(b);
 return a + b;
}</pre>

<pre>//Usage:
doubleAndAdd('one', 2)
.then(console.log)
.catch(console.log); // <------- use "catch"</pre>

<pre>function doubleAfter1Sec(param) {
 return new Promise((resolve, reject) => {
  setTimeout(function() {
   let val = param * 2;
   isNaN(val) ? reject(NaN) : resolve(val);
  }, 1000);
 });
}</pre>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*X755b572fEcI0vK0fRKWkw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*X755b572fEcI0vK0fRKWkw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*X755b572fEcI0vK0fRKWkw.png" alt=""/></p>

<blockquote>
<p>ECMAScript is currently in final draft and will be out in June or July 2018. All the features covered below are in Stage-4 and will be part of ECMAScript 2018.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="toc_18">1. <a href="https://github.com/tc39/ecmascript_sharedmem">Shared memory andatomics</a></h4>

<p>This is a huge, pretty advanced feature and is a core enhancement to JS engines.</p>

<p><strong>The main idea is to bring some sort of multi-threading feature to JavaScript so that JS developers can write high-performance, concurrent programs in the future by allowing to manage memory by themselves instead of letting JS engine manage memory.</strong></p>

<p>This is done by a new type of a global object called <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/SharedArrayBuffer">SharedArrayBuffer</a> that essentially stores data in a <strong>_shared_</strong> <strong>memory space</strong>. So this data can be shared between the main JS thread and web-worker threads.</p>

<p>Until now, if we want to share data between the main JS thread and web-workers, we had to copy the data and send it to the other thread using <code>postMessage</code>. Not anymore!</p>

<p>You simply use SharedArrayBuffer and the data is instantly accessible by both the main thread and multiple web-worker threads.</p>

<p>But sharing memory between threads can cause race conditions. To help avoid race conditions, the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Atomics">_Atomics_</a> global object is introduced. <u>Atomics</u> provides various methods to lock the shared memory when a thread is using its data. It also provides methods to update such data in that shared memory safely.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The recommendation is to use this feature via some library, but right now there are no libraries built on top of this feature.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you are interested, I recommend reading:</p>

<ol>
<li> <a href="http://lucasfcosta.com/2017/04/30/JavaScript-From-Workers-to-Shared-Memory.html">_From Workers to Shared Memor_</a>_y_<a href="http://lucasfcosta.com/">_lucasfcosta_</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/category/code-cartoons/a-cartoon-intro-to-sharedarraybuffers/">_A cartoon intro to SharedArrayBuffers_</a>__<a href="https://medium.com/@linclark">_Lin Clark_</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://2ality.com/2017/01/shared-array-buffer.html">_Shared memory and atomics_</a>__<a href="http://rauschma.de/">_Dr. Axel Rauschmayer_</a></li>
</ol>

<h4 id="toc_19">2. Tagged Template literal restriction removed</h4>

<p>First, we need to clarify what a Tagged Template literal is so we can understand this feature better.</p>

<p>In ES2015+, there is a feature called a tagged template literal that allows developers to customize how strings are interpolated. For example, in the standard way strings are interpolated like below</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*4EizdrE9LlRZ5GXRq4G3Yw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*4EizdrE9LlRZ5GXRq4G3Yw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*4EizdrE9LlRZ5GXRq4G3Yw.png" alt=""/></p>

<p>In the tagged literal, you can write a function to receive the hardcoded parts of the string literal, for example <code>[ Hello , ! ]</code>, and the replacement variables, for example,<code>[ &#39;Raja&#39;]</code>, as parameters into a custom function (for example <code>greet</code> ), and return whatever you want from that custom function.</p>

<p>The below example shows that our custom Tag function <code>greet</code> appends time of the day like Good Morning! Good afternoon, and so on depending on the time of the day to the string literal and returns a custom string.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*PfeJ5R0h6SHx6SxSkPCLmg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*PfeJ5R0h6SHx6SxSkPCLmg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*PfeJ5R0h6SHx6SxSkPCLmg.png" alt=""/>Tag function example that shows custom string interpolation</p>

<pre>//A "Tag" function returns a custom string literal.
//In this example, greet calls timeGreet() to append Good //Morning/Afternoon/Evening depending on the time of the day.</pre>

<pre>function greet(hardCodedPartsArray, ...replacementPartsArray) {
 console.log(hardCodedPartsArray); //[ 'Hello ', '!' ]
 console.log(replacementPartsArray); //[ 'Raja' ]</pre>

<pre>let str = '';
 hardCodedPartsArray.forEach((string, i) => {
  if (i < replacementPartsArray.length) {
   str += `${string} ${replacementPartsArray[i] || ''}`;
  } else {
   str += `${string} ${timeGreet()}`; //<-- append Good morning/afternoon/evening here
  }
 });
 return str;
}</pre>

<pre>//Usage:
const firstName = 'Raja';
const greetings = greet`Hello ${firstName}!`; //<-- Tagged literal</pre>

<pre>console.log(greetings); //'Hello  Raja! Good Morning!' </pre>

<pre>function timeGreet() {
 const hr = new Date().getHours();
 return hr < 12
  ? 'Good Morning!'
  : hr < 18 ? 'Good Afternoon!' : 'Good Evening!';
}</pre>

<p>Now that we discussed what Tagged functions are, many people want to use this feature in different domains, like in Terminal for commands and HTTP requests for composing URIs, and so on.</p>

<h4 id="toc_20">The problem with Tagged Stringliteral</h4>

<p>The problem is that ES2015 and ES2016 specs doesnt allow using escape characters like \u (unicode), \x(hexadecimal) unless they look exactly like <code>\u00A9</code> or \u{2F804} or \xA9.</p>

<p>So if you have a Tagged function that internally uses some other domains rules (like Terminals rules), that may need to use <strong>\ubla123abla</strong> that doesnt look like \u0049 or \u{@F804}, then you would get a syntax error.</p>

<p>In ES2018, the rules are relaxed to allow such seemingly invalid escape characters as long as the Tagged function returns the values in an object with a cooked property (where invalid characters are undefined), and then a raw property (with whatever you want).</p>

<pre><code>function myTagFunc(str) {  return { &quot;cooked&quot;: &quot;undefined&quot;, &quot;raw&quot;: str.raw[0] }} var str = myTagFunc `hi \
</code></pre>

<h3 id="toc_21">3. dotall flag for Regular expression</h3>

<p>Currently in RegEx, although the dot(.) is supposed to match a single character, it doesnt match new line characters like <code>\n \r \f etc</code>.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<pre>//Before
/first.second/.test('first\nsecond'); //false</pre>

<p>This enhancement makes it possible for the dot operator to match any single character. In order to ensure this doesnt break anything, we need to use <code>\s</code> flag when we create the RegEx for this to work.</p>

<pre>//ECMAScript 2018
/first.second**/s**.test('first\nsecond'); **//true**   Notice: /s </pre>

<p>Here is the overall API from the <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-regexp-dotall-flag">proposal</a> doc:</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*t5xegqe5su6XgRDcBObyDw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*t5xegqe5su6XgRDcBObyDw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*t5xegqe5su6XgRDcBObyDw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Regex dotAll feature allows matching even \n via . via /sflag</p>

<h3 id="toc_22">4. RegExp Named Group Captures</h3>

<p>This enhancement brings a useful RegExp feature from other languages like Python, Java and so on called Named Groups. This features allows developers writing RegExp to provide names (identifiers) in the format<code>(?&lt;name&gt;...)</code> for different parts of the group in the RegExp. They can then use that name to grab whichever group they need with ease.</p>

<h4 id="toc_23">4.1 Basic Named groupexample</h4>

<p>In the below example, we are using <code>(?&lt;year&gt;) (?&lt;month&gt;) and (?&lt;day&gt;)</code> names to group different parts of the date RegEx. The resulting object will now contain a <code>groups</code> property with properties <code>year</code>, <code>month</code>, and <code>day</code> with corresponding values.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*1ORiZapMHp_SV5gvOVT2WA.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*1ORiZapMHp_SV5gvOVT2WA.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*1ORiZapMHp_SV5gvOVT2WA.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Regex named groupsexample</p>

<h4 id="toc_24"><strong>4.2 Using Named groups inside regexitself</strong></h4>

<p>We can use the <code>\k&lt;group name&gt;</code> format to back reference the group within the regex itself. The following example shows how it works.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*O6i-gXHBifD27qD73Sw7TA.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*O6i-gXHBifD27qD73Sw7TA.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*O6i-gXHBifD27qD73Sw7TA.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Regex named groups back referencing via \k<groupname></p>

<h4 id="toc_25"><strong>4.3 Using named groups in String.prototype.replace</strong></h4>

<p>The named group feature is now baked into Strings <code>replace</code> instance method. So we can easily swap words in the string.</p>

<p>For example, change firstName, lastName to lastName, firstName.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*weBLy9CAXFnWNwUqcwNMAg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*weBLy9CAXFnWNwUqcwNMAg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*weBLy9CAXFnWNwUqcwNMAg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Using RegExs named groups feature in replacefunction</p>

<h3 id="toc_26">5. Rest properties forObjects</h3>

<p>Rest operator<code>...</code> (three dots) allows us to extract Object properties that are not already extracted.</p>

<h4 id="toc_27"><strong>5.1 You can use rest to help extract only properties youwant</strong></h4>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*Uh4-1F3aeoy5k3hq8nVlfQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Uh4-1F3aeoy5k3hq8nVlfQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Uh4-1F3aeoy5k3hq8nVlfQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Object destructuring viarest</p>

<h4 id="toc_28"><strong>5.2 Even better, you can remove unwanted items!</strong></h4>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*43kFc4JJy8DSQiA_zQXZZA.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*43kFc4JJy8DSQiA_zQXZZA.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*43kFc4JJy8DSQiA_zQXZZA.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Object destructuring viarest</p>

<h3 id="toc_29">6. Spread properties forObjects</h3>

<p>Spread properties also look just like rest properties with three dots<code>...</code> but the difference is that you use spread to create (restructure) new objects.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Tip: the spread operator is used in the right side of the equals sign. The rest are used in the left-side of the equals sign.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*QmSUhdHQiXaXL9vdE27Djg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*QmSUhdHQiXaXL9vdE27Djg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*QmSUhdHQiXaXL9vdE27Djg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Object restructuring viaspread</p>

<h3 id="toc_30">7. RegExp Lookbehind Assertions</h3>

<p>This is an enhancement to the RegEx that allows us to ensure some string exists immediately <em>_before</em>_ some other string.</p>

<p>You can now use a group <code>(?&lt;=)</code> <u>(question mark, less than, equals)</u> to look behind for positive assertion.</p>

<p>Further, you can use <code>(?&lt;!)</code> <u>(question mark, less than, exclamation)</u>, to look behind for a negative assertion. Essentially this will match as long as the -ve assertion passes.</p>

<p><strong>Positive Assertion:</strong> Lets say we want to ensure that the <code>#</code> sign exists before the word <code>winning</code> (that is: <code>#winning</code>) and want the regex to return just the string winning. Here is how youd write it.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*MJuEF0dePb_NE8DHFm0XNw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*MJuEF0dePb_NE8DHFm0XNw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*MJuEF0dePb_NE8DHFm0XNw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018<code>(?&lt;=) for positive assertion</code></p>

<p><strong>Negative Assertion:</strong> Lets say we want to extract numbers from lines that have  signs and not $ signs before those numbers.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*e1N-waOWBc3ykLRFCIzXSA.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*e1N-waOWBc3ykLRFCIzXSA.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*e1N-waOWBc3ykLRFCIzXSA.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018(?&lt;!) for negative assertions</p>

<h3 id="toc_31"><strong>8.</strong> <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-regexp-unicode-property-escapes"><strong>RegExp Unicode PropertyEscapes</strong></a></h3>

<p>It was not easy to write RegEx to match various unicode characters. Things like <code>\w</code>, <code>\W</code>, <code>\d</code> etc only match English characters and numbers. But what about numbers in other languages like Hindi, Greek, and so on?</p>

<p>Thats where Unicode Property Escapes come in. <strong>It turns out Unicode adds metadata properties for each symbol (character) and uses it to group or characterize various symbols.</strong></p>

<p>For example, Unicode database groups all Hindi characters() under a property called <code>Script</code> with value <code>Devanagari</code> and another property called <code>Script_Extensions</code> with the same value <code>Devanagari</code>. So we can search for <code>Script=Devanagari</code> and get all Hindi characters.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devanagari_%28Unicode_block%29">Devanagari</a> can be used for various Indian languages like Marathi, Hindi, Sanskrit, and so on.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Starting in ECMAScript 2018, we can use <code>\p</code> to escape characters along with <code>{Script=Devanagari}</code> to match all those Indian characters. <strong>That is, we can use:</strong> <code>**\p{Script=Devanagari}**</code> <strong>in the RegEx to match all Devanagari characters.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*c-bRDN8WERPUYevc38jZMg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*c-bRDN8WERPUYevc38jZMg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*c-bRDN8WERPUYevc38jZMg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018showing\p</p>

<pre>//The following matches multiple hindi character
**/^\p{Script=Devanagari}+$/u.test(''); //true ** 
//PS:there are 3 hindi characters h</pre>

<p>Similarly, Unicode database groups all Greek characters under <code>Script_Extensions</code> (and <code>Script</code> ) property with the value <code>Greek</code>. So we can search for all Greek characters using <code>Script_Extensions=Greek</code> or <code>Script=Greek</code>.</p>

<p><strong>That is, we can use:</strong> <code>**\p{Script=Greek}**</code> <strong>in the RegEx to match all Greek characters.</strong></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*DwP_VN4VUp7osFQC-I9OsQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DwP_VN4VUp7osFQC-I9OsQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DwP_VN4VUp7osFQC-I9OsQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018showing\p</p>

<pre>//The following matches a single Greek character
**/\p{Script_Extensions=Greek}/u.test('');** // true</pre>

<p>Further, the Unicode database stores various types of Emojis under the boolean properties <code>Emoji</code>, <code>Emoji_Component</code>, <code>Emoji_Presentation</code>, <code>Emoji_Modifier</code>, and <code>Emoji_Modifier_Base</code> with property values as <code>true</code>. So we can search for all Emojis by simply selecting <code>Emoji</code> to be true.</p>

<p><strong>That is, we can use:</strong> <code>**\p{Emoji}**</code><strong>,</strong><code>**\Emoji_Modifier**</code> <strong>and so on to match various kinds of Emojis.</strong></p>

<p>The following example will make it all clear.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*DsQryeDlp8fAKBS8k_ohqw.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DsQryeDlp8fAKBS8k_ohqw.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DsQryeDlp8fAKBS8k_ohqw.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018showing how \p can be used for variousemojis</p>

<pre>//The following matches an Emoji character
/\p{Emoji}/u.test(''); //true</pre>

<pre>//The following fails because yellow emojis don't need/have Emoji_Modifier!
/\p{Emoji}\p{Emoji_Modifier}/u.test(''); //false</pre>

<pre>//The following matches an emoji character\p{Emoji} followed by \p{Emoji_Modifier}
/\p{Emoji}\p{Emoji_Modifier}/u.test(''); //true</pre>

<pre>//Explaination:
//By default the victory emoji is yellow color.
//If we use a brown, black or other variations of the same emoji, they are considered
//as variations of the original Emoji and are represented using two unicode characters.
//One for the original emoji, followed by another unicode character for the color.
//
//So in the below example, although we only see a single brown victory emoji,
//it actually uses two unicode characters, one for the emoji and another
// for the brown color.
//
//In Unicode database, these colors have Emoji_Modifier property.
//So we need to use both \p{Emoji} and \p{Emoji_Modifier} to properly and
//completely match the brown emoji.
/\p{Emoji}\p{Emoji_Modifier}/u.test(''); //true</pre>

<p><strong>Lastly, we can use capital &quot;P(</strong><code>\P</code> <strong>) escape character instead of small p (</strong><code>\p</code> )<strong>, to negate the matches.</strong></p>

<p>References:</p>

<ol>
<li> <a href="https://mathiasbynens.be/notes/es-unicode-property-escapes">_ECMAScript 2018 Proposal_</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://mathiasbynens.be/notes/es-unicode-property-escapes">_https://mathiasbynens.be/notes/es-unicode-property-escapes_</a></li>
</ol>

<h3 id="toc_32">8. Promise.prototype.finally()</h3>

<p><code>finally()</code> is a new instance method that was added to Promise. The main idea is to allow running a callback after either <code>resolve</code> or <code>reject</code> to help clean things up. The <code>**finally**</code> <strong>callback is called without any value and is always executed no matter what.</strong></p>

<p>Lets look at various cases.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*P1V6c1ncEjeCgtS6zzR0gg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*P1V6c1ncEjeCgtS6zzR0gg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*P1V6c1ncEjeCgtS6zzR0gg.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018finally() in resolvecase<img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*tSbu3kZCkoGpXaWDuP6MPA.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*tSbu3kZCkoGpXaWDuP6MPA.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*tSbu3kZCkoGpXaWDuP6MPA.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018finally() in rejectcase<img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*kB6Ar5YJoAlwwhFqzMGBGg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*kB6Ar5YJoAlwwhFqzMGBGg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*kB6Ar5YJoAlwwhFqzMGBGg.png" alt=""/>ECMASCript 2018finally() in Error thrown from Promisecase<img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*wCcbabJsS8UbFclumSISqg.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*wCcbabJsS8UbFclumSISqg.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*wCcbabJsS8UbFclumSISqg.png" alt=""/>**ECMAScript 2018Error thrown from within <strong>catch</strong> case**</p>

<h3 id="toc_33">9. Asynchronous Iteration</h3>

<p>This is an <em>extremely</em> useful feature. Basically it allows us to create loops of async code with ease!</p>

<p>This feature adds a new <strong>for-await-of</strong> loop that allows us to call async functions that return promises (or Arrays with a bunch of promises) in a loop. The cool thing is that the loop waits for each Promise to resolve before doing to the next loop.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/freeze/max/30/1*liLeNfWxZ3x1sqrVmRUdRQ.png?q=20" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*liLeNfWxZ3x1sqrVmRUdRQ.png" alt=""/><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*liLeNfWxZ3x1sqrVmRUdRQ.png" alt=""/>ECMAScript 2018Async Iterator via for-await-of</p>

<p>Thats pretty much it!</p>

<h4 id="toc_34">If this was useful, please click the clap  button down below a few times to show your support! </h4>

<h3 id="toc_35">My OtherPosts</h3>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/@rajaraodv/latest">_https://medium.com/@rajaraodv/latest_</a></p>

<h4 id="toc_36">Related ECMAScript 2015+posts</h4>

<ol>
<li> <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/check-out-these-useful-ecmascript-2015-es6-tips-and-tricks-6db105590377">_Check out these useful ECMAScript 2015 (ES6) tips and tricks_</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@rajaraodv/5-javascript-bad-parts-that-are-fixed-in-es6-c7c45d44fd81#.7e2s6cghy">_5 JavaScript Bad Parts That Are Fixed In ES6_</a></li>
<li><p><a href="https://medium.com/@rajaraodv/is-class-in-es6-the-new-bad-part-6c4e6fe1ee65#.4hqgpj2uv">_Is Class In ES6 The New Bad Part?_</a></p></li>
</ol>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/javascript?source=post">JavaScript</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/tech?source=post">Tech</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/programming?source=post">Programming</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/startup?source=post">Startup</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/web-development?source=post">Web Development</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[>  [ SimpRead](http://ksria.com/simpread/)   https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzAwMDU1MTE1OQ==&mid=2653548297&idx=1&sn=71fc309da16f1ed2b3d8b0d847f730a0&chksm=813a7e91b64df78734a2d155e79bedab66ebd078aed5d6ab3f01eb1b1b2a1d957f7c3ca204d5&scene=21#wechat_redirect]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15352960653784.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T23:07:45+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15352960653784.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<p></p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMFfEjD6rrQsA0WwRZRO3qIAxXqlMnWvILWiadCNXYPEa33aJO5PsaLDQ/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p>  Uber  Namba Taxi  Go </p>

<h2 id="toc_0"><strong></strong></h2>

<p> 2015   [1] </p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMxosd5hJ54PXZDDXnOFqibTIYtdsQGWtr4VTgYObn1zb2ULagtDvmMCg/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p> 15   SOS   </p>

<h2 id="toc_1"><strong></strong></h2>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<p> [2]</p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMdWKnMmHpaANJJicc67qKbmkgTPExVVtAl0y9MOeW1bjbRBavJOakx4w/0?wx_fmt=gif" alt=""/></p>

<p> OpenStreetMap Routeing MachineOSRM</p>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> OSRM </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<p></p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMoo1cEvvjvZgAuZ35V80cBJRJxyqHyfIGvQmDxJzDfMgUS2xuzzbNZg/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p>  OSRM <br/>
 <strong> 20 </strong> <br/>
</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong></strong> </p></li>
<li><p> 15 15 </p></li>
<li><p> GPS </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_2"><strong></strong></h2>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<p>  2  100  2000 </p>

<h2 id="toc_3"><strong></strong></h2>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> session  session id</p></li>
<li><p> ID </p></li>
</ol>

<p> 100  </p>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p>HTTP</p></li>
<li><p>WebSockets</p></li>
<li><p>TCP</p></li>
<li><p>UDP</p></li>
</ol>

<p><strong> UDP</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> 20 </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p>JSON</p></li>
<li><p>MsgPack</p></li>
<li><p>Protobuf</p></li>
</ol>

<p><strong> ProtoBuf</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMLibAuRGlVYtrciaab5sWnAvKNlqe2ia2EiawGkbC9UovDeibPfdU186oGrQ/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p> PB  TimYang  [3] </p>

<h2 id="toc_4"><strong></strong></h2>

<ol>
<li><p>42 </p></li>
<li><p> 20  IP </p></li>
<li><p> 62 </p></li>
</ol>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_5"><strong></strong></h2>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p> session id</p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> ID </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p>N </p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_6"><strong></strong></h2>

<ol>
<li><p> Percona  </p></li>
<li><p>Redis </p></li>
<li><p>Elasticsearch </p></li>
</ol>

<p> </p>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p>KD </p></li>
<li><p>R </p></li>
</ol>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p> N </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_7">KD <img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMNpwaMWy5okg9EBiaHFXPRZuX6SwT3ceQKficI55o5bCebUcPNDgicySKw/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></h2>

<p>KD   kd-tree  k-nearest  R-tree </p>

<h2 id="toc_8">R - </h2>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwMsYQQnUbcAwXMXR5drAE1gxHPEDeKnYfct9TgYtzyQjEnQxxicicPGicnw/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p>  N  </p>

<p> Go  [5]</p>

<p> 900   LRU   N  </p>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p><strong> R-tree </strong></p></li>
<li><p> session </p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_9"><strong></strong></h2>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p> UDP </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> -  Redis </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> -  LRU</p></li>
<li><p> r-tree</p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_10"><strong>HTTP </strong></h2>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p> session id</p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="toc_11"><strong></strong></h2>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li><p>UDP + Protobuf </p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p>R </p></li>
<li><p>LRU  n </p></li>
<li><p>OSRM </p>

<p><img src="http://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/8XkvNnTiapOMnaWlypBttlyEyfP2FFJwM4mXrsdcMWvsrRnGLjT82TuFmG7CMibUeb7ONlhHxRscdWpTD34nImNg/0?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p></li>
</ol>

<p> github [5]</p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<ol>
<li><p>GIF <a href="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*nI6cNApASR1mg6F5Sjgp7Q.gif">https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*nI6cNApASR1mg6F5Sjgp7Q.gif</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*KfGB1SARPoqOUtPtl4NNBg.gif">https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*KfGB1SARPoqOUtPtl4NNBg.gif</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://weibo.com/10503/24F1QpDmL">http://weibo.com/10503/24F1QpDmL</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/dhconnelly/rtreego">https://github.com/dhconnelly/rtreego</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/maddevsio/openfreecabs">https://github.com/maddevsio/openfreecabs</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://blog.maddevs.io/how-we-built-a-backend-system-for-uber-like-map-with-animated-cars-on-it-using-go-29d5dcd517a#.npo2x5788">https://blog.maddevs.io/how-we-built-a-backend-system-for-uber-like-map-with-animated-cars-on-it-using-go-29d5dcd517a#.npo2x5788</a></p></li>
</ol>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzAwMDU1MTE1OQ==&amp;mid=209153643&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=e0a64a8e7fcb8b43ceac85cc5782719f&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect">Uber </a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzAwMDU1MTE1OQ==&amp;mid=2653547609&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=cbb55ee823ddec9d98ef1fa984e001f6&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"> Uber  Postgres  MySQL?</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzAwMDU1MTE1OQ==&amp;mid=2653547482&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=13675fae5e037d720a9e9fb4a4861afd&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"> passport :  7  ( PPT)</a></p></li>
</ul>

<p></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ES modules: A cartoon deep-dive]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15352957865945.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T23:03:06+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15352957865945.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2018/03/es-modules-a-cartoon-deep-dive/">https://hacks.mozilla.org/2018/03/es-modules-a-cartoon-deep-dive/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>ES modules bring an official, standardized module system to JavaScript. It took a while to get here, thoughnearly 10 years of standardization work.</p>

<p>But the wait is almost over. With the release of Firefox 60 in May (<a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/developer/">currently in beta</a>), all major browsers will support ES modules, and the Node modules working group is currently working on adding ES module support to <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">Node.js</a>. And <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qR_b5gajwug">ES module integration for WebAssembly</a> is underway as well.</p>

<p>Many JavaScript developers know that ES modules have been controversial. But few actually understand how ES modules work.</p>

<p>Lets take a look at what problem ES modules solve and how they are different from modules in other module systems.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">What problem do modulessolve?</h3>

<p>When you think about it, coding in JavaScript is all about managing variables. Its all about assigning values to variables, or adding numbers to variables, or combining two variables together and putting them into another variable.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/01_variables.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/01_variables-500x178.png" alt=""/></a></strong></p>

<p>Because so much of your code is just about changing variables, how you organize these variables is going to have a big impact on how well you can code and how well you can maintain that code.</p>

<p>Having just a few variables to think about at one time makes things easier. JavaScript has a way of helping you do this, called scope. Because of how scopes work in JavaScript, functions cant access variables that are defined in other functions.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_01.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_01-500x292.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>This is good. It means that when youre working on one function, you can just think about that one function. You dont have to worry about what other functions might be doing to your variables.</p>

<p>It also has a downside, though. It does make it hard to share variables between different functions.</p>

<p>What if you do want to share your variable outside of a scope? A common way to handle this is to put it on a scope above you for example, on the global scope.</p>

<p>You probably remember this from the jQuery days. Before you could load any jQuery plug-ins, you had to make sure that jQuery was in the global scope.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_02.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_02-500x450.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>This works, but they are some annoying problems that result.</p>

<p>First, all of your script tags need to be in the right order. Then you have to be careful to make sure that no one messes up that order.</p>

<p>If you do mess up that order, then in the middle of running, your app will throw an error. When the function goes looking for jQuery where it expects iton the globaland doesnt find it, it will throw an error and stop executing.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_03.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_03-500x450.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>This makes maintaining code tricky. It makes removing old code or script tags a game of roulette. You dont know what might break. The dependencies between these different parts of your code are implicit. Any function can grab anything on the global, so you dont know which functions depend on which scripts.</p>

<p>A second problem is that because these variables are on the global scope, every part of the code thats inside of that global scope can change the variable. Malicious code can change that variable on purpose to make your code do something you didnt mean for it to, or non-malicious code could just accidentally clobber your variable.</p>

<h3 id="toc_1">How do moduleshelp?</h3>

<p>Modules give you a better way to organize these variables and functions. With modules, you group the variables and functions that make sense to go together.</p>

<p>This puts these functions and variables into a module scope. The module scope can be used to share variables between the functions in the module.</p>

<p>But unlike function scopes, module scopes have a way of making their variables available to other modules as well. They can say explicitly which of the variables, classes, or functions in the module should be available.</p>

<p>When something is made available to other modules, its called an export. Once you have an export, other modules can explicitly say that they depend on that variable, class or function.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_04.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/02_module_scope_04-500x450.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Because this is an explicit relationship, you can tell which modules will break if you remove another one.</p>

<p>Once you have the ability to export and import variables between modules, it makes it a lot easier to break up your code into small chunks that can work independently of each other. Then you can combine and recombine these chunks, kind of like Lego blocks, to create all different kinds of applications from the same set of modules.</p>

<p>Since modules are so useful, there have been multiple attempts to add module functionality to JavaScript. Today there are two module systems that are actively being used. CommonJS (CJS) is what Node.js has used historically. ESM (EcmaScript modules) is a newer system which has been added to the JavaScript specification. Browsers already support ES modules, and Node is adding support.</p>

<p>Lets take an in-depth look at how this new module system works.</p>

<h3 id="toc_2">How ES moduleswork</h3>

<p>When youre developing with modules, you build up a graph of dependencies. The connections between different dependencies come from any import statements that you use.</p>

<p>These import statements are how the browser or Node knows exactly what code it needs to load. You give it a file to use as an entry point to the graph. From there it just follows any of the import statements to find the rest of the code.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/04_import_graph.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/04_import_graph-500x291.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>But files themselves arent something that the browser can use. It needs to parse all of these files to turn them into data structures called Module Records. That way, it actually knows whats going on in the file.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/05_module_record.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/05_module_record-500x287.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>After that, the module record needs to be turned into a module instance. An instance combines two things: the code and state.</p>

<p>The code is basically a set of instructions. Its like a recipe for how to make something. But by itself, you cant use the code to do anything. You need raw materials to use with those instructions.</p>

<p>What is state? State gives you those raw materials. State is the actual values of the variables at any point in time. Of course, these variables are just nicknames for the boxes in memory that hold the values.</p>

<p>So the module instance combines the code (the list of instructions) with the state (all the variables values).</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/06_module_instance.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/06_module_instance-500x372.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>What we need is a module instance for each module. The process of module loading is going from this entry point file to having a full graph of module instances.</p>

<p>For ES modules, this happens in three steps.</p>

<ol>
<li> Constructionfind, download, and parse all of the files into module records.</li>
<li> Instantiation find boxes in memory to place all of the exported values in (but dont fill them in with values yet). Then make both exports and imports point to those boxes in memory. This is called linking.</li>
<li> Evaluation run the code to fill in the boxes with the variables actual values.</li>
</ol>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/07_3_phases.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/07_3_phases-500x184.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>People talk about ES modules being asynchronous. You can think about it as asynchronous because the work is split into these three different phasesloading, instantiating, and evaluatingand those phases can be done separately.</p>

<p>This means the spec does introduce a kind of asynchrony that wasnt there in CommonJS. Ill explain more later, but in CJS a module and the dependencies below it are loaded, instantiated, and evaluated all at once, without any breaks in between.</p>

<p>However, the steps themselves are not necessarily asynchronous. They can be done in a synchronous way. It depends on whats doing the loading. Thats because not everything is controlled by the ES module spec. There are actually two halves of the work, which are covered by different specs.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://tc39.github.io/ecma262/#sec-modules">ES module spec</a> says how you should parse files into module records, and how you should instantiate and evaluate that module. However, it doesnt say how to get the files in the first place.</p>

<p>Its the loader that fetches the files. And the loader is specified in a different specification. For browsers, that spec is the <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/#fetch-a-module-script-tree">HTML spec</a>. But you can have different loaders based on what platform you are using.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/07_loader_vs_es.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/07_loader_vs_es-500x286.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The loader also controls exactly how the modules are loaded. It calls the ES module methods<code>ParseModule</code>, <code>Module.Instantiate</code>, and <code>Module.Evaluate</code>. Its kind of like a puppeteer controlling the JS engines strings.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/08_loader_as_puppeteer.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/08_loader_as_puppeteer-500x330.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Now lets walk through each step in more detail.</p>

<h4 id="toc_3">Construction</h4>

<p>Three things happen for each module during the Construction phase.</p>

<ol>
<li> Figure out where to download the file containing the module from (aka module resolution)</li>
<li> Fetch the file (by downloading it from a URL or loading it from the file system)</li>
<li> Parse the file into a module record</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="toc_4">Finding the file and fetchingit</h4>

<p>The loader will take care of finding the file and downloading it. First it needs to find the entry point file. In HTML, you tell the loader where to find it by using a script tag.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/08_script_entry.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/08_script_entry-500x188.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>But how does it find the next bunch of modulesthe modules that <code>main.js</code> directly depends on?</p>

<p>This is where import statements come in. One part of the import statement is called the module specifier. It tells the loader where it can find each next module.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/09_module_specifier.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/09_module_specifier-500x105.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>One thing to note about module specifiers: they sometimes need to be handled differently between browsers and Node. Each host has its own way of interpreting the module specifier strings. To do this, it uses something called a module resolution algorithm, which differs between platforms. Currently, some module specifiers that work in Node wont work in the browser, but there is <a href="https://github.com/domenic/package-name-maps">ongoing work to fix this</a>.</p>

<p>Until thats fixed, browsers only accept URLs as module specifiers. They will load the module file from that URL. But that doesnt happen for the whole graph at the same time. You dont know what dependencies the module needs you to fetch until youve parsed the file and you cant parse the file until you fetched it.</p>

<p>This means that we have to go through the tree layer-by-layer, parsing one file, then figuring out its dependencies, and then finding and loading those dependencies.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/10_construction.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/10_construction-500x302.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>If the main thread were to wait for each of these files to download, a lot of other tasks would pile up in its queue.</p>

<p>Thats because when youre working in a browser, the downloading part takes a long time.</p>

<p><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/11_latency-500x270.png" alt=""/>Based on <a href="https://twitter.com/srigi/status/917998817051541504">this chart</a>.</p>

<p>Blocking the main thread like this would make an app that uses modules too slow to use. This is one of the reasons that the ES module spec splits the algorithm into multiple phases. Splitting out construction into its own phase allows browsers to fetch files and build up their understanding of the module graph before getting down to the synchronous work of instantiating.</p>

<p>This approachhaving the algorithm split up into phasesis one of the key differences between ES modules and CommonJS modules.</p>

<p>CommonJS can do things differently because loading files from the filesystem takes much less time than downloading across the Internet. This means Node can block the main thread while it loads the file. And since the file is already loaded, it makes sense to just instantiate and evaluate (which arent separate phases in CommonJS). This also means that youre walking down the whole tree, loading, instantiating, and evaluating any dependencies before you return the module instance.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/12_cjs_require.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/12_cjs_require-500x298.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The CommonJS approach has a few implications, and I will explain more about those later. But one thing that it means is that in Node with CommonJS modules, you can use variables in your module specifier. You are executing all of the code in this module (up to the <code>require</code> statement) before you look for the next module. That means the variable will have a value when you go to do module resolution.</p>

<p>But with ES modules, youre building up this whole module graph beforehand before you do any evaluation. This means you cant have variables in your module specifiers, because those variables dont have values yet.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/13_static_import.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/13_static_import-500x146.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>But sometimes it is really useful to use variables for module paths. For example, you might want to switch which module you load depending on what the code is doing or what environment it is running in.</p>

<p>To make this possible for ES modules, theres a proposal called <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-dynamic-import">dynamic import</a>. With it, you can use an import statement like <code>import(</code>${path}/foo.js<code>)</code>.</p>

<p>The way this works is that any file loaded using <code>import()</code> is handled as the entry point to a separate graph. The dynamically imported module starts a new graph, which is processed separately.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/14dynamic_import_graph.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/14dynamic_import_graph-500x389.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>One thing to note, thoughany module that is in both of these graphs is going to share a module instance. This is because the loader caches module instances. For each module in a particular global scope, there will only be one module instance.</p>

<p>This means less work for the engine. For example, it means that the module file will only be fetched once even if multiple modules depend on it. (Thats one reason to cache modules. Well see another in the evaluation section.)</p>

<p>The loader manages this cache using something called a <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/webappapis.html#module-map">module map</a>. Each global keeps track of its modules in a separate module map.</p>

<p>When the loader goes to fetch a URL, it puts that URL in the module map and makes a note that its currently fetching the file. Then it will send out the request and move on to start fetching the next file.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/15_module_map.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/15_module_map-500x170.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>What happens if another module depends on the same file? The loader will look up each URL in the module map. If it sees <code>fetching</code> in there, it will just move on to the next URL.</p>

<p>But the module map doesnt just keep track of what files are being fetched. The module map also serves as a cache for the modules, as well see next.</p>

<h4 id="toc_5">Parsing</h4>

<p>Now that we have fetched this file, we need to parse it into a module record. This helps the browser understand what the different parts of the module are.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/25_file_to_module_record.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/25_file_to_module_record-500x199.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Once the module record is created, it is placed in the module map. This means that whenever its requested from here on out, the loader can pull it from that map.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/25_module_map.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/25_module_map-500x239.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>There is one detail in parsing that may seem trivial, but that actually has pretty big implications. All modules are parsed as if they had <code>&quot;use strict&quot;</code> at the top. There are also other slight differences. For example, the keyword <code>await</code> is reserved in a modules top-level code, and the value of <code>this</code> is <code>undefined</code>.</p>

<p>This different way of parsing is called a parse goal. If you parse the same file but use different goals, youll end up with different results. So you want to know before you start parsing what kind of file youre parsingwhether its a module or not.</p>

<p>In browsers this is pretty easy. You just put <code>type=&quot;module&quot;</code> on the script tag. This tells the browser that this file should be parsed as a module. And since only modules can be imported, the browser knows that any imports are modules, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/26_parse_goal.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/26_parse_goal-500x311.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>But in Node, you dont use HTML tags, so you dont have the option of using a <code>type</code> attribute. One way the community has tried to solve this is by using an<code>.mjs</code> extension. Using that extension tells Node, this file is a module. Youll see people talking about this as the signal for the parse goal. The discussion is currently ongoing, so its unclear what signal the Node community will decide to use in the end.</p>

<p>Either way, the loader will determine whether to parse the file as a module or not. If it is a module and there are imports, it will then start the process over again until all of the files are fetched and parsed.</p>

<p>And were done! At the end of the loading process, youve gone from having just an entry point file to having a bunch of module records.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/27_construction.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/27_construction-500x406.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The next step is to instantiate this module and link all of the instances together.</p>

<h4 id="toc_6">Instantiation</h4>

<p>Like I mentioned before, an instance combines code with state. That state lives in memory, so the instantiation step is all about wiring things up to memory.</p>

<p>First, the JS engine creates a module environment record. This manages the variables for the module record. Then it finds boxes in memory for all of the exports. The module environment record will keep track of which box in memory is associated with each export.</p>

<p>These boxes in memory wont get their values yet. Its only after evaluation that their actual values will be filled in. There is one caveat to this rule: any exported function declarations are initialized during this phase. This makes things easier for evaluation.</p>

<p>To instantiate the module graph, the engine will do whats called a depth first post-order traversal. This means it will go down to the bottom of the graphto the dependencies at the bottom that dont depend on anything elseand set up their exports.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_01.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_01-500x206.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The engine finishes wiring up all of the exports below a moduleall of the exports that the module depends on. Then it comes back up a level to wire up the imports from that module.</p>

<p>Note that both the export and the import point to the same location in memory. Wiring up the exports first guarantees that all of the imports can be connected to matching exports.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_02.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_02-500x206.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>This is different from CommonJS modules. In CommonJS, the entire export object is copied on export. This means that any values (like numbers) that are exported are copies.</p>

<p>This means that if the exporting module changes that value later, the importing module doesnt see that change.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/31_cjs_variable.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/31_cjs_variable-500x113.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>In contrast, ES modules use something called live bindings. Both modules point to the same location in memory. This means that when the exporting module changes a value, that change will show up in the importing module.</p>

<p>Modules that export values can change those values at any time, but importing modules cannot change the values of their imports. That being said, if a module imports an object, it can change property values that are on that object.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_04.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/30_live_bindings_04-500x206.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The reason to have live bindings like this is then you can wire up all of the modules without running any code. This helps with evaluation when you have cyclic dependencies, as Ill explain below.</p>

<p>So at the end of this step, we have all of the instances and the memory locations for the exported/imported variables wired up.</p>

<p>Now we can start evaluating the code and filling in those memory locations with their values.</p>

<h4 id="toc_7">Evaluation</h4>

<p>The final step is filling in these boxes in memory. The JS engine does this by executing the top-level codethe code that is outside of functions.</p>

<p>Besides just filling in these boxes in memory, evaluating the code can also trigger side effects. For example, a module might make a call to a server.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/40_top_level_code.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/40_top_level_code-500x146.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Because of the potential for side effects, you only want to evaluate the module once. As opposed to the linking that happens in instantiation, which can be done multiple times with exactly the same result, evaluation can have different results depending on how many times you do it.</p>

<p>This is one reason to have the module map. The module map caches the module by canonical URL so that there is only one module record for each module. That ensures each module is only executed once. Just as with instantiation, this is done as a depth first post-order traversal.</p>

<p>What about those cycles that we talked about before?</p>

<p>In a cyclic dependency, you end up having a loop in the graph. Usually, this is a long loop. But to explain the problem, Im going to use a contrived example with a short loop.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/41_cjs_cycle.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/41_cjs_cycle-500x224.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Lets look at how this would work with CommonJS modules. First, the main module would execute up to the require statement. Then it would go to load the counter module.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/41_cyclic_graph.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/41_cyclic_graph-500x281.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The counter module would then try to access <code>message</code> from the export object. But since this hasnt been evaluated in the main module yet, this will return undefined. The JS engine will allocate space in memory for the local variable and set the value to undefined.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/42_cjs_variable_2.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/42_cjs_variable_2-500x113.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Evaluation continues down to the end of the counter modules top level code. We want to see whether well get the correct value for message eventually (after main.js is evaluated), so we set up a timeout. Then evaluation resumes on <code>main.js</code>.</p>

<p><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/43_cjs_cycle.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/43_cjs_cycle-500x224.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>The message variable will be initialized and added to memory. But since theres no connection between the two, it will stay undefined in the required module.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/44_cjs_variable_2.png"><img src="https://2r4s9p1yi1fa2jd7j43zph8r-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/files/2018/03/44_cjs_variable_2-500x216.png" alt=""/></a></strong></p>

<p>If the export were handled using live bindings, the counter module would see the correct value eventually. By the time the timeout runs, <code>main.js</code>s evaluation would have completed and filled in the value.</p>

<p>Supporting these cycles is a big rationale behind the design of ES modules. Its this three-phase design that makes them possible.</p>

<h3 id="toc_8">Whats the status of ESmodules?</h3>

<p>With the release of Firefox 60 in early May, all major browsers will support ES modules by default. Node is also adding support, with a <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/modules">working group</a> dedicated to figuring out compatibility issues between CommonJS and ES modules.</p>

<p>This means that youll be able to use the script tag with <code>type=module</code>, and use imports and exports. However, more module features are yet to come. The <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-dynamic-import">dynamic import proposal</a> is at Stage 3 in the specification process, as is <a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-import-meta">import.meta</a> which will help support Node.js use cases, and the <a href="https://github.com/domenic/package-name-maps">module resolution proposal</a> will also help smooth over differences between browsers and Node.js. So you can expect working with modules to get even better in the future.</p>

<h2 id="toc_9">Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>Thank you to everyone who gave feedback on this post, or whose writing or discussions informed it, including Axel Rauschmayer, Bradley Farias, Dave Herman, Domenic Denicola, Havi Hoffman, Jason Weathersby, JF Bastien, Jon Coppeard, Luke Wagner, Myles Borins, Till Schneidereit, Tobias Koppers, and Yehuda Katz, as well as the members of the WebAssembly community group, the Node modules working group, and TC39.</p>

<h2 id="toc_10">About <a href="http://code-cartoons.com">Lin Clark</a></h2>

<p>Lin is an engineer on the Mozilla Developer Relations team. She tinkers with JavaScript, WebAssembly, Rust, and Servo, and also draws code cartoons.</p>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="http://code-cartoons.com">code-cartoons.com</a></li>
<li>  <a href="http://twitter.com/linclark">@linclark</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/author/lclarkmozilla-com/">More articles by Lin Clark</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[13 Noteworthy Points from Googles JavaScript Style Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15352953904391.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T22:56:30+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15352953904391.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/google-publishes-a-javascript-style-guide-here-are-some-key-lessons-1810b8ad050b">https://medium.freecodecamp.org/google-publishes-a-javascript-style-guide-here-are-some-key-lessons-1810b8ad050b</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*ouYvMzYuksK-IH1BPNKD0A.jpeg" alt=""/></p>

<p>For anyone who isnt already familiar with it, <a href="https://google.github.io/styleguide/jsguide.html">Google puts out a style guide</a> for writing JavaScript that lays out (what Google believes to be) the best stylistic practices for writing clean, understandable code.</p>

<p>These are not hard and fast rules for writing valid JavaScript, only proscriptions for maintaining consistent and appealing style choices throughout your source files. This is particularly interesting for JavaScript, which is a flexible and forgiving language that allows for a wide variety of stylistic choices.</p>

<p>Google and <a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript">Airbnb</a> have two of the most popular style guides out there. Id definitely recommend you check out both of them if you spend much time writing JS.</p>

<p>The following are thirteen of what I think are the most interesting and relevant rules from Googles JS Style Guide.</p>

<p>They deal with everything from hotly contested issues (tabs versus spaces, and the controversial issue of how semicolons should be used), to a few more obscure specifications which surprised me. They will definitely change the way I write my JS going forward.</p>

<p>For each rule, Ill give a summary of the specification, followed by a supporting quote from the style guide that describes the rule in detail. Where applicable, Ill also provide an example of the style in practice, and contrast it with code that does not follow the rule.</p>

<h4 id="toc_0">Use spaces, nottabs</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Aside from the line terminator sequence, the ASCII horizontal space character (0x20) is the only whitespace character that appears anywhere in a source file. This implies that Tab characters are <strong>not</strong> used for indentation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The guide later specifies you should use two spaces (not four) for indentation.</p>

<pre>// bad
function foo() {
let name;
}
// bad
function bar() {
let name;
}
// good
function baz() {
let name;
}</pre>

<h4 id="toc_1">Semicolons ARErequired</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Every statement must be terminated with a semicolon. Relying on automatic semicolon insertion is forbidden.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Although I cant imagine why anyone is opposed to this idea, the consistent use of semicolons in JS is becoming the new spaces versus tabs debate. Googles coming out firmly here in the defence of the semicolon.</p>

<pre>// bad
let luke = {}
let leia = {}
[luke, leia].forEach(jedi => jedi.father = 'vader')</pre>

<pre>// good
let luke = {};
let leia = {};
[luke, leia].forEach((jedi) => {
  jedi.father = 'vader';
});</pre>

<h4 id="toc_2">Dont use ES6 modules(yet)</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Do not use ES6 modules yet (i.e. the <code>export</code> and <code>import</code> keywords), as their semantics are not yet finalized. Note that this policy will be revisited once the semantics are fully-standard.</p>
</blockquote>

<pre>// Don't do this kind of thing yet:</pre>

<pre><code>//------ lib.js ------
</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_3">Horizontal alignment is discouraged (but not forbidden)</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>This practice is permitted, but it is <strong>generally discouraged</strong> by Google Style. It is not even required to <u>maintain</u> horizontal alignment in places where it was alreadyused.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Horizontal alignment is the practice of adding a variable number of additional spaces in your code, to make certain tokens appear directly below certain other tokens on previous lines.</p>

<pre>// bad
{
  tiny:   42,  
  longer: 435, 
};</pre>

<pre>// good
{
  tiny: 42, 
  longer: 435,
};</pre>

<h4 id="toc_4">Dont use varanymore</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Declare all local variables with either <code>_const_</code> or <code>_let_</code>. Use const by default, unless a variable needs to be reassigned. The <code>_var_</code> keyword must not beused.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I still see people using <code>var</code> in code samples on StackOverflow and elsewhere. I cant tell if there are people out there who will make a case for it, or if its just a case of old habits dying hard.</p>

<pre>// bad
var example = 42;</pre>

<pre>// good
let example = 42;</pre>

<h4 id="toc_5">Arrow functions are preferred</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Arrow functions provide a concise syntax and fix a number of difficulties with <code>_this_</code>. Prefer arrow functions over the <code>_function_</code> keyword, particularly for nested functions</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ill be honest, I just thought that arrow functions were great because they were more concise and nicer to look at. Turns out they also serve a pretty important purpose.</p>

<pre>// bad
[1, 2, 3].map(function (x) {
  const y = x + 1;
  return x * y;
});
// good
[1, 2, 3].map((x) => {
  const y = x + 1;
  return x * y;
});</pre>

<h4 id="toc_6">Use template strings instead of concatenation</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Use template strings (delimited with ```) over complex string concatenation, particularly if multiple string literals are involved. Template strings may span multiplelines.</p>
</blockquote>

<pre>// bad
function sayHi(name) {
  return 'How are you, ' + name + '?';
}
// bad
function sayHi(name) {
  return ['How are you, ', name, '?'].join();
}
// bad
function sayHi(name) {
  return `How are you, ${ name }?`;
}
// good
function sayHi(name) {
  return `How are you, ${name}?`;
}</pre>

<h4 id="toc_7"><strong>Dont use line continuations for longstrings</strong></h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Do not use <u>line continuations</u> (that is, ending a line inside a string literal with a backslash) in either ordinary or template string literals. Even though ES5 allows this, it can lead to tricky errors if any trailing whitespace comes after the slash, and is less obvious toreaders.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interestingly enough, this is a rule that Google and Airbnb disagree on (heres <a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript#strings--line-length">Airbnbs spec</a>).</p>

<p>While Google recommends concatenating longer strings (as shown below) Airbnbs style guide recommends essentially doing nothing, and allowing long strings to go on as long as they need to.</p>

<pre>// bad (sorry, this doesn't show up well on mobile)
const longString = 'This is a very long string that \
    far exceeds the 80 column limit. It unfortunately \
    contains long stretches of spaces due to how the \
    continued lines are indented.';</pre>

<pre>// good
const longString = 'This is a very long string that ' + 
    'far exceeds the 80 column limit. It does not contain ' + 
    'long stretches of spaces since the concatenated ' +
    'strings are cleaner.';</pre>

#### for of is the preferred type of forloop

> With ES6, the language now has three different kinds of `for` loops. All may be used, though `for`-`of` loops should be preferred when possible.

This is a strange one if you ask me, but I thought Id include it because it is pretty interesting that Google declares a preferred type of `for` loop.

I was always under the impression that `for... in` loops were better for objects, while `for... of` were better suited to arrays. A right tool for the right job type situation.

While Googles specification here doesnt necessarily contradict that idea, it is still interesting to know they have a preference for this loop in particular.

#### Dont useeval()

> Do not use `eval` or the `Function(...string)` constructor (except for code loaders). These features are potentially dangerous and simply do not work in CSP environments.

The [MDN page](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/eval) for `eval()` even has a section called Dont use eval!

<pre>// bad
`let obj = { a: 20, b: 30 };
let propName = getPropName();  // returns "a" or "b"
eval( 'var result = obj.' + propName );`</pre>

<pre>// good
`let obj = { a: 20, b: 30 };
let propName = getPropName();  // returns "a" or "b"
let result = obj[ propName ];  //  obj[ "a" ] is the same as obj.a`</pre>

<h4 id="toc_8">Constants should be named in ALL_UPPERCASE separated by underscores</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Constant names use <code>CONSTANT_CASE</code>: all uppercase letters, with words separated by underscores.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If youre absolutely sure that a variable shouldnt change, you can indicate this by capitalizing the name of the constant. This makes the constants immutability obvious as it gets used throughout your code.</p>

<p>A notable exception to this rule is if the constant is function-scoped. In this case it should be written in camelCase.</p>

<pre>// bad
const number = 5;</pre>

<pre>// good
const NUMBER = 5;</pre>

<h4 id="toc_9">One variable per declaration</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Every local variable declaration declares only one variable: declarations such as <code>let a = 1, b = 2;</code> are notused.</p>
</blockquote>

<pre>// bad
let a = 1, b = 2, c = 3;</pre>

<pre>// good
let a = 1;
let b = 2;
let c = 3;</pre>

<h4 id="toc_10">Use single quotes, not doublequotes</h4>

<blockquote>
<p>Ordinary string literals are delimited with single quotes (<code>&#39;</code>), rather than double quotes(<code>&quot;</code>).</p>

<p>Tip: if a string contains a single quote character, consider using a template string to avoid having to escape thequote.</p>
</blockquote>

<pre>// bad
let directive = "No identification of self or mission."</pre>

<pre>// bad
let saying = `'Say it ain\u0027t so.';`</pre>

<pre>// good
let directive = 'No identification of self or mission.';</pre>

<pre>// good
let saying = `Say it ain't so`;</pre>

<h4 id="toc_11">A finalnote</h4>

<p>As I said in the beginning, these are not mandates. Google is just one of many tech giants, and these are just recommendations.</p>

<p>That said, it is interesting to look at the style recommendations that are put out by a company like Google, which employs a lot of brilliant people who spend a lot of time writing excellent code.</p>

<p>You can follow these rules if you want to follow the guidelines for Google compliant source codebut, of course, plenty of people disagree, and youre free to brush any or all of this off.</p>

<p>I personally think there are plenty of cases where Airbnbs spec is more appealing than Googles. No matter the stance you take on these particular rules, it is still important to keep stylistic consistency in mind when write any sort of code.</p>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/javascript?source=post">JavaScript</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/google?source=post">Google</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/web-development?source=post">Web Development</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/programming?source=post">Programming</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/tagged/tech?source=post">Tech</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15352773081191.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T17:55:08+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15352773081191.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://tech.youzan.com/you-zan-tong-ri-zhi-ping-tai-chu-tan/">https://tech.youzan.com/you-zan-tong-ri-zhi-ping-tai-chu-tan/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<pre><code>2015HawkTrack
</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_0"></h4>

<p> ( 1.1  1.5  9  2.4T )</p>

<p></p>

<p> KafkaFlumeScribeChukwaELK   </p>

<h4 id="toc_1"></h4>

<p> 2-1  <img src="http://7xtb4n.com1.z0.glb.clouddn.com/track-pic-2-1.png" alt=""/>  2-1 </p>

<p> flume  logstash  (kafka ) TrackStormSpark  HDFS  ElasticSearch  Hawk </p>

<h4 id="toc_2"></h4>

<p></p>

<h5 id="toc_3">3.1 </h5>

<p> 1  rsyslog  logstash 2  flume-ng</p>

<h6 id="toc_4">3.1.1</h6>

<p><img src="http://7xtb4n.com1.z0.glb.clouddn.com/track-pic-3-1.png" alt=""/>  3-1  1</p>

<p> ( nginx phpfpm ) nginx  rsyslog  local0 logstash  local0  topic  3-1 </p>

<h6 id="toc_5">3.1.2</h6>

<p>Flume NG  Failover Flume NG Agent Collector  Store  Agent  SourceChannel  Sink Agent<br/>
Source Channel <br/>
Channel Source  Chanel<br/>
Sink Channel  Channel </p>

<p> Agent  3-2:</p>

<p><img src="http://7xtb4n.com1.z0.glb.clouddn.com/track-pic-3-2.png" alt=""/></p>

<p> 3-2  2</p>

<p> kafka  topic  topic :</p>

<pre><code>&lt;158&gt;yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss host/ip level[pid]: topic=track.**** {&quot;type&quot;:&quot;error&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;redis connection refused&quot;,&quot;platform&quot;:&quot;java/go/php&quot;,&quot;level&quot;:&quot;info/warn/error&quot;,&quot;app&quot;:&quot;appName&quot;,&quot;module&quot;:&quot;com.youzan.somemodule&quot;,&quot;detail&quot;:&quot;any things you want here&quot;}

</code></pre>

<p> PHP Server PHP  SDKPHP  Flume  Java Server SDK( logback <code>TrackAppender</code>) Dubbox  logback.xml  appender  topic  Flume  ( GoNode.JSPython ) Flume </p>

<p> 3-2 <code>TrackSink</code> Flume  KafkaSink KafkaSink  topic  Sink  topic  topic </p>

<p>Flume  Supervisor  Flume  Failover </p>

<p>3.2 </p>

<p> 24  HDFS kafka :</p>

<pre><code>  1
  2(1.5/)
  3topic
  4
  5O(1)
  6broker

</code></pre>

<p>3.3 </p>

<p></p>

<p> topic  topic </p>

<pre><code>1ElasticSearch
2
3
4
5

</code></pre>

<p></p>

<h4 id="toc_6"></h4>

<p>:</p>

<pre><code>1elasticsearchelasticsearchSDK
2(logstashflumekafkaelasticsearch)
3
4elasticsearch
5
6FlumeUDP
7HDFSKafkaHDFS
8

</code></pre>

<h4 id="toc_7"></h4>

<p></p>

<p> 2  ( CTO) </p>

<p>, : <a href="http://job.youzan.com/" title=""></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MySQL8 Authentication plugin Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15348499248375.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-21T19:12:04+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15348499248375.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="http://samchu.logdown.com/posts/7425945-mysql8-authentication-plugin-change">http://samchu.logdown.com/posts/7425945-mysql8-authentication-plugin-change</a></p>

<p><img src="media/15348499248375/15348503868862.jpg" alt=""/></p>
</blockquote>

<p> MySQL  8 , , XD</p>

<p>  MySQL <code>mysql_native_password</code>,  8.0  <code>caching_sha2_password</code>, , ,  SQL  (Navicat)  ...</p>

<p>!!</p>

<pre><code>Authentication plugin &#39;caching_sha2_password&#39; cannot be loaded: dlopen(/usr/local/mysql/lib/plugin/caching_sha2_password.so, 2): image not found
</code></pre>

<h2 id="toc_0">1 : ,  JDBC </h2>

<ol>
<li> JDBC  runtime &#39;mysql:mysql-connector-java:8.0.11&#39;</li>
<li> driver-class-name ,  Loading class `com.mysql.jdbc.Driver&#39;. This is deprecated. ,  com.mysql.cj.jdbc.Driver</li>
<li>JDBC URL <code>allowPublicKeyRetrieval=true</code></li>
</ol>

<p>,  JDBC <code>caching_sha2_password</code></p>

<h2 id="toc_1">2 : </h2>

<p> Docker , <code>--default-authentication-plugin=mysql_native_password</code></p>

<pre><code>docker run --name askask-mysql -e MYSQL_DATABASE=askask -e MYSQL_ROOT_PASSWORD=1qaz2wsx -p 3306:3306 -d mysql --default-authentication-plugin=mysql_native_password
</code></pre>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_2">3 : </h2>

<pre><code class="language-sql">CREATE DATABASE rep2 CHARACTER SET utf8mb4 COLLATE utf8mb4_unicode_ci;
CREATE USER &#39;dev&#39;@&#39;%&#39; IDENTIFIED WITH mysql_native_password BY &#39;Dev.1234&#39;;
ALTER USER &#39;dev&#39;@&#39;%&#39; IDENTIFIED WITH mysql_native_password BY &#39;password&#39;;
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON rep2.* TO &#39;dev&#39;@&#39;%&#39;;
</code></pre>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[**The Path to Becoming a Software Architect**]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15344302211672.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-16T22:37:01+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15344302211672.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/the-path-to-becoming-a-software-architect-de53f1cb310a">https://medium.com/@nvashanin/the-path-to-becoming-a-software-architect-de53f1cb310a</a></p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin" title="Go to the profile of Nikolay Ashanin">Nikolay Ashanin</a> | Oct 1, 2017</p>

<p>Lead Software Engineer at EPAM Systems. Interested in software architecture and team management.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*JFdmWD8_X5gpCjNVaqILgQ.png" alt=""/>Image source: monumentvalleygame</p>

<p>Have you ever wondered what career opportunities a developer has? What directions are open, beyond what horizons to grow. And most importantly, where are developers beyond the age of 45? Is there a developer among your friends who is over 45? I personally know several developers beyond this age and many of them are hardcore programmers who even saw punch cards back in the day.</p>

<p><strong>There are several career paths a developer might take:</strong></p>

<p> The first and obvious one is to <strong>grow in the area in which you are working</strong>. If you are a junior developer, then just grow to middle, then senior and lead roles.</p>

<p> <strong>Transition to another technology stack</strong>. Actually, a big number of developers moved into the mobile area when iOS and Android OS gained ground.</p>

<p> <strong>Grow into a manager role</strong>. As a developer, the greatest staffing issue I saw was the shortage of competent managers. Clever managers are expensive, hence they are scarce. If the manager has a technical background, that will allow him to be on the same wavelength with the developers.</p>

<p> <strong>Become a software architect</strong>. This direction will be considered in this series of articles.</p>

<p> <strong>Get out of IT</strong>. Sometimes this happens. It is never too late to do what you like to do.</p>

<h3 id="toc_0">Article series</h3>

<ol>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/the-path-to-becoming-a-software-architect-de53f1cb310a">The Path to Becoming a Software Architect</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/stakeholders-in-software-architecture-6d18f36250f9">Stakeholders in Software Architecture</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/types-of-software-architects-aa03e359d192">Types of Software Architects</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/quality-attributes-in-software-architecture-3844ea482732">Quality attributes in Software Architecture. Part I</a></li>
<li> TBD Quality attributes in Software Architecture. Part II</li>
<li> TBD Software Architect. Diagrams and documentation</li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/certificates-in-software-architecture-6b18e0102fe7">Certificates in Software Architecture</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://medium.com/@nvashanin/books-in-software-architecture-6ad974e524ce">Books in Software Architecture</a></li>
<li> TBD Software Architect. Design vs Architecture</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="toc_1">Yes, This Was MyPath</h3>

<p>In the past 8 years, I have worked with Java EE, then moved to iOS, and became a team lead. I managed various developer teams, including Android, and Web stacks. Created the architecture of the network layer for several services developed by the company, with sockets and REST API. I became acquainted with the managerial role and the prospect of growing in this direction while in the position of team lead for over two years. In my next role, my goal is to grow as a software architect.</p>

<p>For most developers, the function of the architect on the project is often unclear, so in this series of articles, I will try to find the answers to these related questions. Who is an architect, what is the scope of responsibilities, and how to grow in this direction and outline and action plan for myself and beginners wanting to move along this path.</p>

<h3 id="toc_2"><strong>Who Can Benefit fromThis?</strong></h3>

<p>This series of articles will help you if you belong to one of the following categories:</p>

<p> <strong>IT developer or engineer</strong>. You are still growing as a developer, but you are looking ahead and planning your career. Even if the goals are initially vague, a person who consciously sets strategic goals will reach them much quicker than a person who does not plan where she is heading.</p>

<p> <strong>Team leader, lead software engineer</strong>. You are at the highest stage of the software development discipline. To grow further, you have a choice to either learn one more stack of technologies, pursue a career outside software engineering, or to become a software architect.</p>

<p> <strong>Software architect</strong>. You recently took this position, or have been working in this field for a long time. Perhaps one of the main qualities of such a specialist is the understanding that there are always areas that a person does not know and that the learning process is continuous.</p>

<p> <strong>IT manager</strong>. Although you are a manager, you understand perfectly well that you should at least approximately understand what your subordinates or colleagues are doing. The acute problem of management is the technical incompetence of the manager in the field in which he or she is managing.</p>

<h3 id="toc_3"><strong>Who is an Architect?</strong></h3>

<p>Before moving on to more specific questions, it is necessary to define the software architect role and it responsibilities.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>A <strong>software architect</strong> is a software expert who makes high-level design choices and dictates technical standards, including software coding standards, tools, and platforms. The leading expert is referred to as the chief architect. (Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, s.v. Software architect, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_architect">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_architect</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Like most high-level positions, there are no clear criteria that define this role. However, it is possible to define a number of responsibilities and qualities that contribute to the career of the architect.</p>

<p>First, lets consider the <strong>characteristics of the architect</strong>:</p>

<p> <strong>Communicability</strong>. Having talked with many software architects, I heard that it is one of the most important characteristic of this specialist. During the working day, they have to talk with customers in the language of business, managers of all levels, business analysts and developers. If you have a natural charisma and you know how to convince people, then this will be a huge plus, as it is very important to explain your actions correctly. Architects are laconic, eloquent and competent speakers. The software architects with whom I spoke have highly developed skills in communication and persuasion. Another reason why this characteristic is most important is that the architect in this role participates in most discussion making processes, and often compromises must be reach that are acceptable and beneficial for all involved parties.</p>

<p> <strong>Broad and deep technical knowledge</strong>. This should be obvious since one cannot become a software architect with a medical background. In addition, the architect usually has knowledge in several technological stacks at a decent level, and should have a good understanding of a few other ones. The software architect should also be prepared to compose a large number of technical documentation, reports and diagrams.</p>

<p> <strong>Responsibility</strong>. You should understand that architect decisions are usually the most expensive. Therefore, a person in this position should take the most responsible approach to his work and to the decisions made. If the developers error costs a couple days of work of one person, then the architects mistake can cost person-years on complex projects!</p>

<p> <strong>Stress resistance</strong>. You will have to make decisions because in this role, you will be asked to do so and you will need response. You will be working with different people from different areas, and you will have to deal with rapidly changing demands or even with changing business environments. Therefore, it is necessary to be ready for stress and to look for some ways to escape negative emotions. Work is always more pleasant when it brings pleasure. So if you choose this role only for the money, then think again.</p>

<p> <strong>Management skills</strong>. This includes both organizational and leadership skills. The ability to lead a team, which may be distributed and composed of very different specialists, is essential.</p>

<p> <strong>Analytic skills</strong>. Even if a specialist has a wide erudition in technology, he has tried many things on his own or participated in projects of various types, this does not guarantee that he can easily change the style of thinking to architect. One of the most important tasks is the ability to represent an abstract problem in the form of some finite real object of the system, which developers are already evaluating, designing and developing. Great communications skills are essential to clearly represent the abstraction in the form of the final system to the members of the team and the customer. It will be necessary to clearly communicate to both business and development, what is still to be done.</p>

<p>If we talk about the responsibilities of the architect, then here is the perfect example from 19th century about bridge construction. At that time, the tests of the newly constructed bridge were the following: the key group of engineers, architects and workers stood under the bridge while the first vehicles were on it. Thus, they staked their lives upon the construction and the strength of the structure. So if there is a questionwhat is the responsibility of the software architect on the project? The answer is, he is responsible for everything.</p>

<p>If you give up loud and beautiful phrases, then the architects work includes:</p>

<p> Identifying the stakeholders on the project.</p>

<p> Identifying business requirements and requirements of the stakeholders on the project.</p>

<p> Designing the entire system based on the received requirements.</p>

<p> Choosing the system architecture and each individual component of this system at a high level.</p>

<p> Choosing the technologies for the implementation of each component and connections between the components.</p>

<p> Architectural review. Yes, yes, it exists.</p>

<p> Code-review.</p>

<p> Writing project documentation and its support.</p>

<p> Creating unified development standards in the company.</p>

<p> Controlling the architecture during the next iteration of the system release.</p>

<p>This is only a subset of the software architects responsibilities. The most important responsibility is complete technical support of the project from the moment of inception, through product release, to development of enhancements. And supporting the next releases. It will be necessary to switch a lot between different tasks during the working day.</p>

<h3 id="toc_4"><strong>How to Become a Software Architect?</strong></h3>

<p>To begin with, it is important to define milestone goals that lead to achieving your strategic goal of becoming a software architect. For me, such <strong>goals for the next six months</strong> are:</p>

<p> <strong>Understand and try several technological stacks</strong>. My current knowledge is concentrated in the field of iOS. It is necessary to try Android, several server languages, to start python, and refresh Java EE skills. The architect is a full-stack developer, so it is important to have a broad technical knowledge.</p>

<p> <strong>Reading literature</strong>. It is important to determine the most valuable books and articles that will help to grow in this direction. Usually the most effective way to find such literature is ask other professionals in this field for their recommendation. In one of the future articles, I plan to give you such a list of literature.</p>

<p> <strong>Find a mentor</strong>. It is desirable to find a software architect at your current place of employment. It is always easier to get experience from a trained specialist than to start considering a certain area from scratch. It is important to be prepared to ask good questions from your mentor.</p>

<p> <strong>Study courses/obtain certificates</strong>. There are many courses and certificates available, but only a few are worth their money, and the higher level courses cost a lot of money. Personally, I have attended the architectural courses of Luxoft (<a href="http://www.luxoft-training.com/it-course/ARC-001/">http://www.luxoft-training.com/it-course/ARC-001/</a>), which have proven to be a worthy investment. It is extremely important that the lecturer of the course be a professional in this field and be able to answer questions. As for certificates, before starting, it is best to understand whether there are authoritative certification systems for architects and whether it is worthwhile obtaining the certification. This point I will discuss in a future article of this series.</p>

<p>One of the most important parts is a clear and stable plan review. What has been done, what should be reviewed, and where to accelerate or which goal to remove as useless.</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">Check Your Readiness Level</h3>

<p>If you are interested in this introductory article from the series on how to become a software architect, or if you suddenly have thoughts to try this path, it is worth making sure that you really want it.</p>

<p>Firstly, people are afraid of everything new. A new position, new kind of stress, as opposed to the comfortable status quo. Of course, the choice is not always unambiguous and depends on how much you are willing to change something in your life. At the same time, it can depend not only on you, but also on the family, your financial commitments, parents and other factors.</p>

<p>Secondly, this path takes several years. The process of becoming a software architect does not happen overnight. As a team lead, I realized what to do and how to deal with stress only a year after I was appointed to an official position. At the same time six months before that, I performed it unofficially. One software architect I know said that he understood what his responsibilities are 18 months after he was promoted to this role. Such intervals of time are normal and you need to understand whether you are ready to move in this direction. Even if you do not have a stable plan ready, it is better to start taking small steps that move you ahead, rather than remaining in the same place.</p>

<p>Standing in the same place in IT is a synonym for stagnation and personal fetters in life.</p>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.com/tag/software-development?source=post">Software Development</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.com/tag/software-architecture?source=post">Software Architecture</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.com/tag/software-engineering?source=post">Software Engineering</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.com/tag/management?source=post">Management</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://medium.com/tag/software?source=post">Software</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[InnoDB]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15342611126076.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-14T23:38:32+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15342611126076.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p> <a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/R3yuitWpHHGWxsUcE0qIRQ">https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/R3yuitWpHHGWxsUcE0qIRQ</a></p>

<p> 58    2018-08-14</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MjM5ODYxMDA5OQ==&amp;mid=2651961431&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=4f46fbada3d99ca6cf74b305d06c1ac6&amp;chksm=bd2d0d8b8a5a849d8cb5a616c957abde7a6485cd2624372b84a5459eed081bd95429a09572f8&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect">InnoDB </a> InnoDB  case<strong></strong> InnoDB <strong></strong><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>

<p></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong>Concurrency Control</p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Locking</p></li>
<li><p>Multi Versioning</p></li>
</ul>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p></p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p>  </p>

<p><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>S</strong>hare Locks S  S </p></li>
<li><p>e<strong>X</strong>clusive Locks X  X </p></li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<p><u> select </u></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p>1</p>

<p>2</p>

<p>3</p>

<p><img src="https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/YrezxckhYOxqYZaEWwXRwibTg8vNtNIPG7Hfiat5wx6D353IIxWmOKJawOcJ84QFu2WYicElTUeTsy9Am0MQZpcyg/640?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p>1.  V0</p>

<p>2. T1  clone  V1</p>

<p>3. T2  V0 </p>

<p>4. T3 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong></strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong></strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong></strong></p></li>
</ul>

<p><u></u></p>

<p> InnoDB </p>

<p><strong>redo, undo,</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p> InnoDB    redo undo rollback segment</p>

<p><strong> redo</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p> ACID <strong></strong></p>

<p> redo <strong></strong></p>

<p><u><strong></strong></u></p>

<p> redo </p>

<p><strong></strong>redo  ACID </p>

<p><strong> undo</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p> undo  undo </p>

<p><u></u></p>

<p><u> <strong>insert </strong>undo  PK(ROW</u>ID)_</p>

<p><u> <strong>delete/update </strong>undo  row</u></p>

<p><u> buffer </u></p>

<p><strong></strong>undo  ACID </p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p> undo </p>

<p>undo  InnoDB  MVCC </p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p>t(id PK, name);</p>

<p></p>

<p>1, shenjian</p>

<p>2, zhangsan</p>

<p>3, lisi</p>

<p><img src="https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/YrezxckhYOxqYZaEWwXRwibTg8vNtNIPGhicRJvTpNR0lzoZticJ8BLAWEAbMzC9pgZ0yYZ29IdWKekoqiaxuf6Neg/640?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p>start trx;</p>

<p>delete (1, shenjian);</p>

<p>update set(3, lisi) to (3, xxx);</p>

<p>insert (4, wangwu);</p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/YrezxckhYOxqYZaEWwXRwibTg8vNtNIPGLSOOJDKXmdHqkgdeXFibUI0bNhuQN0qb0E5BiaR00gwaS0IU7vzz0tSA/640?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p>(1)  (1, shenjian) </p>

<p>(2)  (3, lisi) </p>

<p>(3) PK(4) </p>

<p> rollback undo </p>

<p><u> undo </u></p>

<p><img src="https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/YrezxckhYOxqYZaEWwXRwibTg8vNtNIPGMuEql2dsc2US7uwMaP9fBic9dPeod96CqwcaN6Qd75icNssicNHkaaMzw/640?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p><img src="https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_png/YrezxckhYOxqYZaEWwXRwibTg8vNtNIPGry9tyIxsGfql43eEhWoYHg6ibS1S4th1dMjj6JKTwt8XWnIt0iaS71jw/640?wx_fmt=png" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p><strong>InnoDB</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MjM5ODYxMDA5OQ==&amp;mid=2651961428&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=31a9eb967941d888fbd4bb2112e9602b&amp;chksm=bd2d0d888a5a849e7ebaa7756a8bc1b3d4e2f493f3a76383fc80f7e9ce7657e4ed2f6c01777d&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"> InnoDB</a>InnoDB <strong></strong>Multi Version Concurrency Control, MVCC MVCC </p>

<p>MVCC   </p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong> MySQL</strong> <strong> InnoDB</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p> undo </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2)  MySQL  InnoDB </p>

<p>InnoDB  row </p>

<p>(1)<strong>DB_TRX_ID</strong>6  ID</p>

<p>(2)<strong>DB_ROLL_PTR</strong>7  undo </p>

<p>(3)<strong>DB_ROW_ID</strong>6  ID</p>

<p><strong>InnoDB</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p>snapshotselect </p>

<p><strong></strong>Snapshot Read<strong></strong>Consistent Nonlocking Read InnoDB </p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><strong> select</strong> <strong></strong></p>

<p> select </p>

<p>select * from t where id&gt;2;</p>

<p></p>

<p>select * from t where id&gt;2 <strong>lock in share mode</strong>;</p>

<p>select * from t where id&gt;2 <strong>for update</strong>;</p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p>(1) <strong></strong><strong></strong></p>

<p>(2) <strong></strong><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>

<p>(3)<strong>redo </strong> ACID </p>

<p>(4)<strong>undo </strong></p>

<p>(5)InnoDB  <strong>MVCC</strong>  undo </p>

<p>(6)InnoDB </p>

<p>(7)InnoDB  select </p>

<p><u> MySQL5.6</u></p>

<p> InnoDB <strong></strong></p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p></p>

<p><a href="http://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MjM5ODYxMDA5OQ==&amp;mid=2651961428&amp;idx=1&amp;sn=31a9eb967941d888fbd4bb2112e9602b&amp;chksm=bd2d0d888a5a849e7ebaa7756a8bc1b3d4e2f493f3a76383fc80f7e9ce7657e4ed2f6c01777d&amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect">InnoDB5 </a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netflix]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15342609315238.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-14T23:35:31+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15342609315238.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/articles/tips-for-high-availability">http://www.infoq.com/cn/articles/tips-for-high-availability</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Netflix  5000  1.25 </p>

<p> Netflix Spinnaker  Spinnaker </p>

<h2 id="toc_0"></h2>

<p> AWS </p>

<p></p>

<p> Spinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/12111-1533721785047.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/12111-1533721785047.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_1"></h2>

<p></p>

<p> Spinnaker Spinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/12612-1533721785745.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/12612-1533721785745.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_2"></h2>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<p>Spinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/413-1533721787411.jpeg"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/413-1533721787411.jpeg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_3"></h2>

<p> Spinnaker  cron  cron </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/8914-1533721784600.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/8914-1533721784600.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_4"> Chaos Monkey</h2>

<p>Chaos Monkey  Netflix Chaos Monkey Chaos Monkey  Netflix Chaos Monkey Chaos Monkey </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/7415-1533721786316.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/7415-1533721786316.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_5"></h2>

<p></p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/5616-1533721787677.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/5616-1533721787677.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p> Kayenta Spinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/5217-1533721786866.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/5217-1533721786866.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_6"></h2>

<p></p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/4618-1533721785369.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/4618-1533721785369.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_7"></h2>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_8"></h2>

<p></p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/3819-1533721783682.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/3819-1533721783682.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<p>Spinnaker  Page application owner </p>

<h2 id="toc_9"></h2>

<p></p>

<p> Spinnaker  Server Group  Rollback  ASG ASGSpinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/320-1533721786579.jpeg"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/320-1533721786579.jpeg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_10"></h2>

<p> </p>

<p>Spinnaker Spinnaker  ASG Spinnaker Spinnaker </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/8221-1533721786054.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/8221-1533721786054.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_11"></h2>

<p> Netflix Slack  Spinnaker  Slack </p>

<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/infoq.content.live.0/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/6422-1533721787145.png"><img src="https://res.infoq.com/articles/tips-for-high-availability/zh/resources/6422-1533721787145.png" alt=""/></a></p>

<h2 id="toc_12"></h2>

<p>  </p>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_13"></h2>

<p> Netflix</p>

<h2 id="toc_14"></h2>

<p> Netflix </p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/@NetflixTechBlog/tips-for-high-availability-be0472f2599c">https://medium.com/@NetflixTechBlog/tips-for-high-availability-be0472f2599c</a></p>

<p><input type="hidden"></p>

<p></p>

<h3 id="toc_15"><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/articles/how-netflix-does-failovers-7-minutes-flat?utm_source=infoq&amp;utm_medium=related_content_link&amp;utm_campaign=relatedContent_undefined_clk">Netflix  7 </a></h3>

<h3 id="toc_16"><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/articles/mysql-high-availability-at-github?utm_source=infoq&amp;utm_medium=related_content_link&amp;utm_campaign=relatedContent_undefined_clk">GitHub  MySQL </a></h3>

<h3 id="toc_17"><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/articles/netflix-what-happens-when-you-press-play?utm_source=infoq&amp;utm_medium=related_content_link&amp;utm_campaign=relatedContent_undefined_clk">Netflix:   </a></h3>

<h3 id="toc_18"><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/news/2018/05/netflix-zuul2?utm_source=infoq&amp;utm_medium=related_content_link&amp;utm_campaign=relatedContent_undefined_clk">Netflix  API  Zuul 2</a></h3>

<h3 id="toc_19"><a href="http://www.infoq.com/cn/presentations/the-practice-of-open-source-distributed-monitoring-cat-system?utm_source=infoq&amp;utm_medium=related_content_link&amp;utm_campaign=relatedContent_undefined_clk"> CAT </a></h3>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Reasons and 101 Bugfixes  Why You Should Use Hibernate 5.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15342604876749.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-14T23:28:07+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15342604876749.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<p>Hibernate 5.3 is available for a little more than 3 months now, and last week, the team released the <a href="http://in.relation.to/2018/07/24/hibernate-orm-533-final-out/">3rd maintenancerelease</a>. So, its about time to take a closer look at the new version.</p>

<p>In addition to more than 100 bug fixes, Hibernate 5.3 includes a few features and improvements that might motivate you to update your current project.</p>

<h2 id="toc_0">Improved Memory consumption</h2>

<p>Lets start with probably the best reason to update to Hibernate 5.3: It consumes less memory than the previous versions.</p>

<p>The improvement was triggered by an interesting discussion in the<a href="https://discourse.hibernate.org/t/batch-fetch-style-recommendations/631">Hibernate forum</a>. A user reported that he tried to migrate his application from Hibernate 3.6 to 5.3. During the migration, he recognized that the memory consumption of Hibernates SessionFactory went up to 950MB.</p>

<p>The issue was caused by the size and number of <u>EntityLoader</u>s that Hibernate instantiated. It was fixed in 2 steps:</p>

<ol>
<li> <a href="https://hibernate.atlassian.net/browse/HHH-12556">HHH-12556</a>  Similar <u>EntityLoader</u>s now share some internal data structures. This reduced the memory consumption of the application by ~50%.
The fix was backported to Hibernate 5.2.18. So, if youre using Hibernate 5.2 and dont want to upgrade to 5.3, you should at least update to 5.2.18.</li>
<li> <a href="https://hibernate.atlassian.net/browse/HHH-12558">HHH-12558</a>  Hibernate supports a bunch of different lockmodes with specific loaders. In the past, it instantiated all loaders eagerly. Hibernate 5.3 only instantiates the 2 most common ones and loads all others lazily.</li>
</ol>

<p>At the end of the discussion, the user who reported the issue wrote that the improved Hibernate version only used ~ 250MB. So, for his application, these two changes reduced the memory consumption by ~70%.</p>

<p>I obviously cant promise that it will be equally effective for your project. However, the reported improvement is so enormous that you should at least give it a try.</p>

<h2 id="toc_1">JPA 2.2 compliance</h2>

<p>Hibernate 5.3.0 is the first version thats fully compliant with JPA 2.2. However, because the support for all the interesting features was already added in Hibernate 5.0, 5.1 and 5.2, and I already wrote extensive tutorials about all of them, I will not dive any deeper into this topic.</p>

<p>If youre not already familiar with JPA 2.2, you can read more about it in the following articles:</p>

<ul>
<li>  <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/map-date-time-api-jpa-2-2/">How To Map The Date And Time API with JPA 2.2</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/get-query-results-stream-hibernate-5/">How to get query results as a Stream with Hibernate 5.2</a>(please note that Hibernate now also offers the <u>getResultStream</u> method)</li>
<li>  <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-2-2s-new-stream-method-and-how-you-should-not-use-it/">JPA 2.2s new getResultStream() method and how you should NOT use it</a></li>
<li>  <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-2-2-repeatable-annotations/">JPA 2.2 Introduces @Repeatable Annotations</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="toc_2">Small Improvements</h2>

<p>Learn more about primary keys<meta itemprop="thumbnailUrl" content="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/wp-content/plugins/wp-youtube-lyte/lyteThumbs.php?origThumbUrl=%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fqn9SbW44rQ8%2Fmaxresdefault.jpg"><meta itemprop="embedURL" content="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qn9SbW44rQ8"><meta itemprop="uploadDate" content=""></p>

<p><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/qn9SbW44rQ8/0.jpg" alt=""/><br/>
Watch this video on YouTube<meta itemprop="description" content="">](<a href="https://youtu.be/qn9SbW44rQ8">https://youtu.be/qn9SbW44rQ8</a>)</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/qn9SbW44rQ8"></a><a href="http://bit.ly/2cUsid8">Follow me on YouTube</a> to not miss any new videos.</p>

<h3 id="toc_3">Implicit ID generator definitions</h3>

<p>If you <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-generate-primary-keys/">generate your primary key values</a>, youre probably aware of Hibernates <u>@SequenceGenerator</u> and <u>@TableGenerator</u> annotations. You can use them to define which sequence or table Hibernate shall use to generate the primary key value.</p>

<p>Here is a typical example of a primary key mapping that tells Hibernate to use the database sequence <u>author</u>seq_ to generate the unique primary key values.</p>

<pre><code class="language-java">@Entity
public class Author {
 
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue(strategy = GenerationType.SEQUENCE, generator = &quot;author_seq&quot;)
    @SequenceGenerator(name=&quot;author_seq&quot;, sequenceName = &quot;author_seq&quot;)
    private Long id;
 
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>The mapping definition consists of 2 parts:</p>

<ol>
<li> The <u>@GeneratedValue</u> annotation defines which generation strategy Hibernate shall use and references a custom generator.</li>
<li> The <u>@SquenceGenerator</u> annotation specifies the generator and tells Hibernate the name of the sequence you want to use.</li>
</ol>

<p>As you can see in the code snippet, I use the same name for the generator and the database sequence. Thats a pretty common and verbose mapping.</p>

<p>If your mapping looks the same, I have good news for you: You no longer need to define the generator if your database sequence or table has the same name as your <u>@SequenceGenerator</u> or <u>@TableGenerator</u>.</p>

<p>That enables me to shorten the previous mapping and to remove the <u>@SequenceGenerator</u> definition.</p>

<pre><code class="language-java">@Entity
public class Author {
 
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue(strategy = GenerationType.SEQUENCE, generator = &quot;author_seq&quot;)
    private Long id;
 
    ...
}
</code></pre>

<h3 id="toc_4">Support for MySQL 8 SKIP LOCKED and NOWAIT</h3>

<p>MySQL 8.0.1 added the SKIP LOCKED and NOWAIT feature to provide different options to handle locked rows during read-operations. The MySQL Server team explained them in great detail on their blog:<a href="https://mysqlserverteam.com/mysql-8-0-1-using-skip-locked-and-nowait-to-handle-hot-rows/">MySQL 8.0.1: Using SKIP LOCKED and NOWAIT to handle hot rows.</a></p>

<p>Heres a quick description of both features:</p>

<ul>
<li>  SKIP LOCKED enables you to perform a non-deterministic read that skips all locked rows. That means that locked rows are missing in your result set.</li>
<li>  If you require a deterministic read but dont want to wait for the locks to be released, you can use the NOWAIT feature. It causes your query to fail immediately if any records in your result set are locked.</li>
</ul>

<p>The <u>MySQL8Dialect</u> included in Hibernate 5.3 supports both these features so that you can use them in your queries.</p>

<p>Learn more about AttributeConverter<meta itemprop="thumbnailUrl" content="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/wp-content/plugins/wp-youtube-lyte/lyteThumbs.php?origThumbUrl=%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FTIeeRif4ocg%2Fmaxresdefault.jpg"><meta itemprop="embedURL" content="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TIeeRif4ocg"><meta itemprop="uploadDate" content=""></p>

<p><img src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/TIeeRif4ocg/0.jpg" alt=""/><br/>
Watch this video on YouTube<meta itemprop="description" content="">](<a href="https://youtu.be/TIeeRif4ocg">https://youtu.be/TIeeRif4ocg</a>)</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/TIeeRif4ocg"></a><a href="http://bit.ly/2cUsid8">Follow me on YouTube</a> to not miss any new videos.</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">Apply AttributeConverter when calling a function</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-21-how-to-implement-type-converter/">AttributeConverters</a> provide a standardized, easy way to define the mapping of a Java type. You can either use them to add support for unsupported classes or to customize the <a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-21-type-converter-better-way-to/">mapping of an already supported Java type</a>.</p>

<p>The following code snippet shows an example from my<a href="https://www.thoughts-on-java.org/jpa-tips-map-duration-attribute/">JPA Tip: How to map a Duration attribute</a>. JPA 2.2 doesnt provide a mapping for_java.time.Duration_ objects. If you want to map such an object, you can use this <u>AttributeConverter</u> to map it to a <u>Long</u>.</p>

<pre><code class="language-java">@Converter(autoApply = true)
public class DurationConverter implements AttributeConverter&lt;Duration, Long&gt; {
     
    Logger log = Logger.getLogger(DurationConverter.class.getSimpleName());
 
    @Override
    public Long convertToDatabaseColumn(Duration attribute) {
        log.info(&quot;Convert to Long&quot;);
        return attribute.toNanos();
    }
 
    @Override
    public Duration convertToEntityAttribute(Long duration) {
        log.info(&quot;Convert to Duration&quot;);
        return Duration.of(duration, ChronoUnit.NANOS);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>After you applied the AttributeConverter to an attribute or automatically applied them to all attributes of a specific type, it gets transparently used:</p>

<ul>
<li>  during all lifecycle state transitions,</li>
<li>  to map the result of a query and</li>
<li>  when used in path expressions in a <a href="http://JPQL">JPQL</a> or CriteriaQuery.</li>
</ul>

<p>However, for whatever reason, the usage of converted attribute values as function parameters is explicitly undefined.</p>

<p>Previous Hibernate versions didnt convert the attribute value if you referenced it as a function parameter. This changed with Hibernate 5.3.2. It now converts the attribute value before it provides it as a function parameter.</p>

<h2 id="toc_6">Support for Java 9 and preparations for Java 11</h2>

<p>Beginning with Hibernate 5.3.0, all Hibernate modules specify a <a href="https://blog.codefx.org/java/java-module-system-tutorial/">Java 9 module</a> name following the pattern_org.hibernate.orm.${module-name}_, e.g., the hibernate-core module defines the name_org.hibernate.orm.core._</p>

<p>The Hibernate team also updated the dependencies, prepared the build process and run their test suite with the latest JDK 11 build. So, we can hope for a smooth transition to JDK11.</p>

<h2 id="toc_7">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Should you update to Hibernate 5.3?</p>

<p>You probably already know my answer. Its a clear yes! Especially the improved memory consumption is a great reason to do the update.</p>

<p>However, please keep in mind that every update has its risks and that you obviously shouldnt update any project dependency without testing it carefully.</p>

<p>So, what about you? Did you already update your application to use Hibernate 5.3 or will you update it in the near future?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Java ]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15340923334107.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-13T00:45:33+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15340923334107.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p> <a href="http://calvin1978.blogcn.com/articles/javatuning.html"></a></p>
</blockquote>

<p></p>

<p><a href="http://www.hdb.com/party/bajzu.html"></a><strong></strong>.  <strong>66  PPT</strong></p>

<p>1.4 :<a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgRySAAAAAAAC42ozG7w4w912.pdf">Java  V1.4.pdf</a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/08/02/CoFCGVgHnLkAAAAAAAETKzIbY-c369.jpg" title="01"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/08/02/CoFCGVgHnLkAAAAAAAETKzIbY-c369.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_0"></h3>

<p> JMeter </p>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li>  JVM </li>
<li>  </li>
<li>  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHnPMAAAAAAADXW3vnM8I951.jpg" title="03"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHnPMAAAAAAADXW3vnM8I951.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHnSkAAAAAAACnv2fHcK0833.jpg" title="04"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHnSkAAAAAAACnv2fHcK0833.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_1"></h3>

<p></p>

<ol>
<li> </li>
<li>  JMH</li>
<li>  JDK </li>
</ol>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/00/D1/CpCCFVgHnewAAAAAAAC4WC08BEA045.jpg" title="06"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/00/D1/CpCCFVgHnewAAAAAAAC4WC08BEA045.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/04/D0/CoFCGVgHnjEAAAAAAADZwUFf8O8583.jpg" title="07"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/04/D0/CoFCGVgHnjEAAAAAAADZwUFf8O8583.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHnokAAAAAAACCHhzO17w957.jpg" title="08"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHnokAAAAAAACCHhzO17w957.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/08/02/CoFCGVgHn6YAAAAAAADGggFLBi0755.jpg" title="09"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/08/02/CoFCGVgHn6YAAAAAAADGggFLBi0755.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_2">JVM </h3>

<p>JIT JVM  GC </p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHoB4AAAAAAACR8THhKLc792.jpg" title="21"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHoB4AAAAAAACR8THhKLc792.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHqVoAAAAAAADQAgCkMkE356.jpg" title="30"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgHqVoAAAAAAADQAgCkMkE356.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_3"></h3>

<p> GC </p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHoGwAAAAAAADk5iKpsPw033.jpg" title="34"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp02/M00/08/EF/CpAZrVgHoGwAAAAAAADk5iKpsPw033.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_4"></h3>

<p> JMC Btrace </p>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/00/D1/CpCCFVgHoZMAAAAAAAC3Llc-Yyw623.jpg" title="51"><img src="http://files.blogcn.com/wp04/M00/00/D1/CpCCFVgHoZMAAAAAAAC3Llc-Yyw623.jpg" alt=""/></a></p>

<h3 id="toc_5"></h3>

<p> R    JVM </p>

<p> Chembo() PPT </p>

<h3 id="toc_6"> PPT </h3>

<p><a href="http://files.blogcn.com/wp06/M00/00/ED/CpCCFVgRySAAAAAAAC42ozG7w4w912.pdf">Java  V1.4.pdf</a>, by , </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ | ]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15340916506798.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-13T00:34:10+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15340916506798.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/41646747">https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/41646747</a> </p>

<p><br/>
 APaaSASPaaS</p>

<p>PaaSAPM </p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://pic3.zhimg.com/v2-448a9367fbd6d700321a85583097d054_r.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> ArchSummit  PPT </p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-fa07d74992a0f5f565dbfd12a5391aa5_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<ul>
<li>  </li>
<li>  </li>
<li>   </li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-bc3a8986b6158bf772dd6b2e711a40e2_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> </p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-d99a3a7f381fc64de0f3d43c07146cea_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>5  4 </p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-02129e0f6899ad2c991f93f0383154b2_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><strong>  </strong><br/>
 IDC  weblogic  KCXP  KCBP  Oracle  EMC </p>

<p> IOE <br/>
 10  100W 3 </p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-5816971a16e8e2b907617e72c69a7da4_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> 30~50  1~2 </p>

<p> 2.0</p>

<p> 2.0  SLB  ECS  web  weblogic</p>

<p> Oracle  50  RDS  50  50  ID  1000  20 </p>

<p> 120W  /  2000W  /  7  2  1 </p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-6413443e5520ec8dfcae02e4bc97e5bd_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> 2.0  3  </p>

<p>2016   3.0</p>

<p> 3  3.0  2.0  buffer  50 </p>

<p> 2.0  2  2016  4  2.0  </p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-ffb278a398ee7a6d383025d3e579863f_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>2017  4.0 </p>

<p> 3.0 </p>

<p> 340  480  4  4~8  2017 </p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-49d8eaa19b1a017f36edd9ae65199acb_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p></p>

<p><br/>
</p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-f2286374d36cbd661878e12ee089f9de_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><strong></strong><br/>
     TA <br/>
</p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-d4ef2511eaa39b96914d43002786fcab_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><br/>
<strong> </strong></p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-f23511243bdad6525dd807da0e29b059_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> SLB I  P APM</p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-4eb0d4d090cc40b5e6bf09278b050c95_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>web  APP  ODS  </p>

<p> MaxComputeDTSQuickBI  ETL </p>

<p><strong></strong></p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-485378d5ee7e8316cd128b96ce0c0b68_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> SOFARPCSOFARPC  Spring  Spring  bean  Mock</p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-425203cfc2fd880b46e9e9848f3ff95e_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> SOFARPC  Guardian  Netflix  Hystrix </p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-ecf0fe4b534d372dc36043fc9e913ba5_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> mPaaS mPaaS  OSGi APP  SOFARPCmpaaS  SOFA  APP  mPaaS </p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-6b965f3bb1d5779437aa9d4bd751a8f8_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> <br/>
  </p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-53adc1cb5473ec83cb8ab8e1ee178c47_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><strong></strong><br/>
 log4j  logstash  flume  IO IO IO  40% </p>

<p> IO  Spring AOP </p>

<p> + </p>

<p> 1~2 </p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-43b32c2fb751fef1fb7ec0c1d3be9af5_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>    </p>

<p> traceId </p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-010c471293822c6edf53598a35e63545_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>  </p>

<p> SOFARPC  APM <br/>
 </p>

<p> SDK </p>

<p></p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-44b14c158d5433d1b6d3bdac49166903_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> P2P  Mock  Mock  Mock  mockito when..thenReturn. </p>

<p> Mock  Mock  Mock  Mock  Mock  Mock </p>

<p>Mock  </p>

<p> Mock  Mock  Mock </p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-83de9c9141a351da2a3119e50308ffce_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p> Mock  Mock  Mock <br/>
<strong>Mock </strong><br/>
 Mock   Mock  Mock  Mock  bsh  groovy Mock </p>

<p> Mock </p>

<p> Mock  mock  Mock <strong> Mock </strong></p>

<p> Mock    Mock  Mock </p>

<p> Mock   Mock  Mock <strong></strong></p>

<p><img src="https://pic1.zhimg.com/80/v2-0d2850203e49e03b0be9e89235823248_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p>   3 </p>

<p>      ID </p>

<p> TCC  TCC <br/>
 TCC  TCC  TCC <br/>
 TCC  TRY  Confirm  Cancel  TRYConfirm  Cancel  ID    ID ID  RPC  ID  ID ID <br/>
 </p>

<p><img src="https://pic2.zhimg.com/80/v2-b70c0af13fbc3a1e8019e0aaf8dbb0f8_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><br/>
  buffer backlog  buffer</p>

<p> UI UI  UI  UI <br/>
 DevOps  JekinsJiraWiki  DevOps  Pipeline  IaaS  DevOps </p>

<p><img src="https://pic3.zhimg.com/80/v2-87efc79672b19d697a03793aa134e1f6_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

<p><br/>
 I  P   SOFA  SOFARPC</p>

<p><img src="https://pic4.zhimg.com/80/v2-6cd70446d9f8bc3be06edb1fcd87e57b_hd.jpg" alt=""/></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git]]></title>
    <link href="http://panlw.github.io/15340911901321.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-13T00:26:30+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://panlw.github.io/15340911901321.html</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.ctolib.com/topics-133950.html">https://www.ctolib.com/topics-133950.html</a></p>

<p><a href="https://thecuriousdev.org/useful-git-tips-commands/">https://thecuriousdev.org/useful-git-tips-commands/</a></p>
</blockquote>

<pre><code> | viktor
 | 
</code></pre>

<p>Git  Git </p>

<h2 id="toc_0">Git diff</h2>

<p></p>

<pre>git diff branch1 branch</pre>

<p></p>

<p> HEAD</p>

<pre>git diff --cached</pre>

<p> git diff </p>

<p></p>

<p>Git </p>

<pre>git rm path/to/file --cached</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git rm file -f</pre>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_1">Git reset</h2>

<p></p>

<pre>git reset</pre>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<pre>git reset --hard</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git reset --mixed</pre>

<p> git reset  HEAD</p>

<pre>git reset --soft</pre>

<p></p>

<p> git reset </p>

<pre>git reset --hard COMMIT_ID</pre>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_2">Git stash</h2>

<p> git stash  git stash pop </p>

<pre>git stash --include-untracked</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git stash list</pre>

<p></p>

<h2 id="toc_3"></h2>

<p>Git </p>

<pre>git log --graph --decorate --oneline</pre>

<p>git log  HEAD ID </p>

<pre>git show COMMIT_ID/HEAD/BRANCH</pre>

<p></p>

<p></p>

<pre>git blame path/to/file</pre>

<p></p>

<p> git diff  HEAD </p>

<pre>git diff HEAD HEAD~2</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git log --patch</pre>

<p> apple </p>

<pre>git log --grep apples --oneline</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git log HEAD~5..HEAD^ --oneline</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>git log branch_name..master --oneline</pre>

<h2 id="toc_4"></h2>

<p></p>

<p> git </p>

<pre>git commit --amend</pre>

<p></p>

<p> git  (rebase origin  master </p>

<pre>git rebase -i origin/master</pre>

<p></p>

<pre>1 pick 80f2a48 Add feature X
2 squash 2c74ea2 Add junit tests for feature X
3 squash 4k81nm5 Bugfix for feature X</pre>

<p> Add feature X </p>

<p></p>

<pre>git revert COMMIT_ID</pre>

<p></p>

<p> git  git reflog </p>

<h2 id="toc_5">cherry-pick</h2>

<p></p>

<pre>git cherry-pick COMMIT_ID</pre>

<h2 id="toc_6"> </h2>

<p> git  git </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
